<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Familiar letters. Vol. II. Containing thirty six letters, / by the Right Honourable John, late Earl of Rochester. Printed from his original papers. With letters and speeches, by the late Duke of Buckingham, the Honourable Henry Savile, Esq; Sir George Etherridge, to several persons of honour. And letters by several eminent hands.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 222 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 111 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05024</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1748</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R182833</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51784624</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 51784624</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175034</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05024)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175034)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2710:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Familiar letters. Vol. II. Containing thirty six letters, / by the Right Honourable John, late Earl of Rochester. Printed from his original papers. With letters and speeches, by the late Duke of Buckingham, the Honourable Henry Savile, Esq; Sir George Etherridge, to several persons of honour. And letters by several eminent hands.</title>
                  <author>Rochester, John Wilmot, Earl of, 1647-1680.</author>
                  <author>Savile, Henry, 1642-1687.</author>
                  <author>Brown, Thomas, 1663-1704.</author>
                  <author>Buckingham, George Villiers, Duke of, 1628-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 207 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Rich. Wellington ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Bound and filmed following R1745A (Familiar letters vol. I).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Universität Göttingen Bibliothek.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English letters --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Love-letters --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:175034:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books printed for, and ſold by</hi> R. Wellington.</head>
            <p>THe Hiſtory of <hi>Polybius</hi> the <hi>Megalopolitan,</hi> containing an Account of the Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the whole World, but principally of the <hi>Roman</hi> People, in 3 Vol. tranſlated by Sir <hi>Henry Sheers</hi> and Mr. <hi>Dryden,</hi> the like never before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant: Price ten Shillings.</p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of the Nature and Faculties of Man, in ſeveral <hi>Eſſays,</hi> with ſome Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the Occurrences of Human Life; by <hi>Tim. Nourſe,</hi> Gent. price 4 Shillings.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory and Novels of the late Ingenious Mrs. <hi>Behn</hi> collected into one Vol. viz. <hi>Oroonoko,</hi> or <hi>The Royal Slave:</hi> The Fair Jilt, or <hi>Prince Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin: Agves de Caſtro,</hi> or <hi>The Force of Generous Love:</hi> The Lover's Watch, or the Art of Make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Love: The Ladies Looking-glaſs to dreſs themſelves by: The Lucky Miſtake: Memoirs of the Court of the King of <hi>Bantam:</hi> The Nun, or the Perjur'd Beauty: The Adventures of the Black Lady. Theſe 3 never before publiſh'd, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with her Life and Memoirs, written by one of the <hi>Fair Sex;</hi> interwoven with ſeveral Love-Letters, which paſſed beeween her and <hi>Myn Heer Van Bruin,</hi> a <hi>Dutch</hi> Merchant, the third Edition enlarged; price 5 Shillings.</p>
            <p>A brief and eaſy Method to underſtand the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Hiſtory, with an exact Chron. of the Reign of the Emperors, and an Account of the moſt Eminent Authors, when they flouriſh'd; and an Abridgment of the <hi>Roman</hi> Antiquities and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, by way of Dialogue, for the uſe of the Duke of <hi>Burgundy:</hi> Done out of <hi>French,</hi> with large Additions, by Mr. <hi>Tho. Brown;</hi> price two Shillings.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175034:1"/>
            <p>Familiar Letters: Vol. II.</p>
            <p>CONTAINING Thirty Six LETTERS, By the Right Honourable <hi>John,</hi> late Earl of Rochester. <hi>Printed from his Original Papers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH Letters and Speeches, BY The late Duke of <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham,</hi> The Honourable <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Savile,</hi> Eſq, Sir <hi>George Etheridge,</hi> to ſeveral Perſons of Honour.</p>
            <p>And <hi>LETTERS,</hi> By ſeveral Eminent Hands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Rich. Wellington,</hi> at the <hi>Lute</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:175034:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175034:2"/>
            <head>TO Sir <hi>EDWIN SADLER,</hi> B<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. OF <hi>Temple-Dinſley,</hi> in <hi>Hertfordſhire.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THo' ſome may accuſe me of Preſumption, in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering this <hi>Collection of Letters</hi> to your Patronage, without ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Honour of your Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance; yet, conſidering the <hi>Merits</hi> of the <hi>Noble Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors</hi> concern'd in it, and your own, all Impartial Judges will acquit me, and applaud my Choice. Since not to know the Intereſt you, Sir, have in the Republick of Letters, and what our Country has ow'd to the happy Counſels of your Great
<pb facs="tcp:175034:3"/>
Anceſtors, is to be equally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with our Hiſtory, and with all thoſe whom you Honour with any Intimacy. In the firſt we ſhall find, what a conſiderable Figure Sir <hi>Ralph Sadler,</hi> your Noble Progenitor, once made in the Publick Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of this Nation. Among the latter, we ſhall meet with no Man more Celebrated for the Politer Studies, and that true <hi>Generoſity,</hi> which compoſe a Fine Gentleman: and in you, Sir, give us an agreeable Proof of the preſent Care <hi>Providence</hi> takes of Eminent Merit.</p>
            <p>The Reputation of the Viva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and Wit of my Lord <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> is ſo eſtabliſh'd, that it is not in the Power of thoſe Ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur'd <hi>Criticks,</hi> deſcrib'd by Himſelf, that
<q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:175034:3"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Are dully vain of being hard</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>to pleaſe,</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
to leſſen his Eſteem. The great Succeſs of the Firſt Volume, has made this evident; of which this Second (I hope) will be a farther Proof.</p>
            <p>The late Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> Mr. <hi>Savile,</hi> Sir <hi>George Etheridge,</hi> bring their own Credentials: And as for the reſt that make up this Book, I ſhall leave them to their own Deſert, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing convinc'd that no <hi>Apology</hi> will ever prepoſſeſs a <hi>Reader</hi> to the Advantage of whatever wants Force enough to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it ſelf; and all that a Man can ſay, is taken (like Court Recommendations) for Words of Courſe; tho' I might here be allow'd to be Impartial,
<pb facs="tcp:175034:4"/>
where I have nothing of my own to bribe my Opinion. But, Sir, as I offer the Diverting Part to Your Pleaſure, ſo I muſt that, which may prove other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to Your Generous Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, with him, who begs leave to ſubſcribe my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR, </salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your most Humble and Obedient Servant,</hi>
Charles Gildon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="bookseller_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:175034:4"/>
            <head>THE BOOKSELLER TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Extraordinary Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of the Firſt Volume of my Lord</hi> Rocheſter'<hi>s Letters, and the great Encouragement of ſeveral Perſons of Quality, (who had ſeen the Original Papers) to go on with the Undertaking, have engaged me to preſent You with this Second Volume, (in Compliance with the frequent Importunities of Gentlemen for the ſpeedy Edition of it) before an Excellent Collection of Fifty more of my Lord's, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable number of the Duke of</hi> Buckingham'<hi>s, and Sir</hi> George
<pb facs="tcp:175034:5"/>
Etheridge'<hi>s came to my Hands; and which are now tranſcribing for the Preſs, being ſufficient to make a Volume by themſelves; and therefore I ſhall mingle none with them, unleſs any Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman or Lady, who have any of theſe Incomparable Authors by them, will ſend 'em me to gratifie the Publick, which has with ſo much pleaſure received thoſe already publiſhed. This Volume I deſign to get ready in</hi> Trinity <hi>Term.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If any one ſhould doubt the Reality and Authentickneſs of theſe Letters in either of theſe Volumes, I have yet the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals by me, and ſhall willingly ſhew 'em to any Gentleman or Lady that deſires it; which must convince all that know my Lord's Hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:175034:5"/>
               <hi>There's a Letter, by Miſtake, put into this Volume, which was never intended for it, tho' not diſcovered till the Sheet was wrought off, for which I deſire the</hi> Reader'<hi>s Pardon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:175034:6"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF LETTERS In this Second Volume.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>THirty ſix</hi> Love-Letters, <hi>written by the Right Honourable</hi> John, <hi>late Earl of</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter, <hi>to Mrs.—, from</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 1. <hi>to</hi> p. 37</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Four Letters by Mrs.</hi> J. Price, <hi>to Madam</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts, <hi>from</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 38. <hi>to</hi> p. 41</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Letter by the Honourable</hi> H. Savile, <hi>to</hi> Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Killigrew, <hi>Eſq.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 42</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sir</hi> George Etheridge <hi>from</hi> Ratisbonne, <hi>to his Friend in</hi> London,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 44</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sir</hi> George Etheridge <hi>to the Earl of</hi> Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 47</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sir</hi> George Etheridge <hi>to the Earl of</hi> Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 50</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Letter from</hi> England, <hi>to Sir</hi> George Ethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridge <hi>in</hi> Germany,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 52</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:175034:6"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Letter to a Lady, that deſired to marry a Courtier,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 56</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Letter to Mr.</hi> Congreve,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 61</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Letter to Mr.</hi> Wicherly, <hi>by Mr.</hi> Dennis,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 65</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Letter to</hi> Dorinda,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 68</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Letter of his Grace,</hi> George, <hi>late Duke of</hi> Buckingham, <hi>to the Lord</hi> Berkley,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 71</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The</hi> Duke'<hi>s Speeches on ſeveral Occaſions, from</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 73. <hi>to</hi> p. 102</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Emperor of</hi> Morocco'<hi>s Letter to King</hi> Charles <hi>the Second,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 103</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Madam</hi> Peachy'<hi>s Letter to Mr.</hi> Bulſtrode, <hi>at</hi> White-hall,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 107</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Letter to Sir Politick, by—</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 109</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>To Mr.</hi> Savage,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 111</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Letter from a Gentleman in the Country, to a Lady in the City,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 114</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Three</hi> Love-Letters,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 116. <hi>to</hi> p. 121</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Letter to Mr.</hi> G—</cell>
                     <cell>p. 122</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Letters from a Perſon of Honour from on Board—at St.</hi> Hellens, May</cell>
                     <cell>27, 1694. p. 124</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Letter to Mrs.—</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 127</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Letter from</hi> Paris <hi>to the Lord</hi> H—</cell>
                     <cell>p. 131</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Letter to Mr.</hi> T—</cell>
                     <cell>p. 135</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>To the Chevalier</hi> Choiſeul, <hi>at</hi> La Hogue</cell>
                     <cell>p. 138</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Letter to Mr.—</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 145</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>To Mrs.—</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 147</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>To Sir</hi> John—</cell>
                     <cell>p. 149</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>To Mrs.—</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 153</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>To a Gentleman at</hi> Cambridge,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 155</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:175034:7"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>To</hi> T—W—, <hi>Eſq.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 157</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Letters of</hi> Love <hi>and</hi> Gallantry <hi>to</hi> Eugenia,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 167</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>To the ſame,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 171</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>To the ſame,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 173</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>To the ſame,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 175</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>To the ſame,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 178</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lyſander <hi>to</hi> Eugenia,</cell>
                     <cell>p. 182</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>To the ſame,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 186</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>To the ſame,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 188</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>To the ſame,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 190</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>To my Lady—</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 193</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>To Mr.—</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 195</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>To Mrs.—</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 198</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Letter of</hi> Aeneas Sylvius, <hi>who was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Pope</hi> Pius <hi>the Second, to his Father about a Baſtard ſon; whom he ſent to him,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 200</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:175034:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books printed for, and ſold by</hi> R. Wellington.</head>
            <p>AN <hi>Italian</hi> Voyage, or a compleat Journey thro' <hi>Italy,</hi> in 2 Parts; with the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of the People, and a Deſcription of the Chief Towns, Churches, Monaſteries, Tombs, Libraries, Palaces, Villa's, Gardens, Pictures, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and Antiquities; as alſo of the Intereſt, Government, Riches, Forces, &amp;c. of all the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with Inſtructions concerning Travels; the ſecond Edition, very much enlarged, by a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Hand; price 5 Shillings.</p>
            <p>The whole Works of that Excellent <hi>Practic. Phyſician</hi> Dr. <hi>Tho. Sydenham,</hi> wherein not only the Hiſt. and Cure of acute Diſeaſes are treated of, after a new and accurate Method; but alſo the ſhorteſt and ſafeſt way of curing moſt Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Diſeaſes, tranſlated from the Original <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> by <hi>John Pechey,</hi> of the <hi>College</hi> of <hi>Phyſicians;</hi> price 5 Shillings.</p>
            <p>A General Treatiſe of the Diſeaſes of Infants and Children, collected from the beſt Authors, viz. <hi>Etmuller, Willis,</hi> &amp;c. by <hi>John Pechey,</hi> of the <hi>College</hi> of <hi>Phyſicians;</hi> price 1 Shilling and 6 d.</p>
            <p>The Family-Phyſician, or a choice Collection of Remedies for all Diſeaſes incident to Human Bodies, whether internal or external, uſeful in Families, and ſerviceable to Country People: To which is added the <hi>Engliſh Wine-Cellar,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the beſt Method for making <hi>Engliſh Wines,</hi> and <hi>Metheglin,</hi> with a Collection of <hi>Coſmetick</hi> Remedies, for the preſerving the Beauty and Complection of Ladies, never before publiſh'd, by <hi>George Harman, Philo Chymist,</hi> Servant to Sir <hi>Kenelm Digby</hi> till he died; price 3 Shill.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:175034:8"/>
               <hi>OVid Traveſtie,</hi> or a Burleſque on <hi>Ovid</hi>'s Epiſtles, by Capt. <hi>Alexander Radcliff,</hi> of <hi>Gray's-Inn;</hi> price 2 Shillings.</p>
            <p>Reflections on Ancient and Modern Learning, by <hi>William Wooton,</hi> Chaplain to his Grace the Earl of <hi>Nottingham;</hi> with a Diſſertation upon the Epiſtles of <hi>Phalaris, Euripides, Themiſtocles, Socrates,</hi> and the Fables of <hi>Europe,</hi> by Doctor <hi>Bentley;</hi> price 6 Shillings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cocker</hi>'s Decimal Arithmetick, the ſecond Edition enlarged, by <hi>John Hawkings,</hi> School-Maſter at St. <hi>George</hi>'s Church in <hi>Southwarke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Incognita,</hi> or Love and Duty reconciled, a Novel, by Mr. <hi>Congreve;</hi> price 1 Shilling.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Examen Poeticum Duplex, ſive Muſarum An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicanarum Delectus alter cuiſubjicitur Epigram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matum, ſeu Poematum Minorum Specimen novum; Lond. impenſis</hi> Rich. Wellington, <hi>ad Inſigne Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyos in Coemeterio Paulino:</hi> price 3 Shillings.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Treatiſe of Education, but eſpecially of Young Gentlemen, in two Parts; price 3 Shillings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where You may have most other</hi> Books <hi>and</hi> Plays <hi>newly Printed.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:175034:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>LOVE-LETTERS,</hi> By the Right Honourable JOHN, LATE <hi>Earl of</hi> ROCHESTER.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Printed from his Original PAPERS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Vol. II.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To Mrs.———</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SO much <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Beauty,</hi> as You have, ſhou'd think of nothing leſs than doing <hi>Miracles;</hi> and there cannot be a <hi>Greater,</hi> than to continue to <hi>love</hi> Me: affecting every thing is <hi>mean,</hi> as loving Pleaſure, and being <hi>fond</hi> where
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:175034:9"/>
You find <hi>Merit;</hi> but to pick out the <hi>wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est,</hi> and moſt <hi>fantaſtical odd</hi> Man alive, and to place your <hi>Kindneſs</hi> there, is an Act ſo <hi>brave</hi> and <hi>daring,</hi> as will ſhew the <hi>Greatneſs</hi> of Your Spirit, and <hi>diſtinguiſh</hi> You in <hi>Love,</hi> as You are in <hi>all things</hi> elſe, from Womankind. Whether I have made a <hi>good</hi> Argument for <hi>my ſelf,</hi> I leave You to <hi>judge;</hi> and beg You to believe me, whenever I tell You what Mrs. <hi>R.</hi> is, ſince I give you ſo <hi>ſincere</hi> an Account of her humbleſt Servant: Remember the Hour of a <hi>ſtrict</hi> Account, when both Hearts are to be <hi>open,</hi> and we oblig'd to ſpeak <hi>freely,</hi> as You order'd it <hi>Yeſterday,</hi> for ſo I muſt ever call the <hi>Day</hi> I ſaw you <hi>last,</hi> ſince all time between that and the next <hi>Viſit,</hi> is no part of my <hi>Life,</hi> or at leaſt like a <hi>long Fit</hi> of the <hi>Falling-ſickneſs,</hi> wherein I am <hi>dead</hi> to all <hi>Joy</hi> and <hi>Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Here's a damn'd impertinent <hi>Fool</hi> bolted in, that hinders me from ending my <hi>Letter;</hi> the Plague of——take him, and any Man or Woman alive that take my <hi>Thoughts</hi> off of <hi>You:</hi> But in the <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> I will ſee You, and be <hi>happy</hi> in ſpite of all the <hi>Fools</hi> in the World.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:175034:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF there be yet alive within you the leaſt Memory of me, which I can hope only, becauſe of the Life that remains with me, is the dear Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of you; and methinks your Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as the younger, ſhou'd out-live mine: Give me leave to aſſure you, I will meet it very ſhortly with ſuch a ſhare on my ſide, as will juſtifie me to you from all <hi>Ingratitude;</hi> tho' your <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours</hi> are to me the greateſt <hi>Bliſs</hi> this <hi>World,</hi> or <hi>Womankind,</hi> which I think <hi>Heaven,</hi> can beſtow, (but the hopes of it:) If there can be any <hi>Addition</hi> to one of the higheſt Misfortunes, my <hi>Abſence</hi> from you has found the way to give it me, in not affording me the leaſt <hi>Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of doing you any <hi>Service</hi> ſince I left you: It ſeems, till I am capable of <hi>greater</hi> Merit, you reſolve to keep me from the <hi>Vanity</hi> of pretending any at <hi>all.</hi> Pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider when you give another leave to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175034:10"/>
                  <hi>ſerve</hi> you, <hi>more</hi> than <hi>I,</hi> how much <hi>Injuſtice</hi> you run the hazard of committing, when it will not be in your power to <hi>reward</hi> that <hi>More-deſerving</hi> Man with half ſo much Happineſs as you have thrown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way upon my <hi>Worthleſs</hi> Self,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Reſtleſs Servant, —</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:175034:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>———</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Know not well who has the <hi>worst</hi> on't, you, who love but a <hi>little,</hi> or I, who doat to an <hi>Extravagance;</hi> ſure, to be half-kind, is as bad as to be half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witted; and <hi>Madneſs,</hi> both in <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> bears a better Character than a moderate ſtate of either. Would I cou'd bring you to my <hi>Opinion,</hi> in this Point; I wou'd then confidently pretend you had too juſt Exceptions either againſt me or my <hi>Paſſion,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh</hi> and the <hi>Devil;</hi> I mean all the <hi>Fools</hi> of my own <hi>Sex,</hi> and that <hi>fat,</hi> with the other <hi>lean</hi> One of yours, whoſe prudent Advice is daily concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you, how dangerous it is to be kind to the Man, upon <hi>Earth,</hi> who loves you beſt. I, who ſtill perſwade my ſelf, by all the Arguments I can bring, that I am Happy, find this none of the leaſt, that you are too unlike theſe People every way, to agree with them in any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. This is writ between ſleeping and waking, and I will not anſwer for its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Sence;</hi> but I, dreaming you were
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175034:11"/>
at Mrs. <hi>N</hi>——'s, with five or ſix <hi>Fools,</hi> and the <hi>Lean</hi> Lady wak'd in one of your <hi>Horrours,</hi> and, in Amaze, Fright, and Confuſion, ſend this to beg a kind one from you, that may remove my <hi>Fears,</hi> and make me as Happy as I am Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>———</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOU are ſtark Mad, and therefore the fitter for me to love; and that is the reaſon, I think, I can never leave to be</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Humble Servant,———</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:175034:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>———</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>TO convince you how juſt I muſt ever be to you, I have ſent this on purpoſe, that you may know you are not a <hi>moment</hi> out of my <hi>Thoughts;</hi> and ſince ſo much Merit as you have, and ſuch convincing Charms (to me at leaſt) need not wiſh a greater Advantage over any; to forget you, is the only <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieve</hi> poſſible for a Man ſo much your Creature and Servant as I am; which I am ſo far from <hi>wiſhing,</hi> that I conjure you by all the aſſurances of <hi>Kindneſs</hi> you have ever made me proud and happy with, that not two Days can paſs without ſome <hi>Letter</hi> from you to me: You muſt leave 'em, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>——to be ſent to me with <hi>ſpeed.</hi> And till the <hi>bleſt</hi> Hour wherein I ſhall ſee you again, may Happineſs of all kinds be as far from me, as I do, both in <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Jealouſie,</hi> pray Mankind may be from you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:175034:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>———</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THere is now no minute of my Life that does not afford me ſome new <hi>Argument</hi> how much I love you; the little <hi>Joy</hi> I take in every thing wherein you are not concern'd, the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>Perplexity</hi> of endleſs <hi>Thought,</hi> which I fall into, where-ever you are brought to my <hi>Remembrance;</hi> and laſtly, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual <hi>Diſquiet</hi> I am, in, during your <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> convince me ſufficiently, that I do you <hi>Juſtice</hi> in loving you, ſo as <hi>Woman</hi> was never lov'd before.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:175034:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>———</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOur ſafe <hi>Delivery</hi> has deliver'd me too from <hi>Fears</hi> for your ſake, which were, I'll promiſe you, as <hi>burthenſom</hi> to me, as your <hi>Great-belly</hi> cou'd be to you. Every thing has fallen out to my <hi>Wiſh,</hi> for you are out of <hi>Danger,</hi> and the Child is of the <hi>ſoft Sex</hi> I love. Short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly my Hopes are to ſee you, and in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while after to look on you with all your <hi>Beauty</hi> about you. Pray let no Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy but your ſelf open the <hi>Box</hi> I ſent you; I did not know, but that in <hi>Lying-in,</hi> you might have uſe of thoſe <hi>Trifles: Sick,</hi> and in <hi>Bed,</hi> as I am, I cou'd come at no <hi>more</hi> of 'em; but if you find 'em, or whatever is in my power of uſe, to your Service, let me know it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:175034:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THis is the firſt Service my Hand has done me, ſince my being a <hi>Cripple,</hi> and I wou'd not imploy it in a <hi>Lie</hi> ſo ſoon; therefore, pray, believe me <hi>ſincere,</hi> when I aſſure you, that you are very <hi>dear</hi> to me; and, as long as I live, I will be <hi>kind</hi> to you:</p>
               <closer/>
               <postscript>
                  <head>P. S.</head>
                  <p>This is all my <hi>Hand</hi> wou'd <hi>write,</hi> but my <hi>Heart thinks</hi> a great deal more.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>NOthing can ever be ſo <hi>dear</hi> to me as you are; and I am ſo <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd</hi> of this, that I dare under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to love you whilſt I live: Believe all I ſay, for that is the kindeſt thing ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, and when you can deviſe any way that may make me appear ſo to you, inſtruct me in it, for I need a better <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,</hi> than my own, to ſhew my <hi>Love,</hi> without wrong to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:175034:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>NOw, as I love you, I think I have reaſon to be <hi>Jealous;</hi> your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour came in laſt Night with all the <hi>Marks</hi> and <hi>Behaviour</hi> of a <hi>Spy;</hi> every word and look imply'd, that ſhe came to ſolicite your <hi>Love,</hi> or <hi>Conſtancy:</hi> May her <hi>Endeavours</hi> prove as vain as I wiſh my <hi>Fears.</hi> May no Man ſhare the <hi>Bleſſings</hi> I enjoy, without my <hi>Curſes;</hi> and if they fall on him alone, without touching you, I am happy, tho' he deſerves 'em not: but ſhou'd you be concern'd, they'll all flie back upon my ſelf; for he, whom you are kind to, is ſo bleſt, he may ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtand the <hi>Curſes</hi> of all the World with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repining; at leaſt, if like me, he be ſenſible of nothing but what comes from Mrs.—</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:175034:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOu are the moſt afflicting fair Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the World; and however you wou'd perſwade me to the contrary, I cannot but believe the <hi>Fault</hi> you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to excuſe, is the only one I cou'd ever be guilty of to you: when you think of receiving an Anſwer with Common Sence in it, you muſt write <hi>Letters</hi> that give leſs <hi>Confuſion</hi> than your laſt: I will wait on you, and be reveng'd by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing to love you, when you grow wearieſt of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:175034:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YEſterday it was impoſſible to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer your Letter, which I hope, for that reaſon, you will forgive me; tho' indeed you have been pleas'd to expreſs your ſelf ſo extra ordinarily, that I know not what I have to Anſwer to you. Give me ſome <hi>Reaſon</hi> upon your own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count only, to be ſorry I ever had the Happineſs to know you, ſince I find you repent the <hi>Kindneſs</hi> you ſhew'd me, and undervalue the humble Service I had for you; and, that I might be no happier in your Favours, than you could be in my <hi>Love,</hi> you have contriv'd it ſo well, to make them equal to my Hatred; ſince that cou'd do no more than theſe pretend to, take away the <hi>Quiet</hi> of my Life. I tell this not to exempt my ſelf from any Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice I can do you, (for I can never <hi>forget</hi> how very happy I have been) but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you, the <hi>Love</hi> that gives you the <hi>Torment</hi> of <hi>Repentance</hi> on your ſide, and me the <hi>Trouble</hi> of perceiving it in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is equally unjuſt and cruel to us both, and ought therefore to die.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:175034:15"/>
               <head>To Mrs.—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOu ſhall not fail of———on <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day;</hi> and for your <hi>Wretches,</hi> as you call 'em, 'tis uſually my Cuſtom when I wrong ſuch as they, to make 'em amends; tho' your Maid has <hi>aggravated</hi> that matter more to my <hi>Prejudice</hi> than I expected from one who belong'd to you, and for your own ſhare, If I thought you a Woman of <hi>Forms,</hi> you ſhou'd receive all the <hi>Reparations</hi> ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable; but it is ſo unqueſtionable, that I am thoroughly your humble Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, that all the World muſt know, I cannot offend you, without being ſorry for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:175034:15"/>
               <head>To Mrs.—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THo' upon the Score of <hi>Love,</hi> which is immediately my <hi>Concern,</hi> I find apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs enough to be <hi>jealous;</hi> yet upon that of your <hi>Safety,</hi> which is the only thing in the World <hi>weighs</hi> more with me than my <hi>Love,</hi> I apprehend much more. I know, by woful Experience, what comes of deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with <hi>Knaves;</hi> ſuch I am ſure you have at this time to do with; therefore look well about you, and take it for granted, That unleſs you can <hi>deceive</hi> them, they will certainly <hi>cozen</hi> you. If I am not ſo <hi>wiſe</hi> as they, and therefore leſs <hi>fit</hi> to adviſe you, I am at leaſt more <hi>concern'd</hi> for you, and for that reaſon the likelier to prove <hi>honest,</hi> and the rather to be <hi>truſted.</hi> Whether you will come to the <hi>Duke</hi>'s Play-houſe to Day, or at leaſt let me come to you when the Play is done, I leave to your Choice; let me know, if you pleaſe, by the <hi>Bearer.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:175034:16"/>
               <head>To Mrs.—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>MIght I be ſo happy to receive ſuch <hi>Proofs</hi> of your <hi>Kindneſs,</hi> as I my ſelf wou'd <hi>chooſe,</hi> one of the greateſt I cou'd think of were, that all my <hi>Actions,</hi> however they appear'd at firſt, might be interpreted as meant for your <hi>Service;</hi> ſince nothing is ſo <hi>agreeable</hi> to my Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as ſeeking my own <hi>Satisfaction;</hi> and ſince you are the beſt <hi>Object</hi> of that I can find in the World, how can you entertain a <hi>Jealouſie</hi> or <hi>Fear?</hi> You have the ſtrongeſt <hi>Security</hi> our frail and daily changing Frame can give, that I can <hi>live</hi> to no end ſo much, as that of pleaſing and ſerving you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:175034:16"/>
               <head>To Mrs.—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have not ſinn'd ſo much as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to live two whole Days with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſeeing of you. From your <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Good-nature</hi> therefore I will preſume you will give me leave to wait on you at Night, and for your ſake uſe not that Power (which you find you have abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute over me) ſo unmercifully as you did laſt time, to divert and keep me off, from convincing you by all the Reaſons imaginable, how neceſſary 'tis to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve you faultleſs, and make me happy; and alſo, that you believe and uſe me like the moſt Faithful of all your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:175034:17"/>
               <head>To Mrs.—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>DEareſt of all that ever was deareſt to me, if I love any thing in the World like you, or wiſh it in my Power to do it, may I ever be as unlucky and as hateful as when I ſaw you laſt. I who have no way to expreſs my Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to you, but Letters, which cannot ſpeak it half; whether ſhall I think my ſelf more unfortunate, who cannot tell you how much I love, or you, who can never know how well you are belov'd; I wou'd fain bring it about, if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, to wait upon you to day; for beſides that I never am without the paſſionate Deſire of being with you, at this time I have ſomething to tell you, that is for your Service, and will not be unpleaſant News, but I am in Chains here, and muſt ſeek out ſome Device, to break 'em for a quarter of an hour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:175034:17"/>
               <head>To Mrs.—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IT is impoſſible for me to neglect what I love, as it wou'd be impertinent to profeſs love where I had none; but I take the vanity to aſſure my ſelf, you cannot conclude ſo ſeverely both of my Truth and Reaſon, as to ſuſpect me for either of thoſe Faults. If there has been a Misfortune in the Miſcarriage of my Letters, I beſeech you not to add to it by an uncharitable Cenſure, but do me the right to believe the laſt thing poſſible in the World, is the leaſt Omiſſion of either Kindneſs or Service to you: I wiſh the whole World was as intirely yours as I am, you wou'd then have no reaſon to complain of any Body; at leaſt, it wou'd be your own Fault, if they were not what you pleas'd. Thoſe Wretches you ſpeak of in your Letter, are ſo little valuable, that you will eaſily forget their Malice, and rather look upon the more conſiderable part of the World, who will ever find it their Intereſt, and make it their vanity to ſerve you. And now to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:175034:18"/>
let you know how ſoon I propoſe to be out of pain, two Days hence I leave this Place, in order to my Journey towards <hi>London;</hi> and may I then be but as happy as your Kindneſs can make me, I ſhall have but very little room either for <hi>Envy</hi> or <hi>Ambition.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <date>Octob. 6th.</date> 
                  <hi>This Morning your Meſſenger came.</hi>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>———</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Found you in a Chiding Humour to Day, and ſo I left you; to Morrow I hope for better Luck: till when, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you, nor any you can employ, ſhall know whether I am under or above Ground; therefore lie ſtill, and ſatisfie your ſelf, that your are not, nor can be half ſo kind to Mrs.———as I am:</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Good-night.</salute>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:175034:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>————</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>MY Faults are ſuch, as, among rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable People, will ever find Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe; but to you I will make none, you are ſo very full of <hi>Myſtery:</hi> I believe you make your <hi>Court</hi> with good Succeſs, at leaſt I wiſh it; and as the kindeſt thing I can ſay, do aſſure you, you ſhall never be my <hi>Pattern,</hi> either in <hi>Good-nature,</hi> or <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> for I will be after my own rate, not yours,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your humble Servant, ————</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:175034:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am far from delighting in the <hi>Grief</hi> I have given you, by taking away the <hi>Child;</hi> and you, who made it ſo abſolutely neceſſary for me to do ſo, muſt take that Excuſe from me, for all the ill Nature of it: On the other ſide, pray be aſſur'd, I love <hi>Betty</hi> ſo well, that you need not apprehend any <hi>Neglect</hi> from thoſe I employ; and I hope very ſhortly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore her to you a finer <hi>Girl</hi> than ever. In the mean time you wou'd do well to think of the <hi>Advice</hi> I gave you, for how little ſhew ſoever my <hi>Prudence</hi> makes in my own <hi>Affairs,</hi> in yours it will prove very ſucceſsful, if you pleaſe to follow it; and ſince <hi>Diſcretion</hi> is the thing alone you are like to want, pray ſtudy to get it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:175034:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Came to Town late laſt Night, tho' time enough to receive News from the <hi>King</hi> very ſurprizing, you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing chiefly concern'd in't: I muſt beg that I may ſpeak with you this Morning, at ten a clock; I will not fail to be at your Door: The <hi>Affair</hi> is unhappy, and to me on many Scores, but on none, more than that it has diſturb'd the <hi>Heaven</hi> of <hi>Thought</hi> I was in, to think, after ſo long an <hi>Abſence,</hi> I had liv'd to be again bleſt with ſeeing my Deareſt Dear, Mrs.—</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:175034:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am forc'd at laſt to own, That 'tis very uneaſie to me to live ſo long without hearing a word of you, eſpecially when I reflect how <hi>Ill-natur'd</hi> the World is to <hi>pretty</hi> Women, and what occaſion you may have for their Service. Beſides, I am unſatisfied yet, why that <hi>Inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> Service you gave me leave to do you, and which I left poſitive Orders for when I came away, was left unperform'd; and if the <hi>Omiſſion</hi> reflect upon my <hi>Servant,</hi> or my ſelf, that I might puniſh the one, and clear the other. I have often wiſh'd, I know not why, but I think for your ſake more than my own, that Mrs.—<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>migh forget me quite: but I find it wou'd trouble me of all things, ſhou'd ſhe think ill of me, or remember me to hate me, but when-ever ſhe wou'd make me hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py; if ſhe can yet wiſh me ſo, let her command ſome real Service, and my <hi>Obedience</hi> will prove the beſt <hi>Reward</hi> my <hi>Hopes</hi> can aim at.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:175034:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>MY Viſit Yeſterday was intended to tell you, I had not <hi>Din'd</hi> in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>Women,</hi> which (tho' for a certain <hi>Reaſon</hi> I cou'd not very well expreſs with <hi>Words)</hi> was however ſufficiently made appear, ſince you could not be ſo very <hi>Ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur'd</hi> to make ſevere Reflections upon me when I was gone. Were Men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Frailties,</hi> how wou'd you bring it about to make 'em love you ſo blindly as they do. I cannot yet imagine what fault you could find in my Love-letter; certainly 'twas full of <hi>Kindneſs</hi> and <hi>Duty</hi> to you; and whileſt theſe two Points are kept inviolable, 'tis very hard when you take any thing ill. I fear ſtaying at Home ſo much gives you the <hi>Spleen</hi> (for I am loth to believe 'tis I) I have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſent you the two <hi>Plays</hi> that are acted this Afternoon; if that <hi>Diverſion</hi> cou'd put you into ſo good a Humour, as to make you able to endure me again, I ſhou'd be very much oblig'd to the <hi>Stage.</hi> However, if your <hi>Anger</hi> continue, ſhew your ſelf at the <hi>Play,</hi> that I may look
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:175034:21"/>
upon you, and go <hi>mad.</hi> Your <hi>Revenge</hi> is in your own <hi>Eyes;</hi> and if I muſt ſuffer, I wou'd chuſe that way.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To Mrs.—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THo' not for <hi>real Kindneſs</hi> ſake, at leaſt to make your own Words good, (which is a Point of Honour pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for a <hi>Woman)</hi> endeavour to give me ſome <hi>undeniable Proofs</hi> that you <hi>love</hi> me. If there be any in my <hi>Power</hi> which I have yet neither given nor offer'd, you muſt explain your ſelf; I am perhaps very dull, but withal very ſincere: I could wiſh, for your ſake, and my own, that your Fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings were ſuch; but be they what they will, ſince I muſt love you, allow me the liberty of telling you ſometimes unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly <hi>Truths,</hi> when my <hi>Zeal</hi> for your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice cauſes, and your own <hi>Interest</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it: Theſe <hi>Inconveniences</hi> you muſt bear with from thoſe that love you, with greater regard to you than themſelves; ſuch a One I pretend to be, and I hope, if you do not yet believe it, you will in time find it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:175034:21"/>
You have ſaid ſomething that has made me fancy to Morrow will prove a happy Day to me; however, pray let me ſee you before you ſpeak with any other Man, there are Reaſons for it, <hi>Dearest</hi> of all my <hi>Deſires.</hi> I expect your <hi>Commands.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>An Hour after I left You.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To Mrs.—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have a very juſt <hi>Quarrel</hi> to <hi>Buſineſs,</hi> upon a thouſand <hi>Faults,</hi> and will now continue it, whilſt I live, ſince it takes from me ſome Hours of your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. Till two in the Afternoon, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come to you; pity my <hi>Ill-fortune,</hi> and ſend me word where I ſhall then find you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:175034:22"/>
               <head>To Mrs.—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Was juſt beginning to write You word, that I am the moſt <hi>Unlucky</hi> Creature in the World, when Your Letter came in, and made me more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; for You tempt me by deſiring me to do the thing upon Earth I have the moſt <hi>Fonaneſs</hi> of, at this time; that is, going with You to <hi>Windſor;</hi> but the <hi>Devil</hi> has laid a <hi>Block</hi> in my way, and I muſt not, for my Life, ſtir out of Town theſe ten Days. You will ſcarce believe me in this particular, as You ſhou'd do, but I will convince You of the Truth, when I wait on You; in the mean time (to ſhew the <hi>Reality</hi> of my <hi>Intentions)</hi> there is a Coach ready hired for to morrow, which, if not true, You may diſprove me by making uſe of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:175034:22"/>
               <head>To Mrs.—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>BElieve me, <hi>(Dearest</hi> of all <hi>Pleaſures)</hi> that thoſe I can receive from any thing but You, are ſo extreamly dull they hardly deſerve the Name. If You di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt me, and all my Profeſſions, upon the Score of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> at leaſt let 'em have <hi>Credit</hi> on another, upon which my greateſt Enemies will not deny it me; and that is, its being <hi>Notorious,</hi> that I mind nothing but my own <hi>Satisfaction.</hi> You may be ſure I cannot chuſe but love You above the World, whatever becomes of the <hi>King, Court,</hi> or <hi>Mankind,</hi> and all their <hi>Impertinent</hi> Buſineſs. I will come to You this Afternoon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:175034:23"/>
               <head>To Mrs.—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THat I do not ſee You, is not that I wou'd not, for that, the <hi>Devil</hi> take me, if I would not do every Day of my Life, but for theſe Reaſons You ſhall know hereafter. In the mean time, I can give You no Account of Your <hi>Buſineſs</hi> as yet; but of my own part, which I am ſure will not be agreeable without others, who, I am confident will give full <hi>Satisfaction</hi> in a very ſhort time, to all Your <hi>Deſires:</hi> When 'tis done, I will tell You ſomething that, perhaps, may make You think that I am Mrs.——</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your humble Servant,</signed> 
                  <dateline>
                     <date>Sunday.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:175034:23"/>
               <head>To Mrs.—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>TIll I have mended my Manners, I am aſham'd to look you in the Face, but Seeing You is as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to my Life, as Breathing; ſo that I muſt ſee You, or be Yours no more; for that's the Image I have of Dying. The Sight of You then, being my Life, I cannot but confeſs, with an humble and ſincere Repentance, that I have hitherto liv'd very ill; receive my Confeſſion, and let the Promiſe of my future Zeal and Devotion obtain my Pardon, for laſt Night's <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> againſt You, my <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> ſo ſhall I hope, hereafter, to be made partaker of ſuch <hi>Joys,</hi> in Your Arms, as meeting Tongues but faintly can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:175034:24"/>
               <head>To Mrs.—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Aſſure You I am not half ſo faulty as unfortunate in ſerving You; I will not tell You my Endeavours, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe my Breach of Promiſe; but leave it to You to find the cauſe of my doing ſo ill, to one I wiſh ſo well to; but I hope to give You a better Account ſhortly. The Complaint You ſpoke to me, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Miſs,</hi> I know nothing of, for ſhe is as great a Stranger to me, as ſhe can be to You. So, thou pretty Creature Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your humble Servant,—</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:175034:24"/>
               <head>To Mrs.—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOur Letter ſo tranſports me, that I know not how to anſwer it, the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions are ſo ſoft, and ſeem to be ſo ſincere, that I were the unreaſonableſt Creature on Earth, cou'd I but ſeem to diſtruſt my being the happier: and the beſt Contrivance I can think of, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying a Letter to me, is making a <hi>Porter</hi> bring it my <hi>Foot-man,</hi> where-ever I am, whether at St. <hi>James</hi>'s, <hi>Whitehall,</hi> or home. They are at preſent pulling down ſome part of my Lodging, which will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to ſee You there; but I will wait on You at any other place, what time You pleaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:175034:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>———</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Could ſay a great deal to you, but will conceal it till I have Merit: ſo theſe ſhall be only to beg your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, for deſiring your Excuſe till Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and then you ſhall find me an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Man, and one of my Word. So Mrs.——</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Servant,———</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:175034:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>MY Omitting to write to you all this while, were an unpardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Errour, had I been guilty of it thro' <hi>Neglect</hi> towards you, which I value you too much ever to be capable of. But I have never been two days in a place, ſince Mrs.—went away; which I ought to have given you Notice of, and have let you known, that her Crime was, making her Court to——with Stories of you; entertaining her continually with the <hi>Shame</hi> ſhe underwent to be ſeen in Company of ſo horrid a Body as your ſelf, in order to the obtaining of her—'s <hi>Employment;</hi> and laſtly, that my—was ten times prettier than that naſty B—, I was ſo fond of at <hi>London,</hi> which I had by you. This was the grateful Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment ſhe made you for all your <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours,</hi> and this <hi>Recompence</hi> for all the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>Services;</hi> which, upon your Account, ſhe receiv'd from,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your humble Servant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:175034:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>———</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>ANger, Spleen, Revenge, and Shame, are not yet ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful with me, as to make me diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own this great <hi>Truth,</hi> That I love you above all things in the World: But, I thank <hi>God,</hi> I can diſtinguiſh, I can ſee very <hi>Woman</hi> in you, and from your ſelf am convinc'd I have never been in the wrong in the Opinion of <hi>Women:</hi> 'Tis impoſſible for me to curſe you; but give me leave to pity my ſelf, which is more than ever you will do for me. You have a Character, and you maintain it; but I am ſorry you make me an <hi>Example</hi> to prove it: It ſeems (as you excel in every thing) you ſcorn to grow leſs in that noble Quality of Uſing your <hi>Servants</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hardly: You do well not to forget it; and rather practice upon me, than loſe the Habit of being very <hi>Severe,</hi> for you that chuſe rather to be Wiſe than Juſt or Good-natur'd, may freely diſpoſe of all things in your Power, without Regard
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:175034:26"/>
to one, or the other. As I admire you, I wou'd be glad I cou'd imitate you; it were but Manners to endeavour it; which, ſince I am not able to perform, I confeſs you are in the right to call that Rude, which I call Kind; and ſo keep me in the Wrong for ever, which you cannot chuſe but take great Delight in: You need but continue to make it fit for me not to love you, and you can never want ſomething to upbraid me with.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Three a Clock in the Morning.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the E. of R.'s Letters.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:175034:27"/>
            <head>LETTERS ON <hi>SEVERAL OCCASIONS,</hi> Written by Mrs. J. PRICE.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi> Roberts.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>HAving ſo much Wit, I wonder you ſhou'd in the leaſt miſtake Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for Prudence; that's a thing I never had yet laid to my Charge. In time I doubt not but you will know me better: I am the ſorrier for my Indiſpoſition, ſince I cannot comply with your <hi>Deſires;</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, if you pleaſe to come hither, you ſhall be extreamly welcome to her that will eſteem her ſelf happy in you <hi>Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. Price.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Thurſday.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:175034:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi> Roberts.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>'TWere very dull and ill-natur'd in me, to forget the Joy and Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction I receiv'd in your laſt Kindneſs; and ſeeming to do it, were a Fault not pardonable: therefore, <hi>Madam,</hi> forgive this <hi>Impertinence,</hi> ſince there is no way that can tell ſo much the Sence of your <hi>Favours</hi> as this; and I have had a Hope that you wou'd be ſo Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur'd, as to have ſeen me: But the ſame Croſs-fate, which generally purſues me, leaves me not in this concern: Let me know that you are well, and 'twill make ſome Reparation for the Pain I ſuffer in not ſeeing you; and, if you think I deſerve your Kindneſs, 'tis a Happineſs, which ſhall never be forgot, by</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your most humble Servant,
J. Price.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:175034:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi> Roberts.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have this Morning acquainted the Party with the Honour you did me laſt Night; and, as you expreſs your ſelf to me only in general Terms, I cou'd do no more to him: I find him very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of his Obligation to you, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to comply in any thing, in his own Power, reaſonable for your Service; it is an eaſier Task for <hi>Beauty</hi> to get twenty <hi>new</hi> Servants, than recover one <hi>old</hi> one; and, truly, I conceive him in a deſperate condition: He was a little ſurpriz'd to find me your <hi>Embaſſadour;</hi> but, I believe, took it better from my Mouth, than he would have done from any other.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. Price.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:175034:28"/>
               <head>A Letter to Mrs. <hi>Price.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Need not tell you how drunk we were on <hi>Saturday;</hi> ſince, as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, we gave you good proof of it under our own Hands: however, I made a ſhift to ride home, but am now galloping to <hi>Poltimore;</hi> and, if I am not miſtaken, you will have occaſion to take a little Journey too; Mum! for that. Here's not a Syllable of News, but that all things of our Concern ſtand fair and well; and if it ſhou'd ever happen other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, which I'm confident it will not, be aſſur'd it ſhall not be the Fault of,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Love,</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:175034:29"/>
            <head>A LETTER, Written by the Honourable <hi>HENRY SAVILE.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>
               <hi>To</hi> Henry Killigrew, <hi>Eſq.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Noble HENRY,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SWeet <hi>Nameſake</hi> of mine, happy Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour'd <hi>Killigrew,</hi> Soul of Mirth, and all Delight; the very Sight of your Letter gave me a kind of Joy, that I thought had been at ſuch a Diſtance with me, that <hi>She</hi> and <hi>I</hi> were never more to meet: For, ſince I have been at <hi>St. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans, Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> were nearer one another, than <hi>Joy</hi> and <hi>Fermyn;</hi> for, here, ſome half a Mile out of Town, abſent from all my Friends, in the fear of being forgot by 'em, I paſs my weariſom time, in a little melancholly Wood, as fit for a reſtleſs Mind to complain of his ſad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:175034:29"/>
as I am unfit to relate my Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferances, to one ſo happy as your Bleſſed Humour makes you; therefore as freely I quit you of Hearing what I cou'd ſay on this Subject: likewiſe allow me the Liberty of not anſwering in your own Stile; yet, dear <hi>Harry,</hi> write ſtill the ſame way: Once I could drink, talk ſtrangely, and be as mad as the beſt of you, my <hi>Boys;</hi> who knows but that I may come to it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain? Comfort me, 'tis well I can ſtay thus long upon the matter, after the Life I have led, it is more than I did believe was poſſible for me to do; therefore do not abandon me yet, try two or three Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters more, there is great hopes of me; and if that does not do the buſineſs, ſend me to my <hi>Wood</hi> again, and allow me not other <hi>Correſpondent,</hi> but pert and dull <hi>Maſt</hi>—'s, a Puniſhment great enough for a greater Offender; for, in this my Miſery, he plays the <hi>Devil</hi> with me, ſurpaſſes himſelf by much: Prithee, <hi>Killigrew,</hi> allay his Tongue with two or three ſuch ſharp things, as you and I us'd to ſay of, you know <hi>who,</hi> for I loſt mine. And ſo <hi>Farewel.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Savile.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:175034:30"/>
            <head>LETTERS IN <hi>PROSE</hi> and <hi>VERSE,</hi> ON Several Occaſions, BY Sir George Etheridge, <hi>Knight.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>To his Friend in</hi> London.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>MY Letters from <hi>England</hi> tell me, that this Summer My Lord <hi>Chamberlain</hi> has won the Mony at <hi>Bowls,</hi> and my Lord <hi>Devonſhire</hi> at <hi>Dice;</hi> I hope neither of 'em have been lucky at your coſt. Before you receive this, I reckon you will be in your <hi>Winter Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:175034:30"/>
where you may have leiſure to give me a ſhort Account of what paſs'd at the Campaign at <hi>Tunbridge.</hi> I cannot but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member Mr. <hi>M.</hi> tho' he ſeems to have quite forgot me; he is a very extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Perſon, I find he had rather lend a Friend a hundred Pounds, than take the pains to write to him. I'm ſenſible his many Employments afford him little lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and I ſhou'd pity his Miſtreſs, but that I am perſwaded his Prudence has made him chuſe her in the Family. The Women here are not generally handſom; yet there is a file of young Ladies in this Town, whoſe Arms wou'd glitter, were they drawn up againſt the <hi>Maids of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour;</hi> but the <hi>Devil</hi>'s in't, Marriage is ſo much their Buſineſs, that they cannot ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie a Lover that has Deſires more fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent than <hi>Frank Villers.</hi> 'Tis a fine thing for a Man, who has been nouriſh'd ſo many Years with good ſubſtantial Fleſh and Blood, to be reduc'd to Sighs an Wiſhes, and all thoſe Airy Courſes which are ſerved up to feaſt a <hi>Belle</hi> Paſſion; but to comfort my ſelf, in my Misfortune, I have learn'd to <hi>Ogle</hi> and <hi>Languiſh</hi> in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, like any <hi>Walcup;</hi> and to content my ſelf in private, with a piece of Houſhold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:175034:31"/>
as well as ſome of my Friends. However unkind Fortune has been to you, don't revenge your ſelf on me; force the Sullenneſs of your Temper, and let me hear from you; it is not reaſonable I ſhould loſe a <hi>Friend,</hi> becauſe you have loſt your <hi>Money.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours,
G. Etheridge.</signed> 
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From</hi> Ratisbon, <date>Aug. 23 d, 88.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:175034:31"/>
               <head>To the Earl of Middleton.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Since Love and Verſe, as well as Wine,</l>
                  <l>Are brisker where the Sun does ſhine,</l>
                  <l>'Tis ſomething to loſe two Degrees,</l>
                  <l>Now <hi>Age</hi> it ſelf begins to freeze;</l>
                  <l>Yet this I patiently could bear,</l>
                  <l>If the rich <hi>Danube</hi>'s Beauties were</l>
                  <l>But only two Degrees leſs fair</l>
                  <l>Than the bright Nymphs of gentle <hi>Thames,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who warm me hither with their Beams;</l>
                  <l>Such power they have, they can diſpence</l>
                  <l>Five hundred Miles their Influence:</l>
                  <l>But Hunger forces Men to eat,</l>
                  <l>Tho' no Temptation's in the Meat.</l>
                  <l>How wou'd the Ogling Sparks deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>The Darling-damſel of my Eyes,</l>
                  <l>Should they behold her at a Play,</l>
                  <l>As ſhe's trick'd up on Holiday,</l>
                  <l>When the whole Family combine,</l>
                  <l>For publick Pride, to make her ſhine?</l>
                  <l>Her Locks, which long before lay matted,</l>
                  <l>Are, on this day, comb'd out and platted,</l>
                  <l>A Diamond-bodkin in each Treſs,</l>
                  <l>The Badges of her Nobleneſs;</l>
                  <l>For every Stone, as well as She,</l>
                  <l>Can boast an ancient Pedigree:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:175034:32"/>
Theſe form'd the Jewel Crest did grace</l>
                  <l>The Cap of the first Grave o'th' Race,</l>
                  <l>Preferr'd by <hi>Graffin Maryan,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To adorn the handle of her Fan;</l>
                  <l>And, as by old Record appears,</l>
                  <l>Worn ſince in <hi>Rinigundus</hi> Years,</l>
                  <l>Now ſparkling in the Fraulin's Hair,</l>
                  <l>No Rocket breaking in the Air,</l>
                  <l>Can with her ſtarry Head compare;</l>
                  <l>Such Ropes of Pearl her Arms incumber,</l>
                  <l>She ſcarce can deal the Cards at Omber;</l>
                  <l>So many Rings each Finger freight,</l>
                  <l>They tremble with the mighty Weight;</l>
                  <l>The like in <hi>England</hi> ne'r was ſeen,</l>
                  <l>Since <hi>Holbin Drew, Hal,</hi> and his Queen.</l>
                  <l>But after theſe fantaſtick Flights,</l>
                  <l>The Luſtre's meaner than the Lights:</l>
                  <l>The Thing that bears this glittering Pomp,</l>
                  <l>Is but a tawdry ill-bred Ramp,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Brawny Limbs and Martial Face,</l>
                  <l>Proclaim her of the <hi>Gothick</hi> Race,</l>
                  <l>More than the painted Pageantry</l>
                  <l>Of all her Father's Heraldry.</l>
                  <l>But there's another ſort of Creatures,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ruddy Looks, and groteſque Features,</l>
                  <l>Are ſo much out of Nature's way,</l>
                  <l>You'd think'em ſtamp'd on other Clay,</l>
                  <l>No lawful Daughters of Old <hi>Adam.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Mongst theſe, behold a City-Madam,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:175034:32"/>
With Arms in <hi>Mittins,</hi> Head in <hi>Muff,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A Dapper <hi>Cloak,</hi> and Reverend Ruff.</l>
                  <l>No Farce ſo pleaſant as this Mawkin,</l>
                  <l>And the ſoft ſound of <hi>High-Dutch</hi> talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</l>
                  <l>The pretty Jet ſhe has in walking:</l>
                  <l>Here unattended by the <hi>Graces,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Queen of <hi>Love</hi> in a ſad Caſe is;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nature,</hi> her Active Miniſter,</l>
                  <l>Neglects Affairs, and will not ſtir,</l>
                  <l>Thinks it not worth the while to pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>But when ſhe does is for her Eaſe;</l>
                  <l>Ev'n I, her most devout Adorer,</l>
                  <l>With wand'ring Thoughts appear before her,</l>
                  <l>And when I'm making an <hi>Oblation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Am fain to ſpur <hi>Imagination,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With ſome old <hi>London-Inclination.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Bow is bent at <hi>German</hi> Dame,</l>
                  <l>The Arrow flies at <hi>Engliſh</hi> Game;</l>
                  <l>Kindneſs, that can Indifference warm,</l>
                  <l>And blow that Calm into a Storm,</l>
                  <l>Has, in the very tender'st Hour,</l>
                  <l>Over my Gentleneſs no Power,</l>
                  <l>True to my Country-Womens Charms,</l>
                  <l>When Kiſs'd and Preſs'd in Foreign Arms.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>G. Etheridge.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:175034:33"/>
               <head>To the Earl of MIDDLETON.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>FRom hunting Whores, and hanting Play,</l>
                  <l>And minding nothing elſe all Day,</l>
                  <l>And all the Night too, you will ſay,</l>
                  <l>To make grave Legs in formal Fetters,</l>
                  <l>Converſe with Fops, and write dull Letters,</l>
                  <l>To go to Bed' twixt Eight and Nine,</l>
                  <l>And ſleep away my precious Time,</l>
                  <l>In ſuch a idle ſneaking Place,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Vice</hi> and <hi>Folly</hi> hide their Face;</l>
                  <l>And in a troubleſome Diſguiſe,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Wife</hi> ſeems honest, <hi>Husband</hi> wife;</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Pleaſure</hi> here has the ſame Fate,</l>
                  <l>Which does attend <hi>Affairs</hi> of <hi>State;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The plague of <hi>Ceremony</hi> infects,</l>
                  <l>Even in <hi>Love,</hi> the Softer <hi>Sex,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who an eſſential <hi>Will</hi> neglect,</l>
                  <l>Rather than loſe the least <hi>Reſpect:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In regular <hi>Approach</hi> we ſtorm,</l>
                  <l>And never <hi>Viſit</hi> but in <hi>Form;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That is, ſending to know before,</l>
                  <l>At what a-clock they'll play the Whore.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Nymphs</hi> are conſtant, <hi>Gallants</hi> private,</l>
                  <l>One ſcarce can gueſs who 'tis they drive at,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:175034:33"/>
This ſeems to me a <hi>Scurvey Faſhion,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who have been bred in a <hi>Free Nation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Speech</hi> and <hi>Paſſion:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet cannot I forbear to <hi>Spark</hi> it,</l>
                  <l>And make the best of a <hi>Bad-market;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Meeting with One, by Chance, <hi>Kind-hearted,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who no <hi>Preliminaries</hi> ſtarted,</l>
                  <l>I enter'd beyond <hi>Expectation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Into a cloſe <hi>Negotiation;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of which, here after, a <hi>Relation:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Humble to <hi>Furtune,</hi> not her Slave,</l>
                  <l>I ſtill was pleas'd with what ſhe gave:</l>
                  <l>And with a firm and cheerful <hi>Mind,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I ſteer my Courſe with every <hi>Wind,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To all the <hi>Ports</hi> ſhe has deſign'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>G. ETHERIDGE.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:175034:34"/>
            <head>A LETTER FROM <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">To Sir GEORGE ETHERIDGE, Knight.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>TO you who live in chill Degree,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Map</hi> informs, of Fifty-three,</l>
               <l>And do not much for <hi>Cold</hi> attone,</l>
               <l>By bringing thither Fifty-one:</l>
               <l>Methinks all Climes ſhould be alike,</l>
               <l>From <hi>Tropick</hi> to the <hi>Pole Arctick,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Since you have ſuch a Conſtitution,</l>
               <l>As no where ſuffers Diminution;</l>
               <l>You can be Old in grave Debate,</l>
               <l>And Young in <hi>Love-Affairs</hi> of <hi>State;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And both to Wives and Husbands ſhow,</l>
               <l>The Vigour of a <hi>Plenipo—</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:175034:34"/>
Like mighty <hi>Miffi'ner</hi> you come,</l>
               <l>Ad partes Infidelium:</l>
               <l>A Work of wond'rous <hi>Merit</hi> ſure,</l>
               <l>So far to go, ſo much endure,</l>
               <l>And all to preach to <hi>German</hi> Dame,</l>
               <l>Where ſound of <hi>Cupid</hi> never came;</l>
               <l>Leſs had you done, had you been ſent,</l>
               <l>As far as <hi>Drake,</hi> or <hi>Pinto</hi> went</l>
               <l>For <hi>Cloves</hi> or <hi>Nutmegs</hi> to the Line-a,</l>
               <l>Or even for <hi>Oranges</hi> to <hi>China;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That had indeed been <hi>Charity,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where <hi>Love-ſick</hi> Ladies helpleſs lye,</l>
               <l>Chopt, and for want of Liquor dry.</l>
               <l>But you have made your <hi>Zeal</hi> appear,</l>
               <l>Within the Circle of the <hi>Bear;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What Region of the <hi>Earth</hi> ſo dull,</l>
               <l>That is not of your Labours full?</l>
               <l>Triptolemy, <hi>ſo ſung the</hi> Nine,</l>
               <l>Strew'd Plenty from his Cart <hi>Divine:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But, ſpite of all theſe <hi>Fable-makers,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He never ſow'd on <hi>Almain-acres;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No, that was left, by <hi>Fate</hi>'s Decree,</l>
               <l>To be perform'd and ſung by Thee.</l>
               <l>Thou break'st thro' Forms with as much eaſe,</l>
               <l>As the <hi>French King</hi> thro' Articles.</l>
               <l>In grand Affairs thy Days are ſpent,</l>
               <l>In waging weighty Compliment,</l>
               <l>With Such as <hi>Monarchs</hi> repreſent;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:175034:35"/>
They whom ſuch vast <hi>Fatigues</hi> attend,</l>
               <l>Want ſome ſoft <hi>Minutes</hi> to unbend,</l>
               <l>To ſhew the <hi>World,</hi> that now and then</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Miniſters</hi> are <hi>Mortal Men;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then <hi>Rhiniſh Rummers</hi> walk the Round,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Bumpers</hi> every <hi>King</hi> is crown'd;</l>
               <l>Beſides three Holy <hi>Miter'd Hectors,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And the whole Colledge of <hi>Electors;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No <hi>Health</hi> of <hi>Potentate</hi> is ſunk,</l>
               <l>That pays to make his <hi>Envoy</hi> drunk:</l>
               <l>Theſe <hi>Dutch</hi> Delights I mention'd last,</l>
               <l>Suit not, I know, your <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tast;</l>
               <l>For <hi>Wine,</hi> to leave a <hi>Whore</hi> or <hi>Play,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was ne'r Your <hi>Excellency</hi>'s way;</l>
               <l>Nor need the <hi>Title</hi> give <hi>Offence,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For here You were his <hi>Excellence;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For <hi>Gaming, Writing, Speaking, Keeping,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His <hi>Excellence</hi> for all but <hi>Sleeping.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now if You Tope in <hi>Form,</hi> and <hi>Treat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Tis the ſource <hi>Sawce</hi> to the <hi>Sweet Meat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Fine</hi> You pay for being <hi>Great:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nay, there's a harder <hi>Impoſition,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which is (indeed) the <hi>Court-petition,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That ſetting <hi>Worldly Pomp</hi> aſide,</l>
               <l>(Which <hi>Poet</hi> has at <hi>Font</hi> defy'd.)</l>
               <l>You wou'd be pleas'd, in humble way,</l>
               <l>To write a <hi>Trifle</hi> call'd a <hi>Play;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:175034:35"/>
This truly is a <hi>Degradation,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But wou'd oblige the <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Nation,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Next to Your wiſe <hi>Negotiation:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If You pretend, as well You may,</l>
               <l>Your high <hi>Degree;</hi> Your Friends will ſay,</l>
               <l>The Duke <hi>St. Aignan</hi> made a <hi>Play:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If <hi>Gallick Peer</hi> convince You ſcarce,</l>
               <l>His Grace of <hi>B—</hi>has writ a <hi>Farce:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And You, whoſe <hi>Comick Wit</hi> is <hi>Terſeal,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Can hardly fall below <hi>Rehearſal.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then finiſh what You once began,</l>
               <l>But ſcrible faſter, if You can:</l>
               <l>For yet no <hi>George,</hi> to our <hi>Diſcerning,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Has e're writ under ten Years <hi>Warning.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:175034:36"/>
            <head>A Letter to a Lady, that deſign'd to Marry a Courtier.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHat Irreligious Courſes have you run,</l>
               <l>That ſuch hard Penance must be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone?</l>
               <l>Have you, like Harlots, made your Tail your Trade,</l>
               <l>And whor'd you into Suſtenance and Bread?</l>
               <l>Have you to Hoſpital ſome <hi>Lover</hi> ſent?</l>
               <l>And for <hi>that</hi> Miſchief, by this worſe, repent.</l>
               <l>At <hi>Rome</hi> one Penance for their Ills they bear;</l>
               <l>But you will all in this united ſhare.</l>
               <l>None e're this dangerous Sea of Miſchief past,</l>
               <l>Who did not ſuffer, or repent at laſt.</l>
               <l>The giddy Paſſions of a youthful Mind,</l>
               <l>Are oft by Wiſhes ſway'd or Beauty blind.</l>
               <l>Girls chuſe their Husbands as they do their Cloaths;</l>
               <l>Where, if without no Fault they can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe;</l>
               <l>They eaſily eſpouſe the Pageant Show,</l>
               <l>In hopes the Colour will the Service do:</l>
               <l>So you on Marriage look, are more intent</l>
               <l>Upon a fine trimm'd Coat, than ſettlement.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:175034:36"/>
One, who tho' deſtitute of <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Senſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is ſtockt with Eſſence, Powder, and Pretence,</l>
               <l>What tho' without he ſeem deſign'd for Show,</l>
               <l>The greatest <hi>Aſs</hi> is ſtill the greatest <hi>Beau:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Aſſes</hi> always are eſteem'd by you.</l>
               <l>Don't tell me that his Promiſes are great;</l>
               <l>Who e'r forbore 'em, that deſign'd to cheat?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lovers</hi> and <hi>Courtiers,</hi> you must know, by courſe,</l>
               <l>Are much as fickle as your ſelf, or worſe:</l>
               <l>Nor that his Page that follows at his Tail,</l>
               <l>Will e're ſecure him, upon Change, from Jail.</l>
               <l>There's great Uncertainty in Human Life,</l>
               <l>And he must ſtick to's place, as well as Wife:</l>
               <l>And that, you'll ſay, is a laborious thing;</l>
               <l>All Night to ſerve his Wife, all Day the King.</l>
               <l>Don't tell me of his Gardens and Retreat;</l>
               <l>Fine Wives and Horſes ſeldom make Men great.</l>
               <l>Except we do 'em, as ſome Hackneys take,</l>
               <l>More for our Interest, than our Pleaſure's ſake:</l>
               <l>Both to recreate by turns, when first enjoy'd;</l>
               <l>But, by Poſſeſſion of them both, we're cloy'd.</l>
               <l>Would you procure a Husband for your Eaſe,</l>
               <l>Who for his <hi>Folly,</hi> not his <hi>Parts,</hi> might pleaſe;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:175034:37"/>
Then take a <hi>Stateſman,</hi> when he's gone to <hi>Court,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You may contrive how to promote your <hi>Sport.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In every Inſtant deal for freſh <hi>Delight;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And fill his <hi>Wiſhes,</hi> and his <hi>Arms</hi> at <hi>Night.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or if his <hi>Bus'neſs</hi> ben't a fit <hi>Diſguiſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To give admittance to a <hi>Harmleſs Vice:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet his great <hi>Folly</hi> will contribute ſtill</l>
               <l>To help your <hi>Wiſhes,</hi> and promote your <hi>Will.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Under the Notion of a <hi>Country Friend,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You many pretty <hi>Pleaſures</hi> may intend.</l>
               <l>But to reſerve your <hi>Virtue</hi> for a <hi>Fool,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Exceeds the <hi>Limits</hi> of <hi>Prudential Rule.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For a dull <hi>Aſs,</hi> whoſe <hi>Paſſion</hi>'s like his <hi>Brain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Rather than <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> will create your <hi>Pain.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Lover's Extaſies</hi> are ne'r ſo great,</l>
               <l>As when in <hi>Sympathetick Fire</hi> they meet:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Fools</hi> in <hi>Love,</hi> with <hi>Soldiers</hi> may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare,</l>
               <l>Who, ſtunn'd with clamorous Noiſe of <hi>Guns</hi> and <hi>War,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Are ſilently regardleſs of <hi>Command,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And, ſenſeleſs of your <hi>Pleaſure</hi> uſeleſs ſtand.</l>
               <l>Thus they, when <hi>Pulſe</hi> of <hi>Paſſion</hi> e're beats high,</l>
               <l>Seem quite regardleſs of the profer'd <hi>Joy;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:175034:37"/>
And, ignorant of the <hi>Symptoms</hi> of <hi>Delight,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Smoak out the <hi>Day,</hi> and Snore away the <hi>Night.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Don't tell me, You'r exceſſively in <hi>Love;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Your <hi>Wit</hi> will ſoon that vain <hi>Pretence</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Blockheads</hi> much labour'd under that of old;</l>
               <l>But none dies now, but for their Darling, <hi>Gold.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Great is your <hi>Love,</hi> and great the <hi>Riſque</hi> you run,</l>
               <l>To be <hi>Unhappy,</hi> or at least <hi>Undone.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thoſe <hi>Pleaſures</hi> Young <hi>Girls</hi> fancy are ſo Good,</l>
               <l>Are ſeldom <hi>felt,</hi> but always <hi>underſtood.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Tis but the <hi>Magick Spell,</hi> which <hi>Nature</hi> yields,</l>
               <l>To bring ſuch untry'd <hi>Lovers</hi> to its Fields:</l>
               <l>A ſpecious <hi>Bait,</hi> fit <hi>Mankind</hi> to enſlave,</l>
               <l>And to bereave us of the <hi>Joys</hi> we have.</l>
               <l>Wou'd you be vertuous, get a <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Juice,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fertile in <hi>Wit,</hi> and of his <hi>Love</hi> profuſe;</l>
               <l>For only ſuch are fit for <hi>Womens</hi> Uſe:</l>
               <l>Where you in mutual <hi>Bonds</hi> of <hi>Joy</hi> may range,</l>
               <l>And in your <hi>Kiſſes</hi> may your <hi>Souls</hi> exchange.</l>
               <l>One, with ſuch <hi>Qualities,</hi> wou'd a <hi>Nun</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite,</l>
               <l>To quit <hi>Eternal Day</hi> for <hi>Earthly Night.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:175034:38"/>
Such would your laviſh Wiſhes all engage,</l>
               <l>And guard your Vertue as ſecure as Age.</l>
               <l>In Joys unknown you then might paſs the Day,</l>
               <l>Till Night ſhall take the <hi>Sun</hi>'s bright Beams away,</l>
               <l>And both in clammy Joys, and Slumber, quit the Fray.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:175034:38"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To Mr.</hi> Congreve.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE laſt Fortnight which I paſt in Town, and the firſt which I paſt in the Country, I had ſo much Sickneſs, and ſo much Spleen, that the greateſt Kindneſs I could do my <hi>Friends,</hi> was, to let them know nothing of me. And yet, unleſs I had been ſilent ſo long, I ſhould hardly know what to write to you. The Excuſe for having held my Tongue, affords me Matter to talk of. Otherwiſe I could find nothing to ſay to you, unleſs I would ſend you Profeſſions of <hi>Friendſhip;</hi> which, I hope, are wholly needleſs: or entertain you with Talk of my ſelf. And I am yet more unwilling to do the laſt than the firſt: For I have obſerv'd, That, for the moſt part, a Man who talks much of Himſelf, talks of a Subject which he does not at all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand. But you are to be excepted from this General Rule; and you could oblige me with nothing more grateful
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:175034:39"/>
than ſome News of your ſelf. I long to know how you proceed in your <hi>Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> and ſhould be glad to be inform'd how many are making a Party for it; that is, how many are writing Plays be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides. I make no doubt but it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at the Head of a numerous Train; yet I believe you will have reaſon to be aſham'd of ſome of your Equipage. I hear of three or four, who have a couple of Plays a-piece, which are to go into the Houſe, as Vermin entred into the <hi>Ark,</hi> by Pairs; where they are both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and preſerved with as much care, as the moſt Reaſonable, and the moſt Noble Productions. Since <hi>Providence</hi> will have it ſo, we ought to conclude, that it is fitting it ſhould be ſo. And indeed, why may not their <hi>Songs</hi> and <hi>Madri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gals,</hi> and abſurd and Speechleſs <hi>Farces,</hi> help to conſtitute the Beauty and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the <hi>Intellectual World,</hi> as well as <hi>Owls,</hi> and <hi>Stotes,</hi> and <hi>Polecats,</hi> do that of <hi>Material Beings.</hi> However, theſe Fellows Productions are fit to diſcover one Truth to us, which we ſhould not have imagin'd without them; and that is, That there are greater <hi>Sots</hi> than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; for ſuch are all their Applauders.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:175034:39"/>
But to leave them for better Company, give my Service to all my <hi>Friends</hi> at <hi>Will's;</hi> both to thoſe who ſhew their Wit by their Writing, and to thoſe who by their Silence ſhew their Judgments. Tell—and—and—, that I would fain know of them; nay, and of you too; ſo as <hi>D</hi>—ſays, <hi>What a Devil have I done to you, that you cannot let a Man alone in his</hi> Solitude, <hi>but that you must diſturb the</hi> Tranquility <hi>of his Mind:</hi> I mean that little I have here. For hither come your <hi>Idea's</hi> at Five eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Day preciſely, and give me furious Deſires to be at <hi>Covent-garden.</hi> I am forced to make uſe of a little piece of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy;</hi> for I fancy you Quibling there, and then I am as calm as a Matron. For I am apt to believe, that I have better Diverſion here. I am lately, you muſt know, grown a great <hi>Angler;</hi> perhaps, the greateſt Man in the Age for <hi>Gudgeon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſhing;</hi> tho' I ſay it, who ſhould not ſay it. That is Paſtime which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably you may deſpiſe. However, as I take it, it is better than lying upon the <hi>Catch</hi> at <hi>Will's,</hi> and laying Snares for Puns, as Spiders do for Flies. But I am about to fall into the Vice, which I
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:175034:40"/>
deſign'd to avoid For I am about to talk of My ſelf to you, which is a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of which I am ſure I ought to ſay nothing, ſince it's needleſs to aſſure you, that I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Servant.</signed>
               <dateline>Newport, <date>
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> 96.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:175034:40"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To Mr.</hi> Wycherley.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THo' I have enough to alledge in the behalf of my Silence, to excuſe it to any Man living but You; yet I have always profeſs'd that peculiar Eſteem for you, that to make a ſufficient Apology for my ſelf, when Appearances are ſo much againſt me, I had need have an equal ſhare of Wit with You. But ſince I come infinitely ſhort of that, You would oblige me extreamly, if You would inſtruct me by the next Poſt, what Thoughts and what Words I ſhould uſe to make You forgive me. Yet to engage You to that, I know You expect ſomething at leaſt that is like Wit from me. But You may every jot as reaſonably expect a luſty Letter of Credit from me. And who the Devil, at this Conjuncture, ſhould expect, that the Poſt ſhould bring either Wit or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney with him, when the Paper-credit of the Nation is loſt in relation to both. Yet we have reaſon to believe, ſince You are reſolv'd to turn Author again, that You may retrieve it in regard to one of them. I wiſh You all the Succeſs to which Your
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:175034:41"/>
Merit entitles You; and that is another Reaſon to make me wiſh for a Peace. For the Men who are able to judge, have now no leiſure to read: They who have the greateſt ſhare of Wit and Spirit, being engaged in the Armies, or in Affairs. When <hi>Apollo</hi> now-a-days inſpires a Poet, he did as when he fed <hi>Admetus</hi> his Sheep, and the God ſings now to Cattle. Wit certainly never was at ſo low an Ebb, of which the <hi>Coffee-houſe</hi> is a lamentable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, as it is a miſerable Spectacle. When you, and one or two more went out of Town, the great Supports of Politeneſs left it, and then the Enemy broke in upon us; and ſcarce any thing has appear'd ever ſince in it, unleſs it be that Anti-wit, a Gameſter. We almoſt regret thoſe moments of abominable Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, when Puns flew about as thick as Squibs upon a City-Feſtival. Even Quib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and Quarter-quibbles, if they could now be found, would be as much valued as Vermin are in Dearths. But what ſhall we ſay?
<q>
                  <l>—<hi>Etiam periere ruinae.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The very Ruines of Wit have periſh'd.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>So much of the <hi>Coffee-houſe</hi> in general.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:175034:41"/>
Now for one or two of the noble Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in particular. And firſt, I have Wonders to tell you of <hi>Lucifer:</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quod optanti Divum promittere nemo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Auderet, volvenda dies, en, attulit ultro.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucifer</hi> is grown the moſt regular Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in the Univerſe: For he riſes ſtill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly after Sun-ſetting, and goes to Bed ſtill preciſely before Sun-riſing; and he and his Father, I mean his Spiritual Father, that is, his Father <hi>Phoebus,</hi> live juſt as he and his Natural Father did, without ever ſeeing the Face of one another. But he has juſt ſent a Meſſage to me from the the <hi>Roſe;</hi> where, as the Drawer tells me, he has the moſt earneſt Buſineſs in the World with me. The moſt earneſt Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the World to <hi>Lucifer,</hi> is, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing a Man to ſit up till five with him. However, I will juſt go and hear what he ſays, and drink Mr. <hi>Wycherley</hi>'s Health with him. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Dear Sir, </salute>
               <signed>Your most humble Servant, J. Dennis.</signed>
               <dateline>Lond. <date>Sept. 10, 1696.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:175034:42"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To</hi> Dorinda.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>OH! how tedious is Abſence from the Perſons we adore! And with what killing Anguiſh did I receive the doleful News of your Departure! Where a mutual Inclination has united two ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Hearts, a Separation is more inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable than Death it ſelf: Yet if my <hi>Dorinda</hi> left the Town without a Sigh, I am more miſerable ſtill. You could not ſure forget (ſo ſoon at leaſt) all thoſe obliging Vows you ſo fervently made; Vows, whoſe Solemnity and Frequency were no inconſiderable part of my Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city. Alas! 'tis equally impoſſible for me to expreſs the Horrors I now feel, or the powerful Luſtre of thoſe victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Eyes, that gave Birth to my raging Paſſion. Since that fatal Minute, that raviſh'd from me all my Joys, in your leaving <hi>London,</hi> Heaven's my Witneſs, and every Divinity that conſpir'd my Ruine; nay, by your own belov'd Self I
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:175034:42"/>
ſwear, (the greateſt Oath my Love can invent) That my Heart has known no other Bliſs than the endearing Thoughts of you. The pleaſing <hi>Idea</hi> your irreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable Beauties have imprinted on my faithful Breaſt, at preſent conſtitutes all the eaſie Moments I enjoy; and how few they muſt be, under the rated Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of being depriv'd of your Sight, none can know, but thoſe that love as well. Two Poſt-days are now paſt, and not one Line from my <hi>Dorinda!</hi> Oh! what can mean this Silence? Do you then joyn with <hi>Fate</hi> to break a Heart, that would not vouchſafe to live, but to be yours? An unuſual Shivering darts through every Vein, and my drooping Spirits preſage ſome other evil, which your unhappy <hi>Strephon</hi> muſt undergo. Were it only want of Health, and not of Love, that prevented your writing, my grief wou'd be leſs wounding. You may have a Feaver; but that you ſhou'd be falſe, I will not as yet believe poſſible. One Proof of your Infidelity would ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate all my Pain: For I were utterly unworthy of your Affection, if mine cou'd ſupport ſo fatal an Aſſurance. But ſuch Suſpicions are injurious; and I wou'd
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:175034:43"/>
rather queſtion the Teſtimony of my Senſes, than think you were Untrue. Oh! let me hear from you, tho' but one Word; the Rigors of Abſence from your Arms and Eyes, will be leſs intolerable: Till then, my Torments are more than <hi>Arithmetick</hi> can number, or <hi>Rhetorick</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe. Oh, <hi>Dorinda!</hi> that I were at your Feet, to give you freſh Aſſurances of the Inviolableneſs of my Paſſion, whoſe Greatneſs was once your Wonder and Delight.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letters_and_speeches">
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:175034:43"/>
            <head>LETTERS AND <hi>SPEECHES,</hi> ON SEVERAL SUBJECTS, By the Late Duke of Buckingham.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>To the Lord</hi> Bercley.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My LORD,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Muſt needs beg your Lordſhip's Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, for not waiting upon you next <hi>Sunday</hi> at Dinner, for two Reaſons: The firſt is, Becauſe Mrs. <hi>B</hi>—refuſes to hear me preach; which I take to be a kind Slur upon ſo learned a Divine as I am. The other, That Sir <hi>Robert Cl</hi>—<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is to go into the Country upon <hi>Monday,</hi> and has deſir'd me to ſtay within to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:175034:44"/>
Morrow, about Signing ſome Papers, which muſt be diſpatch'd for the Clearing ſo much of my Eſtate, as in ſpite of my own Negligence, and the extraordinary Perquiſits I have receiv'd from the Court, is yet left me. I'm ſure your Lordſhip is too much my Friend, not to give me Leave to look after my Temporal Affairs, if you do but conſider how little I'm like to get by my Spirituality, except Mrs. <hi>B</hi>—be very much in the wrong: Pray, tell her I am reſolv'd hereafter, never to to ſwear by any other than <hi>Jo. Aſh;</hi> and if that be a Sin, 'tis as odd a one as ever ſhe heard of. I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>My Lord, </salute> 
                  <signed>Your Lordſhip's most humble, and most faithful Servant,
Buckingham.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:175034:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> DUKE'<hi>s</hi> Speech <hi>in a Conference.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Gentlemen of the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi>
                  </salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am commanded by the Houſe of <hi>Peers,</hi> to open to you the Matter of this Conference; which is a Task I could wiſh their Lordſhips had been pleas'd to lay upon Any-body elſe, both for their own ſakes and mine: Having obſerv'd, in that little Experience I have made in the World, there can be nothing of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Difficulty, than to Unite Men in their Opinions, whoſe Intereſts ſeem to diſagree.</p>
               <p>This, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> I fear, is at preſent our Caſe; but yet I hope, when we have a little better conſider'd of it, we ſhall find, that a greater Intereſt does oblige us at this time, rather to joyn in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of both our Priviledges, than to differ about the Violation of either.</p>
               <p>We acknowledge it is our Intereſt to defend the Right of the <hi>Commons;</hi> for, ſhould we ſuffer them to be oppreſt, it
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:175034:45"/>
would not be long before it might come to be our own Caſe: And I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it will alſo appear to be the Intereſt of the <hi>Commons,</hi> to uphold the Priviledge of the <hi>Lords;</hi> that ſo we may be in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to ſtand by and ſupport them.</p>
               <p>All that their <hi>Lordſhips</hi> deſire of you on this Occaſion, is, That you will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed with them as uſually Friends do, when they are in Diſpute one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, That you will not be impatient of hearing Arguments urged againſt your Opinions, but examine the Weight of what is ſaid, and then impartially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider which of us two, are likelieſt to be in the wrong.</p>
               <p>If we are in the wrong, we and our Predeceſſors have been ſo for theſe many hundred of Years; and not only our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, but yours too: This being the firſt time that ever an Appeal was made in point of Judicature, from the <hi>Lords</hi> Houſe, to the houſe of <hi>Commons.</hi> Nay, thoſe very <hi>Commons,</hi> which turn'd the <hi>Lords</hi> out of this Houſe, tho' they took from them many other of their Privileges, yet left them the conſtant Practice of this till the very laſt day of their Sitting. And
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:175034:45"/>
this will be made appear by ſeveral Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedents, theſe Noble <hi>Lords</hi> will lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, much better than I can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to do.</p>
               <p>Since this Buſineſs has been in Agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, their <hi>Lordſhips</hi> have been a little more curious than ordinary, to inform themſelves of the true nature of theſe Matters now in Queſtion before Us; which I ſhall endeavour to explain to you, as far as my ſmall Ability, and my Averſion to hard Words will give me leave. For howſoever the Law, to make it a Myſtery and a Trade, may be wrapt up in Terms of Art, yet it is founded in Reaſon, and is obvious to common Sence.</p>
               <p>The Power of Judicature does natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſcend, and not aſcend; that is, no Inferiour Court can have any Power, which is not deriv'd to it from ſome Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er above it.</p>
               <p>The <hi>King</hi> is, by the Laws of this Land, Supreme Judge, in all Cauſes Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and Civil. And ſo there is no Court, High or Low, can Act, but in Subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to Him; and tho' they do not all Iſſue out their Writs in the <hi>King</hi>'s Name,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:175034:46"/>
yet they can Iſſue out none but by Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of ſome Power they have received from Him.</p>
               <p>Now every particular Court has ſuch particular Power as the <hi>King</hi> has given it, and for that reaſon has it Bounds: But the Higheſt Court, in which the <hi>King</hi> can poſſible Sit; that is, His Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Court of <hi>Lords</hi> in Parliament, has in it all Judicial Power, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently no Bounds: I mean, no Bounds of Juriſdiction; for the Higheſt Court is to Govern according to the Laws, as well as the Loweſt.</p>
               <p>I ſuppoſe none will make a Queſtion, but that every Man, and every Cauſe, is to be tried according to <hi>Magna Charta;</hi> that is, by Peers, or according to the Laws of the Land. And he that is tried by the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, the Court of Admiralty, or the High Court of <hi>Lords</hi> in Parliament, is tried as much by the Laws of the Land, as he that is tried by the <hi>King's-Bench,</hi> or <hi>Common-Pleas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When theſe Inferior Courts happen to wrangle among themſelves, which they muſt often do, by reaſon of their being bound up to particular Cauſes, and their
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:175034:46"/>
having all equally and earneſtly a Deſire to try all Cauſes themſelves, then the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Court is forc'd to hear their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, becauſe there is no other way of deciding them. And this, under favour, is an Original Cauſe of Courts, tho' not of Men.</p>
               <p>Now, theſe Original Cauſes of Courts, muſt alſo of neceſſity induce Men, for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of Charges, and Diſpatch ſake, to bring their Cauſe originally before the Supreme Court. But then the Court is not obliged to receive them; but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds by Rules of Prudence, in either retaining, or diſmiſſing them, as they think fit.</p>
               <p>This is, under Favour, the ſum of all that your Precedents can ſhew us; which is nothing but what we practiſe every day: That is, that very often, becauſe we would not be moleſted with hearing too many particular Caſes, we refer them back to other Courts. And all the Argument you can poſſibly draw from hence, will not in any kind leſſen our Power, but only ſhew an Unwillingneſs we have, to trouble our ſelves often with Matters of this Nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:175034:47"/>
Nor will this appear ſtrange, if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Conſtitution of our Houſe; it being made up, partly of ſuch whoſe Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments will not give them leiſure to attend the Hearing of Private Cauſes; and entirely of thoſe that can receive no Profit by it.</p>
               <p>And the truth is, the Diſpute at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent is not between the Houſe of <hi>Lords,</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> but between Us and <hi>Weſtminſter-hall:</hi> For, as we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to have few or no Cauſes brought before us, becauſe we get nothing by 'em; ſo they deſire to have all Cauſes brought before them, for a Reaſon a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the contrary nature.</p>
               <p>For this very Reaſon, it is their Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to invent new ways of drawing Cauſes to their Courts, which ought not to be pleaded there. As for example, this very Cauſe of <hi>Skinner,</hi> that is now before us, (and I do not ſpeak this by Roat, for I have the Opinion of a Reverend Judge in the Caſe, who informed us of it the other day in the Houſe;) they have no way of bringing this Cauſe into <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter-hall,</hi> but by this Form, the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:175034:47"/>
and Sence of which I leave to you to judge of:</p>
               <p>The Form is this, That inſtead of ſpeaking as we ordinary Men do, that have no Art, That Mr. <hi>Skinner</hi> loſt a Ship in the <hi>East-Indies;</hi> to bring this into their Courts, they muſt ſay, That Mr. <hi>Skinner</hi> loſt a Ship in the <hi>East-Indies,</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Iſlington,</hi> in the County of <hi>Middleſex.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſome of us, <hi>Lords,</hi> that did not underſtand the Refineneſs of this Stile, began to examine what the reaſon of this ſhould be; and ſo we found, that ſince they ought not by Right to try ſuch Cauſes, they are reſolved to make bold, not only with our Priviledges, but the very Sence and Language of the whole Nation.</p>
               <p>This I thought fit to mention, only to let you ſee, that this whole Cauſe, as well as many others, could not be try'd pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly in any place but at our Bar; except Mr. <hi>Skinner</hi> would have taken a Fancy, to try the Right of Juriſdictions between <hi>Weſtminſter-hall</hi> and the Court of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty, inſtead of ſeeking Relief for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:175034:48"/>
he had received in the place, only where it was to be given him.</p>
               <p>One thing I hear is much inſiſted upon which is, The Trial without Juries; to which I could anſwer, That ſuch Trials are allow'd of in the <hi>Chancery,</hi> and other Courts: and, that when there is occaſion for them, we make uſe of Juries too, both by directing them in the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Bench,</hi> and having them brought up to our Bar.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall only crave leave to put you in mind, That if you do not allow Us, in ſome Caſes, to try Men without Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, you will then abſolutely take away the uſe of Impeachments; which I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conceive you will not think proper to have done at this time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:175034:48"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> Duke'<hi>s</hi> Speech <hi>in the Houſe of</hi> Lords.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My LORDS,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THere is a Thing call'd <hi>Property,</hi> which (whatever ſome Men may think) is that the People of <hi>England</hi> are fondeſt of, it is that they will never part with, and it is that His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> in His <hi>Speech,</hi> has promis'd Us to take a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular care of.</p>
               <p>This, my <hi>Lords,</hi> in my Opinion, can never be done, without giving an <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> to all <hi>Proteſtant-Diſſenters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is certainly a very uneaſie kind of Life to any Man that has either <hi>Chriſtian Charity, Humanity,</hi> or <hi>Good-nature,</hi> to ſee his Fellow-ſubjects daily abus'd, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted of their Liberty and Birth-rights, and miſerably thrown out of their Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Freeholds, only becauſe they cannot agree with others in ſome <hi>Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Religion,</hi> which their <hi>Conſciences</hi> will not give them leave to conſent to; and which, even by the Confeſſion of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:175034:49"/>
Thoſe who would Impoſe it upon them, is no way neceſſary to <hi>Salvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, my <hi>Lords,</hi> beſides this, and all that may be ſaid upon it, in order to the Improvement of our Trade, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the Wealth, Strength, and Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this <hi>Nation,</hi> (which, under Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, I ſhall preſume to diſcourſe of at ſome other time) there is, methinks, in this Notion of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> a very groſs Miſtake, both as to the Point of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and the Point of <hi>Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is ſo as to the Point of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> becauſe it makes every Man's Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty depend on the wrong place, not upon the <hi>Governour,</hi> or a Man's living well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Civil Government</hi> eſtabliſhed by <hi>Law,</hi> but upon his being tranſported with Zeal for every Opinion that is held by thoſe that have Power in the <hi>Church</hi> then in Faſhion.</p>
               <p>And it is, I conceive, a Miſtake in <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> becauſe it is poſitively againſt the expreſs Doctrine and Example of <hi>Jeſus Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay, my <hi>Lords,</hi> as to our <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> there is ſomething in it yet
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:175034:49"/>
worſe; for we <hi>Proteſtants</hi> maintain, That none of thoſe OPINIONS, which <hi>Chriſtians</hi> differ about, are <hi>Infallible;</hi> and therefore in Us, it is ſomewhat an inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable Conception, <hi>That Men ought to be deprived of their Inheritance, and all the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Conveniences and Advantages of Life, becauſe they will not agree with us in our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain Opinions of</hi> Religion.</p>
               <p>My humble Motion therefore, to your Lordſhips, is, <hi>That you will give me leave to bring in a Bill of</hi> Indulgence <hi>to all</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting-Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>I know very well, That every <hi>Peer</hi> of the Realm has a Right to bring into <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> any Bill which he conceives to be uſeful to this <hi>Nation:</hi> but I thought it more reſpectful to your Lordſhips, to ask your Leave for it before; I cannot think the doing of it will be of any Prejudice to the Bill, becauſe I am confident the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the Prudence, and the Charitableneſs of it, will be able to juſtifie it ſelf to this <hi>Houſe,</hi> and to the whole <hi>World.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:175034:50"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> DUKE'<hi>S</hi> SPEECH <hi>in the Houſe of</hi> LORDS.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My LORDS,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have often troubled your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> with my Diſcourſe in this <hi>Houſe;</hi> but, I confeſs, I never did it with more trouble to my ſelf, than I do at this time, for I ſcarce know where I ſhould begin, or what I have to ſay to your <hi>Lordſhips:</hi> On the one ſide, I am afraid of being thought an Unquiet and Pragmatical Man; for, in this Age, every Man that cannot bear every thing, is called Unquiet; and he that does but ask Queſtions, for which he ought to be concerned, is looked upon as a Pragmatical. On the other ſide, I am more afraid of being thought a diſhoneſt Man; and of all Men, I am moſt afraid of being thought ſo by my ſelf; for every one is beſt Judge of the Integrity of his own Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And tho' it does not always follow, that he is Pragmatical whom others take to be ſo; yet this never fails to be true, That he is moſt certainly a Knave, who takes himſelf to be ſo. No body is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable for more Underſtanding than
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:175034:50"/>
                  <hi>GOD</hi> Almighty had given him: And therefore, tho' I ſhould be in the wrong, if I tell your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> truly and plainly what I am really convic'd of, I ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have my ſelf like an honeſt Man: For 'tis my Duty, as long as I have the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to ſit in this <hi>Houſe,</hi> to hide nothing from your <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> which, I think, may concern either his <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s Service, your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> Intereſt, or the Good and Quiet of the People of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Queſtion, in my Opinion, which now lies before your <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> is not what we are to do, but whether at this time we can do any thing as a Parliament; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very clear to me, that the Parliament; is Diſſolved: And if, in this Opinion, I have the Misfortune to be miſtaken, I have another Misfortune joyned in it, I Deſire to maintain the Argument with all the Judges and Lawyers in <hi>England,</hi> and leave it afterwards for your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> to decide, whether I am in the right or no.</p>
               <p>This, my <hi>Lords,</hi> I ſpeak not out of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogance, but in my own Juſtification; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if I were not thoroughly convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that what I have now to urge were grounded upon the Fundamental Laws
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:175034:51"/>
of <hi>England;</hi> and that the not preſſing it at this time might prove to be of a moſt dangerous Conſequence, both to his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> and the whole Nation, I ſhould have been loth to ſtart a Motion, which perhaps may not be very agreeable to ſome People: And yet, my <hi>Lords,</hi> when I conſider where I am, whom I now ſpeak to, and what was ſpoken in this Place, about the time of the laſt Proroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I can hardly believe that what I have to ſay, will be diſtaſteful to your <hi>Lordſhips.</hi> I remember very well how your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> were then diſpoſed with the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> and remember too as well what Reaſons they gave to be ſo: It is not ſo long ſince, but that I ſuppoſe your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> may eaſily call to mind, that after ſeveral odd Paſſages between Us, your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> were ſo incenſed, that a Motion was made here for an Addreſs to his <hi>Majeſty</hi> about the Diſſolution of this Parliament; and tho' it fail'd of being car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the Affirmative, by two or three Voices, yet this in the Debate was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, the Cit prevail'd much with the Major part of your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> that were here preſent, and were only over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power'd by the Proxies of thoſe <hi>Lords,</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:175034:51"/>
who never heard the Argument. What change there hath been ſince, either in their behaving, or in the ſtate of our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, that ſhould make your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> change your Opinions, I have not heard; and therefore, if I can make it appear, (as I preſume I ſhall) that by Law the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament is diſſolv'd, I hope your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> ought not to be offended at me for it.</p>
               <p>I have often wondred how it ſhould come to paſs, that this <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> in which there are ſo many honeſt, and ſo many worthy Gentlemen, ſhould be leſs reſpectful to your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> (as certainly they have been) than any <hi>Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> that ever were choſen in <hi>England;</hi> and yet, if the matter be a little enquir'd into, the Reaſon of it will plainly appear: For, my <hi>Lords,</hi> the very Nature of the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> is changed; they do not think now they are an Aſſembly that are to return to their Houſes, and become as private. Men again (as by the Laws of the Land, and the Ancient Conſtitution of Parliament, they ought to do) but they look upon themſelves as a ſtanding Senate, and as a Company of Men pick'd out to be <hi>Legiſlators</hi> for the reſt of their whole Lives; and if that be the cauſe, my
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:175034:52"/>
                  <hi>Lords,</hi> they have reaſon to believe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves our Equals. But, my <hi>Lords,</hi> it is a dangerous thing to try new Experiments in Government. Men do not foreſee the ill Conſequences that muſt happen, when they go about to alter thoſe Eſſential parts of it, upon which the whole Frame of the Government depends, as now in our Fall the Cuſtoms and Conſtitutions of Parliaments; for all Governments are artificial things, and every part of them has a Dependance one upon another. As in Clocks and Watches, if you ſhould put great Wheels in the room of little ones, and little ones in the place of great ones, all the Fabrick would ſtand ſtill: So you cannot alter any one part of the Government, without prejudicing the Motions of the whole. If this, my <hi>Lords,</hi> were well conſidered, People would be more cautious how they went out of the old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Way and Method of Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. But it is not my buſineſs to find fault, and therefore, if your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> will give me leave, I ſhall go on to ſhew you, why, in my Opinion, we are at this time no Parliament.</p>
               <p>The ground of this Opinion of mine, is taken from the ancient and unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:175034:52"/>
State of this Realm: And give me leave to tell your <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> by the way, that Statutes are not like Women, for they are not one jot the worſe for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Old.</p>
               <p>The firſt Statute that I ſhall take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, is That in the Fourth Year of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, <hi>Cap.</hi> 14. and it is thus ſet down in the Printed Book, Item, <hi>It is accorded, that a Parliament ſhall be holden every Year once, and more often, if need be.</hi> Now theſe Words be as plain as a Pike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaff, and that no Man living that is not a Scholar, could poſſibly miſtake the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them. It is the Grammarians of thoſe Days did make a ſhift to explain, that the Words, <hi>If need be,</hi> did relate as well to the Words, <hi>Every Year once,</hi> as to the Words, <hi>More often.</hi> And ſo by this Grammatical Whimſey of theirs, had made this Statute to ſignifie juſt nothing at all. For this Reaſon, my <hi>Lords,</hi> in the 36th Year of the ſame <hi>King</hi>'s Reign, a new Act of Parliament was made, in which thoſe unfortunate Words, <hi>If need be,</hi> are left out, and that Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is Printed thus, relating to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and other Statutes, made for the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:175034:53"/>
Publick Good; Item, <hi>For maintainance of theſe Articles and Statutes, and the Redreſs of divers Miſchiefs and Grievances, which daily happen, a Parliament ſhall be holden every Year, as at other time was ordained by another.</hi> Here now, my <hi>Lords,</hi> there is not left the leaſt Colour or Shadow for any further Miſtake; for it is plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, That the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi> muſt call a Parliament once within a Year: And the Reaſons why they are bound to do ſo, are as plainly ſet down; namely, For the Maintenance of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and other Statutes of the ſame Import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and for the preventing the Miſchiefs and Grievances which daily happen.</p>
               <p>The Queſtion then remains, Whether theſe Statutes have been ſince repealed by any other Statutes, or no? The only Statutes I ever heard mention'd for that, are the two Triennial Bills, the one made in the laſt <hi>King</hi>'s, the other made in this <hi>King</hi>'s Reign. The Triennial Bill in the laſt <hi>King</hi>'s Reign, was made for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the two Statutes of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, before-mention'd: For Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments having been omitted every Year, according to theſe Statutes, a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:175034:53"/>
was made in the laſt <hi>King</hi>'s Reign to this purpoſe, That if the <hi>King</hi> ſhould fail of Calling a Parliament according to theſe Statutes of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, then the third Year the People ſhould Meet of Themſelves, without any Writs at all, and chooſe their Parliament-men of Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. This being thought diſreſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the <hi>King,</hi> a Statute was made by this laſt Parliament, which repealed the Triennial Bill; but after the Repealing Clauſe, which took notice only of the Triennial Bill made in the laſt <hi>King</hi>'s Reign, there was then in this Statute a Paragraph to this purpoſe, That becauſe the ancient Statutes of the Realm, made in <hi>Edward</hi> the Third's Reign, Parliaments were to be holden very often, it ſhould be Enacted, That within three Years after the Determination of that preſent Parliament, Parliaments ſhould not be diſcontinued above three Years at moſt, and ſhould be holden oftner, if need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. Theſe have been ſeveral falſe kind of Arguments drawn out of theſe Triennial Bills againſt the Statutes of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third; which, I confeſs I could never remember; nor, indeed, thoſe that urged them to me ever durſt
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:175034:54"/>
own; for they always laid their Faults upon Some-body elſe: Like ugly aufiſh Children, which, becauſe of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity and want of Wit, the Parents are aſhamed of, and ſo turn them out to the Pariſh. But, my <hi>Lords,</hi> let the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be what it will, I will have this ſhort Anſwer to all that can be wreſted out of the Triennial Bills, That the firſt Triennial Bill was repeal'd before the matter now diſputed of was in queſtion; and the laſt Triennial Bill will not be of force till the Queſtion be decided; that is, till the Parliament be Diſſolved. The whole matter therefore, my <hi>Lords,</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to this ſhort <hi>Dilemma,</hi> Either the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England</hi> are bound by the Acts mentioned of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, or elſe the whole Government of <hi>England</hi> by Parliament, and by Law, is abſolutely at an end: For if the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England</hi> have Power, by an Order of theirs, to inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidate an Act made for the Maintenance of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> they have alſo a Power, by an Order of theirs, to invalidate <hi>Magna Charta</hi> it ſelf; and if they have Power, by an Order of theirs, to invalidate an Act made for the Maintenance of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute <hi>De Talligio non concedendo,</hi> they have
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:175034:54"/>
alſo a Power, when they pleaſe, by an Order of theirs, to invalidate the Statute it ſelf; and they may, not only without the Help of Parliament, raiſe what Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney they pleaſe, but alſo take away any Man's Eſtate when they pleaſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive one of his Liberty and Life, if they pleaſe. This, my Lords, is a Power, I think, that no Judge or Lawyer will pretend the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England</hi> have; and yet this Power muſt be allowed them, or elſe we that are met here this Day can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not act as a Parliament; for we are not met by vertue of the laſt Prorogation; then Prorogation is an Order of the <hi>King</hi>'s, and a point-blank Contrary to the two Acts of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third: For the Acts ſay, <hi>That a Parliament ſhall be holden within a Year.</hi> And the Proroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſays, <hi>That Parliaments ſhall not be held within a Year, but ſome Months after.</hi> This, I conceive, is a plain Contradiction, and conſequently that the Prorogation is void.</p>
               <p>Now, if we cannot act as a Parliament, by vertue of the laſt Prorogation, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech your <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> by vertue of what elſe can we act? Shall we act by vertue of the <hi>King</hi>'s Proclamation? Pray, my
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:175034:55"/>
                  <hi>Lords,</hi> how ſo? Is a Proclamation of more force than a Prorogation? Or if any thing that has been ordered a firſt time be not valued, does the ordering it a ſecond time make it good in Law? I have heard, indeed, That two Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives make an Affirmative: But I never heard before, That two Nothings ever made Any-thing. Well; but how then do we meet? Is it by our own Adjourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? I hope that No-body has the Confidence to ſay ſo. Which way then is it we do meet here? By an Accident: That, I think, may be granted. But an accidental Meeting can no more make a Parliament, than an Accidental Clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of a Crown on a Man's Head can make a <hi>King.</hi> There is a great deal of Ceremony required to give a Matter of that Moment a Legal Sanction. The Laws have repos'd ſo great Truſt and Power in the Hands of the Parliament, that every Circumſtance relating to the manner of their Electing, Meeting, and Proceeding, is lookt after with the moſt Circumſpection imaginable. For this Reaſon the <hi>King</hi>'s Writs about the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of Parliament are to be iſſued out <hi>verbatim,</hi> according to the Form Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:175034:55"/>
by the Laws, or elſe the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is void, and nulled. For the ſame Reaſon, that a Parliament is ſummoned by the <hi>King</hi>'s Writs, does not meet at the very ſame Day it's ſummoned to meet at, that Parliament is void and nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; and by the ſame Reaſon, if a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be not legally Adjourned <hi>de die &amp; in diem,</hi> theſe Parliaments muſt alſo be void, and nulled. O, but ſome ſay, there is nothing in the two Acts of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, to take away the <hi>King</hi>'s Power in Prorogation, therefore Prorogation is good.</p>
               <p>My <hi>Lords,</hi> under Favour, it is a very groſs Miſtake: For pray, examine the Words of the Acts; and the Acts ſay, <hi>Parliaments ſhall be holden Once a Year.</hi> Now, to whom can theſe Words be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, but to them that are to call a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament? And who are they, but the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England?</hi> It is very true, this does not take away the <hi>King</hi>'s Power of Proroguing Parliaments, but it moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly limits it to be within a Year.</p>
               <p>Well then, it is ſaid again, <hi>If the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roguing be null and void, then things are just as they were before:</hi> And therefore the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament is ſtill in being.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:175034:56"/>
My <hi>Lords,</hi> I confeſs there would be ſome weight in this, but for one thing, which is, That not one word is true; for if, when the <hi>King</hi> had prorogued, we had taken no notice of his prorogation, but had gone on like a Parliament, and had adjourn'd our ſelves the <hi>die in diem,</hi> then I confeſs things had been juſt as they were before: but ſince, upon the Prorogation, we went away, and took no care our ſelves for our Meeting again, if we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not meet and act again by virtue of the Prorogations; here is an Impoſſibility of our Meeting and Acting any other way; and one may as probably ſay, that a Man, who is killed by Aſſault, is ſtill alive, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Aſſault was unlawful.</p>
               <p>The next Arguments that thoſe are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to, who would maintain to be yet a Parliament, is, That the Parliament is prorogued <hi>ſine die,</hi> and therefore a <hi>King</hi> may call them by Proclamation.</p>
               <p>To the firſt part of the Propoſition, I ſhall not only agree with them, but alſo do them the Favour to prove, that it is ſo in the Eye of the Law, which I have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard they have yet done: For the Statutes ſay, <hi>A Parliament ſhall be had once within a Year.</hi> And that Prorogation
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:175034:56"/>
having put them off till a Day without the Year, and conſequently excepted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt by the Law, that Day, in the Eye of the Law, is no Day at all, that is <hi>ſine die,</hi> and the Prorogation might as well have put them off till ſo many Days after Doomſday; and then, I think, No-body would have doubted but that had been a very ſufficient Diſſolution. Beſides, my <hi>Lords,</hi> I ſhall deſire your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> to take notice, That, in former time, the uſual way of Diſſolving Parliament, was to diſmiſs them <hi>ſine die;</hi> for the <hi>King,</hi> when he uſed to diſſolve them, ſaid no more, but deſired them to go Home, till he ſent for them again; which is a Diſmiſſion <hi>ſine die.</hi> Now if there were forty ways of diſſolving Parliament, if I can prove this Parliament has been diſſolved by any one of them, I ſuppoſe there is no great need of the other thirty nine.</p>
               <p>Another thing, which they moſt inſiſt upon, is, That they have found a Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Time, when the Parliament was once prorogued three Days beyond a Year: In which I cannot chuſe but obſerve, That it is a very great Confirmation of the Value and Eſteem all People have had of the forementioned
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:175034:57"/>
Acts of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third; ſince, from that time to this, there can be but one Precedent found for the Prorogation of a Parliament above a Year, and that was but three Days neither. Beſides, my <hi>Lords,</hi> this Precedent is of a very odd kind of Nature; for it was in the Time of a very great Plague, when every one of a ſudden was forc'd to run away one from another; and ſo, being in haſt, had not leiſure to calculate well the time of the Prorogation; tho' the appointing of it to be within three Days after a Year, is an Argument, to me, that their Deſign was to keep within the Bounds of the Acts of Parliament; and if the Miſtake had been taken notice of in Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Time, I make no queſtion but She would have given a lawful Remedy to it.</p>
               <p>Now, I beſeech your <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> what more can be drawn from the producing this Precedent, but only becauſe once up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a time a thing was done Illegally, therefore your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> ſhould do ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: Now, my <hi>Lords,</hi> under Favour, this of ours is a very different Caſe from theirs; for as to this Precedent, the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion was never made; and all <hi>Lawyers</hi> will tell you, That Precedent that paſſes
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:175034:57"/>
                  <hi>ſub Silentio,</hi> is of no Validity at all, and will never be admitted in any Judicial Court where it is pleaded: Nay, Judge <hi>Vaughan</hi> ſaith in his Reports, <q>That in Caſes which depend upon Fundamental Principles, from which Demonſtrations may be drawn, Millions of Precedents are to no purpoſe.</q> O but, ſay they, you muſt think prudentially of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience that will follow it; for if this be allowed, all theſe Acts which are made in that Seſſion of Parliament, will be then void; whether that be ſo or no, I ſhall not now examine.</p>
               <p>But this I will pretend to ſay, That no Man ought to paſs for a Prudential Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who only takes notice of the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences on one ſide; it is the part of a wiſe Man to examine the Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences on both, to weigh which are the greateſt, and to be ſure to avoid them; and, my <hi>Lords,</hi> to this kind of due Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, I willingly ſubmit this Cauſe; for, I preſume, it will be eaſie to your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> to judge which of theſe two will be of moſt dangerous Conſequence to the Nation, either to allow that the Statutes made, in that particular Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Time, are void,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:175034:58"/>
which may eaſily be confirm'd at any time by a lawful Parliament; as, to lay down for a Maxim, That the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> by a Titular Order of Theirs, have Power to break all the Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> when they pleaſe: And, my <hi>Lords,</hi> with all the Duty we owe to His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> it is no diſreſpect to Him, to ſay, That His <hi>Majeſty</hi> is bound by the Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> for the Great <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth, GOD Almighty</hi> Himſelf, is bound by His own Decrees; and what is an Act of Parliament, but a Decree of the <hi>King,</hi> made in the moſt ſolemn manner? It is poſſible for Him to make it, that is, with the Conſent of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is plain then, in my Opinion, that we are no more a Parliament; and I humbly conceive your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> ought to give <hi>GOD</hi> thanks for it, ſince it has pleaſed Him thus, by his Providence, to take you out of a Condition wherein you muſt have been intirely uſeleſs to his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> to your ſelves, and the whole Nation.</p>
               <p>For, I beſeech your <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of this I have urged were true, what honourable Excuſe could be found for acting again with this <hi>Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> except we would pretend to ſuch
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:175034:58"/>
an exquiſite Act of Forgetfulneſs, as to avoid calling to mind all that paſſed laſt Seſſions; and unleſs we could alſo have a Faculty of teaching the ſame Art to the whole Nation! What Opinion would they have of us, if it ſhould happen, that the very ſame Men that were ſo earneſt, the laſt Seſſions, for having this <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> diſſolv'd, (when there was no queſtion of their lawful Sitting) ſhould now be willing to joyn with them again, when, without queſtion, they are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved?</p>
               <p>Nothing can be more dangerous to a <hi>King</hi> or People, than the Laws ſhould be made by an Aſſembly, of which there can be doubt whether they have a Power to make Laws or no; and it would be in us ſo much the more inexcuſable, if we ſhould overlook this Danger, ſince there is for it ſo eaſie a Remedy; a Remedy which the Law requires, and which all the Nation longs for, the Calling a New Parliament.</p>
               <p>It is that can only put his <hi>Majeſty</hi> into a poſſibility of receiving Supplies; that can ſecure your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> the Honour of Sitting in this <hi>Houſe of Peers,</hi> and of being Serviceable to the <hi>King</hi> and Country, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:175034:59"/>
that can reſtore, to all the People of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> their undoubted Rights of chooſing Men frequently to repreſent their Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances in Parliament; without this, all we can do is in vain; the Nation might languiſh a while, but muſt periſh at laſt; we ſhould become a Burthen to Our ſelves, and a Prey to our Neighbours.</p>
               <p>My Motion to your <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſhall be, That we humbly addreſs Our ſelves to His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and beg of Him, for His own Sake, as well as for all the People's ſake, to give us ſpeedily a New Parliament, that ſo we may una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly, before it is too late, uſe Our utmoſt Endeavours for His <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and for the Safety, Welfare and Glory of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:175034:59"/>
            <head>THE Emperor of Morocco's LETTER, TO <hi>CHARLES the Second.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHEN theſe Our Letters ſhall be ſo happy as to come to Your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi>'s Sight, I wiſh the Spirit of the <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous God</hi> may ſo direct Your Mind, that You may joyfully embrace the Meſſage I ſend. The Regal Power allotted to Us, makes Us firſt <hi>Common Servants</hi> to Our Creator, then of thoſe People whom we Govern: So that, obſerving the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties we owe to <hi>God,</hi> we deliver Bleſſings to the World. In providing for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good of Our Eſtates, we magnifie the Honour of <hi>God,</hi> like the <hi>Celeſtial Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> which, tho' they have much Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:175034:60"/>
yet ſerve only to the Benefit of the World. It is the Excellency of Our <hi>Office</hi> to be Inſtruments, whereby Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is delivered to Nations.</p>
            <p>Pardon Me, Sir! this is not to <hi>Inſtruct,</hi> (for I know I ſpeak to One of a more clear and quick <hi>Sight</hi> than My ſelf;) but I ſpeak this, becauſe <hi>God</hi> hath pleaſed to grant me a happy <hi>Victory</hi> over ſome part of thoſe <hi>Rebellious Pyrates,</hi> that ſo long have moleſted the peaceable Trade of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope;</hi> and hath preſented further Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to root out the Generation of thoſe, who have been ſo pernicious to the Good of our Nations: I mean, ſince it hath pleaſed <hi>God</hi> to be ſo auſpicious to our Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings, in the Conqueſt of <hi>Sallee,</hi> that we might joyn and proceed in hope of like Succeſs in the Wars of <hi>Tunis, Algiers</hi> and other Places <hi>(Dens</hi> and <hi>Receptacles</hi> of the Inhumane Villanies of thoſe who abhor Rule and Government.) Herein, whilſt we interrupt the Corruption of malignant Spirits of the World, we ſhall glorifie the <hi>Great GOD,</hi> and perform a Duty, that will ſhine as glorious as the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon,</hi> which all the Earth may ſee and reverence: A <hi>Work</hi> that ſhall
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:175034:60"/>
aſcend as ſweet as the Perfume of the moſt precious Odour in the <hi>Noſtrils of the LORD;</hi> a <hi>Work</hi> grateful and happy to Men; a <hi>Work,</hi> whoſe Memory ſhall be reverenced ſo long as there ſhall be any remaining amongſt Men, that love and honour the Piety and Vertue of Noble Minds. This Action I here willingly preſent to You, whoſe Piety and Vertues equal the Greatneſs of Your Power; that We, who are <hi>Vice-gerents</hi> to the <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Mighty GOD,</hi> may hand-in-hand Triumph in the Glory which the Action preſents unto Us.</p>
            <p>Now, becauſe the Iſlands which You Govern, have been ever Famous for the Unconquered Strength of their Shipping, I have ſent this my Truſty <hi>Servant</hi> and <hi>Ambaſſadour,</hi> to know, whether, in Your Princely Wiſdom, You ſhall think fit to Aſſiſt me with ſuch Forces by Sea, as ſhall be anſwerable to thoſe I provide by Land? Which if You pleaſe to grant, I doubt not but the <hi>LORD of Hoſts</hi> will protect and aſſiſt thoſe that fight in ſo Glorious a Cauſe. Nor ought You to think this ſtrange, that I, who ſo much Reverence the Peace and Accord of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:175034:61"/>
ſhould Exhort to a War: Your Great Prophet <hi>Christ Jeſus,</hi> was the <hi>Lion of the Tribe of Judah,</hi> as well as the <hi>Lord and Giver of Peace;</hi> which may ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie unto You, That He which is a Lover and Maintainer of Peace, muſt always appear with the Terror of his Sword; and wading thro' <hi>Seas of Blood,</hi> muſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive to <hi>Tranquillity.</hi> This made <hi>James,</hi> Your Grand-father, of Glorious Memory, ſo happily Renown'd amongſt all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. It was the Noble Fame of Your <hi>Princely Vertues</hi> which reſounds to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt <hi>Corners of the Earth,</hi> that perſuaded me to invite You to partake of that Bleſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wherein I boaſt My ſelf moſt happy. I wiſh <hi>GOD</hi> may heap the Riches of his Bleſſings on You, encreaſe Your Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with Your Days; and hereafter per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate the Greatneſs of Your <hi>Name</hi> in all Ages.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:175034:61"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To Mr.</hi> Bulstrode, <hi>at</hi> White-hall.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE <hi>Turks</hi> breaking their Truce, and beſieging <hi>Vienna,</hi> is very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable, but might reaſonably enough have been foreſeen, and is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the more ſtrange the Emperor ſhould be ſo unprovided. From the Princes of the Empire, ſurely no great Matters are to be expected, for they have their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Intereſt, and ſuch Confederate Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſeldom do great things: and, ſhould they call in the <hi>French</hi> to their Aſſiſtance, the end of that may eaſily be diſcerned; for, in all kind of Probability, it muſt make that <hi>King</hi> the Univerſal Emperor, and perhaps they may then bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves as dangerous an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my as him, they now fear: The old Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is a Truth, <hi>Every-body for himſelf, and God for us all;</hi> and therefore, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, I think it better for theſe Parts of the World, the <hi>Turks</hi> ſhould have that part of <hi>Germany</hi> than the <hi>French;</hi> for that
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:175034:62"/>
Almighty Neighbour, (ſhould he acquire the Empire) will be a perpetual Plague to the Northern Countries, and in time to the warmer Climates too; for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he has already made one Step into <hi>Italy,</hi> by <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal,</hi> and more than two Strides into <hi>Spain</hi> by his other Conqueſts, tho' he had ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly proteſted, at the Holy Altar, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly to obſerve the Peace of the <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renaeans;</hi> but, we ſee, theſe Proteſtations are no Tye upon this <hi>Most Chriſtian King;</hi> for when ever (that he calls) the Advancement of his own Glory, comes in Competition with his Juſtice to His Neighbour, the Latter is ſure to be the Sufferer. I doubt you will think me very impertinent, in medling in State Affairs, but I rely upon your Goodneſs to forgive me, ſince you know, I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your most humble Servant,
M. Peachey.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:175034:62"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To</hi>—</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Sir <hi>Politick,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TO prepare my ſelf for writing to you, I wiſh I could conjure up the Spirit of <hi>Nick Machiavel;</hi> for how can I be able to make good my Promiſe to you, who are the Great <hi>Anima Mundi Politici?</hi> I have naturally a ſtrange unhappy Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, which makes me not the beſt qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified for Politicks. I ſuppoſe you have heard over and over, of the Action in <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> where we have been as honourably Beaten, as a Man could well deſire. The Buſineſs of our Coin, which, under the new Diſpenſation, has been more then <hi>Moſaically</hi> Circumciſed, begins now to make a very handſome Appearance, there being great ſtore of new Money. To tell you my poor Opinion, the Nation has ſuffer'd the Fate of a Man that has got the <hi>Pox,</hi> who yet very wiſely rejects all the <hi>Quacks,</hi> and relies upon the known approv'd Method of Fluxing: She throws off all the unſound Part, the bad Money, and in its room gets up a freſh Stock of Vigour. You very well know how Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:175034:63"/>
have gone with the <hi>Bank:</hi> Their Abatements are not ſo great as they have been, and it is hoped it will be again in a flouriſhing Condition. You and I have private Reaſons to wiſh well, beſides this publick one, That the <hi>Bank</hi> is one of the Pulſes of our Government, and, as it beats high or low, a Man may make his Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences: And thus much for State Affairs; for really, Sir, I have but a mean Opinion of that ſort of Study. Politicks in <hi>Italy,</hi> may be refin'd Underſtanding; in <hi>France,</hi> a genteeler ſort of Villany; in <hi>Holland,</hi> Intereſt coarſe ſpun; but in <hi>England,</hi> are certainly <hi>Flatus Hypocondriaci.</hi> If this be not an effectual Plea for my Careleſneſs, you ought to conſider, I am out of the Road of <hi>Government,</hi> and of an Age when Men generally mind other things: People under Seven and Twenty, tho' they live about Town, either are for none, or elſe for a lower Species of Politicks; ſuch as which, in the preſent War of Pleaſure, ſhall get the better, <hi>King Thomas,</hi> or the Confederacy of Players.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir, </salute> 
               <signed>I am, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Octob. <hi>the First, 1696.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:175034:63"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To Mr.</hi> Savage.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IEſteem, tho' I cou'd not merit your Salute; and, while I return you mine in exchange, I acknowledge you a Loſer by the friendly Venture you have made; yet, let not one Loſs deter you from a farther Correſpondence: The Amorous, or rather Wanton Widow, bears her Loſs like a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> her Grief proceeds more from your Abſence than his Death. I have the Secret, but am not beholding either to him that is dead, or her that is living for it. I am ſorry to hear you made no greater Progreſs in that Affair; but do not wonder the Spirit moves not your Fancy ſo little, ſince you make all your Courtſhip to the Ladies; thoſe more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Miſtreſſes, the <hi>Muſes,</hi> are but thin airy <hi>Phantoms,</hi> and I know you have more of the Real, than the <hi>Platonick</hi> Lover, in you. When you come to my Years, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, you'll be more inclin'd to court the latter; yet, I muſt confeſs, when we come to be Fumblers in <hi>Love,</hi> we are but Bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glers
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:175034:64"/>
in <hi>Poetry:</hi> The <hi>Muſes,</hi> as well as the Ladies, are for the brisk, young and gay: I know not how well (the Ladies you mention) were pleas'd with hearing my Plays read; if they were delighted, I'll aſſure you, 'twas more with the <hi>Reader</hi> than the <hi>Writer.</hi> Children have oft been kiſs'd for their handſome Nurſes ſakes; 'twas you they liked, and not the Plays; the Pleaſure was in your Company, and not in their <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Merit.</hi> You pleaſe to ſay the Ladies often wiſh'd my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; that indeed wou'd have given 'em Diverſion, for then they'd have laugh'd at me too; or if they did heartily wiſh it, I ſuppoſe you did not tell 'em I was an Author of Fifty; which now you may, and ſo preſerve all their kind Thoughts for your ſelf: But had they their Wiſh, I ſhould ne'er have had mine; they wou'd wiſh me gone from 'em, and I ſhou'd wiſh to ſtay with 'em; I ſhou'd admire them, and they would admire at the folly of Wiſhing. The Sighs the Fair One ſent in the Paper, are not come to hand; but if I know by what Meſſenger you ſent the Letter, I wou'd go and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire what is become of 'em; the <hi>fragrancy</hi> of their Breath is wanting too, but that
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:175034:64"/>
may be blown away by the Wind, ſince the Paper paſs'd the Region of Thirty Five Miles at leaſt, for ſo I take it from <hi>Mayfield</hi> to <hi>London;</hi> or at leaſt, the Wind turning, drove back their Sighs and Breath to you agen—. Every thing favours the youthful <hi>Lover;</hi> but give my humble Service to the fair Ladies; for as Youth is pleas'd with real Favours, Age is not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas'd with being handſomly flatter'd. As a farther Token of your Friendſhip, Sir, pray, kiſs theſe Ladies Hands for me; your Kiſſes will be felt, tho' theſe I ſend be inviſible—. I have kiſs'd it twenty times: Pray, make juſt payment, for I think I am indebted ſo many to 'em at leaſt. Sir, I hope this laſt Commiſſion will make amends for the Errors of this Epiſtle.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir, </salute> 
               <signed>Your most oblig'd and humble Servant,
E. Ravenscroft.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:175034:65"/>
            <head>From a Gentleman in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, to a Lady in the City.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Was as apprehenſive of the tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my Journey, as the Effects of my Arrival, for the Perſecution of my Thoughts; each ſtep, I trod, ſeem'd like a Journey from the Land of the Living: I am certain, if Any-body had ſpoke to me, they could not look upon me in my Wits, and perhaps you'll ſay ſo too, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generating into ſo unmanly a Condition. At the ſame time, <hi>Madam,</hi> I'll be judg'd by your Conſcience, I won't ſay your ſelf, (for Womens Modeſty, like falſe Glaſſes, diſcommend 'em only for Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery) whether or no I am not a <hi>Martyr</hi> to a true Cauſe or not. I may well ſay I've made a Sacrifice of my Heart to you; for ever ſince I ſaw you, <hi>Victims</hi> on their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars ne'r burnt with greater Heat and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor. I'm as ſolitary as the place I reſide in: Methinks I cou'd wiſh we might converſe in Thoughts, or that our Souls might meet ſometimes in Sighs; but
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:175034:65"/>
Thoughts and Sighs are Airy Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and barren Food for Womens Souls; ſuch fond <hi>Platonicks</hi> as my ſelf may lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh under them in a Burrough, where <hi>Innocence, Ruſticity,</hi> and <hi>Ignorance</hi> agree, but here I waſte my time and wiſhes in vain: My Writing to you, is like my keeping of you Company, in this, that the Hearing from you, and ceaſing to write to you, ſeems equally perplexing, and at the ſame time equally unavoidable; for the <hi>Idea</hi> I have of you, has ſo transfix'd my Mind, that even my Breath and Sighs can ſcarce forbear to ſpeak the Wiſhing-flame of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam, </salute> 
               <signed>Your most afflicted Sufferer,
DAMON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:175034:66"/>
            <head>Three LOVE-LETTERS.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>To Madam</hi>—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Charming TYRANT,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THo' you forbid me to repeat Suns, Rocks, Mountains, Earth-quakes, which are as eſſential to a Letter of this kind, as Gilt-paper; yet you forgot to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept againſt Sighs, Prayers, Vows, Tears, and the many other little Reliefs the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy fly to; however, I'll now conceal the Trouble of my own Breaſt, rather than diſturb your Patience: I have found, by experience, that neither Deſpair, nor any other Perturbation of Mind, can kill me, ſince I have born a Fortnight's Abſence from you, and am yet alive: 'Tis true, Life is more ſupportable this Morning, than Yeſterday: For, if <hi>Hamlet</hi> had not been murther'd at the Play-houſe laſt Night, I had been worſe than dead to Day. Tell me, Dear <hi>Madam,</hi> how long muſt I live on the Plenty of my laſt
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:175034:66"/>
Night's Feaſt? Muſt I quickly again be happy, or linger out a tedious Life, under your Diſpleaſure? Let me know my Sentence in one Line; ſpeak Truth, and ſay, You hate me, becauſe I love you. 'Tis a Pleaſure to be out of Pain, and when One's going to be Executed, the greateſt Cruelty is the greateſt Mercy. Once more let me beg a ſhort Letter from you, tho' it be to chide me, for troubling you with ſo long a one as this: I ſwear, to hear only you were well, I'd give my Eyes; nor wou'd the loſs be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, becauſe they are of no manner of uſe to me in your abſence, unleſs to read thoſe Letters, which, I hope, Heaven will diſpoſe you to write to,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>YOURS.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:175034:67"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Madam</hi>—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>HOpe is like the Heart; and as it is the firſt thing that lives, ſo 'tis the firſt thing that dies in us, otherwiſe I cou'd deſpair of ſeeing you any more; but methinks 'tis impoſſible for one to have the Beauty and Brightneſs of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in her Eyes, without gentle Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion in her Heart: Reflect upon your Angel's Frame; Conſider, <hi>Madam,</hi> how that Tongue, that was faſhion'd by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to pronounce nothing but Bleſſings to your Adorers, will be miſ-imployed, when you Curſe ſo much, as to forbid me ſeeing you. I'm not ſo vain as to expect any Return to my Paſſion; only ſuffer it, and I am happy; call it by no leſs fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Name, than <hi>Love.</hi> Let it be Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and even that the <hi>Gods</hi> will allow of: They refuſe not our Sacrifices, nor are they angry at our <hi>Anthems:</hi> and if they with-hold their Bleſſings, they plead <hi>Predeſtination</hi> for their Excuſe. Cruel, as
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:175034:67"/>
you are, I muſt thank the Weather, or I'd met you no more; your Journey was fixt for this Morning, but Yeſterday's Rain did more than a Flood of Tears, from the Eyes of,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>YOURS.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:175034:68"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Madam</hi>—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>NEver cou'd the Author of <hi>Don Quixot</hi> more handſomly ridicule the Mad and Airy Gallantries of Roman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick <hi>Heroes,</hi> than you did in your laſt, your moſt unfortunate humble Servant. Your Letter has had ſo good effect upon me, that I have not executed my Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution; tho' this <hi>Scribble</hi> will ſeem to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie, that the Lead has entred my Skull already: Truly, Madam, I have ſo much occaſion for Brains, eſpecially when I write to a Lady of your Apprehenſion, that I can as little part with any, as a Member of—wou'd do with his Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges; but, it is poſſible, <hi>Madam,</hi> that a Piſtol can do more to your Admirer than the Concluſion of your Letter. You tell me there, I muſt not hope to ſee you more; you may from thence imagine, that no other Attempt can be equally fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to a Man of <hi>Errantry.</hi> I have only the Satisfaction left, to know that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be more Miſerable, for he that's
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:175034:68"/>
drown'd, needs no more fear Rain, than the withered Flowers does the hot Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine. Now, Madam, to free you from the pain of Reading any more, (which, I ſuppoſe, you'll take care to do your ſelf, by not calling for them) I'll only ask leave to tell you, That <hi>Cruelty</hi> becomes the <hi>Nymphs,</hi> as little as an Effeminacy does the <hi>Swains,</hi> nor can I ſtudy any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge half ſo terrible to you, as your act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt your ſelf, which is, in deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Marry. I hope, before you leap down the Precipice, you'll once more take leave of,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam, </salute> 
                  <signed>Your humble Servant,</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>I dare not tell you how things go, leſt you ſhould laugh at me; but if you will loſe your time at the Play, in <hi>Lincolns-Inn-fields,</hi> on <hi>Tueſday,</hi> I'll be the Subject of your Diverſion.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:175034:69"/>
            <head>A LETTER by Mr. <hi>M.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>
               <hi>To Mr.</hi> G—</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear <hi>G—,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE dull Buſineſs of the Day is over, and our <hi>Cuſhion-cuffer</hi> has given me leiſure for a better Employment, than hearing him cant over his muſty <hi>Morals;</hi> 'tis not the leaſt Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, in the Country, to do Penance once a Week, and ſit with paſſive Ears, two live-long Hours, and put ſuch a <hi>Violence</hi> on One's Nature: Heav'n be prais'd, in this lukewarm Age, nothing is ſo eaſily coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeited as <hi>Devotion,</hi> otherwiſe poor <hi>Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prit</hi> would have a hard part to play. 'T was the Opinion of a ſage <hi>Monk,</hi> that the Torment of <hi>Hell</hi> was nothing but an eternal Crowding and Elbowing; but I think it an everlaſting Solitude; for, I aſſure you, I think that the Country is but a State of <hi>Probation</hi> for <hi>Hell,</hi> and an Earneſt of <hi>Damnation:</hi> I was reviv'd,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:175034:69"/>
with your Letter, from a ſtupid ſort of a <hi>Lethargy;</hi> for any thing, that comes from <hi>London,</hi> in my forlorn Circumſtances, muſt needs be a Cordial, like poor <hi>Dives</hi> in <hi>Hell,</hi> viewing the great <hi>Gulph</hi> between, and begging ſome Small-beer of the <hi>Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Boſom; even ſo your deſolate Friend, begs the Favour of a Letter to comfort him in the midſt of his Afflictions, who am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend and Servant,
M—</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:175034:70"/>
            <head>LETTERS, Written by a PERSON of HONOUR.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To—</head>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From on Board—at St.</hi> Hellens, <date>May 27th, 1694.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>HEre we are ſtill, Sir, at your Service; Bragging, and Lying, and Hector<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Bouncing of what we are going to do; but the Proof of the <hi>Pudding</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Eating, a Month hence you may expect a truer Account of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and Courage, than I'll pretend to give you now: However, this is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, we have Miſchief in our Hearts. 'Tis poſitive, we are going to do or undo ſomething; here are ſtrong <hi>Simptoms</hi> of War: I have not heard, ſince I came on
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:175034:70"/>
Board, one Sentence (except when the <hi>Chaplain</hi> ſays <hi>Grace)</hi> without <hi>Blood, Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Fire,</hi> or <hi>Rape</hi> in't. Yeſterday I could not bear it, nor my Lord <hi>C—</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: ſo we ſlunk into a little Boat, and made a Deſcent on the <hi>Iſle of Wight,</hi> where I was preſently ſeiz'd, and had like to have dy'd of a Diſeaſe, call'd, <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture:</hi> Such <hi>Hills;</hi> ſuch <hi>Vallies;</hi> ſuch <hi>Woods;</hi> ſuch <hi>Plains;</hi> ſuch <hi>Faces;</hi> ſuch <hi>A—s.</hi> Look you, Sir, I'll ſay no more, but one Expedition under <hi>V—s,</hi> is worth two under <hi>M—s;</hi> and ſo I'll tell you what I did three Nights ſince: Hearing there was a <hi>Cargo</hi> of <hi>French Proteſtants</hi> newly debark'd, about four Leagues off, a certain Lord and your humble Servant, having a mind to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our Selves of the State of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, went a-ſhore, and enquir'd 'em out: We found in a <hi>Cow-houſe,</hi> full of <hi>Straw,</hi> ſixteen Women, nine Children, eight <hi>Lap-dogs,</hi> and a <hi>Tup-cat,</hi> all at Supper to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               <p>We ask't 'em what part of <hi>France</hi> they came from: They all anſwer'd at once, and every one nam'd a different Place.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:175034:71"/>
We ask't 'em what rate Bread was at: They all anſwer'd together again, and every one nam'd a different Price.</p>
               <p>With that, he ſingled out one, and I another: We preſt 'em about half an hour, with a cloſer Examination, and, comparing of Notes, we found, That the <hi>Spirit</hi> is ſometimes as weak as the <hi>Fleſh;</hi> and that Women, as well as <hi>Prieſts,</hi> of all Religions, are the ſame.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Adieu.</salute>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:175034:71"/>
               <head>To Mrs.—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>—,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>BEtter late than never,</hi> is an old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>Madam;</hi> and, I hope, a true one; at leaſt I rely ſo much upon it, that I venture to write to you after ſix Months Neglect. Not that I think you care much for my Letters neither; don't miſtake. But perhaps you may be apt to ſay, <hi>People need not be ſo ſparing of 'em, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they were of greater Value;</hi> and perhaps you'd ſay right: but that does not hinder People from being as lazy as ever; nor from continuing to be ſo impudent to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect Pardon, without being able to urge one tolerable Excuſe: <hi>For what's bred in the Bone,</hi> you know, <hi>will never out at the Fleſh.</hi> So there's another Proverb for you: Half a dozen more would ſtand me in great ſtead to make out my Letter: For I know my Lady—gives you an Account of all material Things, Intrigues and new Petticoats. As for <hi>Politicks,</hi> you'd clap them under Minc'd-pies, and well if they far'd no worſe. In ſhort, I know nothing but <hi>Religion</hi> you care a
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:175034:72"/>
Farthing for; and that the Town's ſo bare of at preſent, I cou'd as ſoon ſend you Money. No-body prays but the Court; and, perhaps, they had as good let it alone; at leaſt No-body ſees, by the Effects, what they pray for; 'tis thought, a general Exciſe. But Heaven, who knows our Wants better, ſeems to be of Opinion a General Peace will do as well. They ſay, The Bully of <hi>France</hi> is leaving all in the Lurch; for which he has both the Bleſſings and Curſes of many a poor Dog about this Town. For as to matters of Wealth and plenty, you muſt know the Impartiality of our Men of Buſineſs has been ſuch, they have brought <hi>Williamite</hi> and <hi>Jacobite</hi> to much about the ſame Pitch. But now we are all going to flouriſh again: ſo, I hope, we ſhall ſee your Ladiſhip in Town againſt the Peace is proclaim'd, that upon the <hi>Bonfire-night</hi> your Billet may burn too.</p>
               <p>I can tell you one thing: You ought to appear in your own Defence; for the firſt time I ſhew'd my ſelf, ſince I came to Town, upon that Theatre of Truth and Good Nature, the <hi>Chocolate-houſe,</hi> I was immediately regal'd with the old Story, (tho' from another Hand) <hi>That
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:175034:72"/>
now you were gone for certain.</hi> But, that worthy Knight-Errant, Mr. <hi>W—,</hi> that Mirrour of <hi>Chivalry,</hi> for all wrong'd La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, drew his Tongue in your Defence; and I, <hi>Madam,</hi> had the Honour to be his <hi>Sancho Pancho</hi> in your Juſtification. But how long we ſhall be able to ſtand our Ground, I can't tell, unleſs you'll come and lug out too, and then I don't doubt but we ſhall make our Party good. Now you muſt know, <hi>Madam, One good turn de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves another,</hi> (there's a Proverb again) I ſtand as much in need of your Weapon, as you can do of mine. Here's a ſcoundrel Play come out lately, by which the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor has been pleas'd to bring all the Reverend Ladies of the Town upon his Back, with my Lady—at the Head of 'em, for ſaying, <hi>An old Bawd was good for nothing.</hi> But that is not all his Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; there's a younger Knot, who having grimac'd themſelves into the Faction of Piety, ſay, <hi>'Tis a wicked Play,</hi> and a <hi>Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Play,</hi> and a <hi>Beaſtly, Filthy, Bawdy Play;</hi> and ſo never go to it, but in a Mask. Dear Mrs. <hi>S—</hi>come to Town again quickly, and don't put your Country-tricks upon us any longer, for here's a World of Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief in your Abſence: The <hi>V—</hi> is
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:175034:73"/>
Leaner than ever. I am grown Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious. My Lord <hi>W</hi>—is going to be Married. Sir <hi>John Fenwick</hi> is going to be Hanged. The <hi>W. L</hi>—is Boarded by a Sea-Officer: The Lady <hi>Sh</hi>—is Storm'd by a Land one. <hi>Yel</hi>—has got a high In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue; and the <hi>P</hi>—has got the Gripes. For <hi>God</hi>'s ſake come to Town quickly: You ſee all's in Diſorder; nor are things much better in the Country, as I hear: For, 'tis ſaid, the Spirit of Wedlock haunts Folks in <hi>Shropſhire,</hi> and has play'd the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil with the Fleſh. Some-body ſwore by—t'other Day, you were Married; to whom, I have forgot, tho' that was ſworn too. But, pray, let's ſee you here again; and don't tell us a Scripture-ſtory, That you have married a Husband, and can't come; the Excuſe, you ſee, was not thought good, even in thoſe Days, when things wou'd paſs on Folks that won't now.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>My due Reſpects to the Mayor and Corporation of <hi>S</hi>—</salute>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:175034:73"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To the Lord</hi> H—</head>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris,</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>Octob.</hi> 21. 1681.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>NOw things mend, my <hi>Lord;</hi> and an <hi>Italian</hi> Abbot makes a good Pimp: His only Fault is, he's damn'd hard of Hearing; a Shout in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Man's Ear, is but a Whiſper in his: A vile Quality for a Bawd. However, he's a Perſon of Buſineſs, and one of his <hi>Belles Dames</hi> is a better <hi>Sophiſter</hi> than you are; for you pretend but to argue <hi>Fornication</hi> no Sin, whilſt ſhe proves it a Vertue; and (all L—apart) wou'd—for the down-right ſake of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Her Caſe is this: She's a Siſter of the String, tickles a <hi>Guitar</hi> to a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, and that ſhe gets her Living by, Her Beauty, her Modeſty, her Wit, and her Youth, would help her to a better Livelihood, if her Conſcience would give her leave to lay about her like the reſt of her Sex; but her Inclinations being Upwards, and having a ſower Contempt of this vile Earth, ſhe deſires to give her
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:175034:74"/>
ſelf to her good <hi>God,</hi> and ſaunter out her Days in a <hi>Nunnery:</hi> But ſhe wants Five Hundred Piſtoles to introduce her; and that ſhe's willing to—for. She computes about a Twelve-month's Run may ſatisfie any Reaſonable Gentleman, and that he'll then give her leave to quit that ſame filthy Buſineſs, for a Swing of Spiritual L—</p>
               <p>So, if your Lordſhip knows ever a Knight-Errant, whoſe Purſe is as laviſh as his—and will both—for the Relief of Diſtreſſed Vertue; pray, tell him this pitiful Story, which is a Truth, by J—</p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> ſay, You'll be altogether by the Ears about ſix Weeks hence; and that they are to go over, and take Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of ſome Houſes and Parks, that belong to <hi>Des Bougres d'Anglois, qui vont a leur ordinaire ſe ſoulever contre leur Prince Naturel.</hi> God ſend this Invaſion, I ſay, 'twill at leaſt have one good Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, 'twill Legitimate <hi>Adultery</hi> here, which I have been ſeeking Arguments for in vain; for if they enter our Houſes, <hi>Lex Talionis,</hi> we whip into their Wives.
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:175034:74"/>
Rapes will be lawful too, by the ſame Morality. So, pray my Lord, come over; for here's like to be Work for a better—than mine.</p>
               <p>My Lord <hi>S</hi>—has got a nauſeous Miſtreſs here; a cry'd-up Beauty, a ſlat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternly Sow, founder'd of both her Feet: In ſhort, I hate her; and ſo I do Every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodies, but my own; and her I like ſo well, I believe I ſhall have my Bones broke about her, before I have done; there being ſome impertinent People a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin to her, who won't let her—in quiet.</p>
               <p>My Lord, the Soup's upon the Table, you'll excuſe me: for there are four tall <hi>Germans</hi> about it, who will ſwallow it down ſcalding hot, in leſs time than an <hi>Engliſh-</hi>man can ſay Grace. May Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven preſerve you ſtill fifty Years more, and kill your Father betwixt this and <hi>Chriſtmas.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Je ſuis tout à Vous.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:175034:75"/>
                  <p>Two Days ſince my Lord <hi>S—</hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in appearance at the Door of Death, he repented, as is uſual: but there is now hopes of a Return to his Health, and Relapſe to his Vices.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:175034:75"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mr.</hi> T—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Rakehelly <hi>T—,</hi>
                  </salute>
               </opener>
               <p>JUſt now, ſtroling thro' my Pocket-Book, I ſtumbl'd upon your Name: Mrs. <hi>P—</hi>'s Name, <hi>Charing-croſs,</hi> and the Sign of the <hi>Elephant,</hi> which gave Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance ſuch a Bang, I have made a Collection of Pen, Ink and Paper, with a deſign to be as good as my Word, and write to you. So the Queſtion how I ſhall write, and the Queſtion whether I ſhall write or not, are indeed become no Queſtions at all; but the Queſtion what I ſhall write, is a great Queſtion ſtill. The Houſe of Office may perhaps help me. You'll excuſe me for a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>I am return'd, and by Providence's help, have done your Buſineſs as well as my own. I have found ſix leaves of a <hi>Dutch</hi> Sermon; the Title-page I have made uſe of, the reſt I ſend you enclos'd. I don't underſtand much of the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, but I think it gives you an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:175034:76"/>
how many Tun of Saints the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans</hi> ſhipp'd off for the Spiritual <hi>Indies,</hi> when the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> liv'd in <hi>Holland:</hi> He ſays the Manufacture now is quite deſtroy'd, and the Trade is not worth a T—Now you muſt know, Parſons in this Country tell Truth in their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; ſo, as to a lover of Truth and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons both, I ſend you this. The Poſtage won't coſt you above half a Piece; a Dog Penny-worth, I think.</p>
               <p>All I have to ſay, is, That this is a ſcoundrel Town. The <hi>Dutch</hi> Women here are greaſie and fat, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and ugly. Here's a great deal of Snow, and very bad Fires; curſed Meat, and worſe Company: That for our Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. As for Buſineſs: My Lord <hi>W—</hi> is aſleep by the Fire-ſide; Mr. <hi>Ruſ—</hi>is picking his Noſe; the P—ſs is Quilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Petticoat; her Maids are all at their Prayers; <hi>Ju</hi>———is Expounding the <hi>Revelations; B—t</hi> is writing of Libels; the Pr—is ſtudying, I gueſs what; and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Embaſſador is a Fool: Zoons, Sir, I have got the Cramp; O G—! how many damn'd Tricks has Nature to plague Mankind—I can't
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:175034:76"/>
write a word more. You'll ſend me an Anſwer to this, won't you? Do, prithee do; and don't be long about it now.</p>
               <p>If you direct your Letter to me at <hi>Youfrow Zouterkin</hi>'s, in <hi>Cut-ſtraet,</hi> 'tis ſix to four but my Hand and my A—will have it in their turns.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:175034:77"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To the Chevalier</hi> De Choiſeul, <hi>at</hi> La Hogue.</head>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>De l'Enfer, ce</hi> 
                     <date>18. <hi>Avril,</hi> 1692.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>Mon Cher Chevalier,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SIvoſtre Voyage a eſte auſſi agreable que voſtre bonne Compagnie l'e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toit aux pauvres Priſonniers à la Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtille, je m'en rejouiray for: Car, ſans Compliment, je m'intereſſe beaucoup à tout ce qui vous regarde. Et quoy que (la Charite commencant chez ſoy) je me plaigne de voſtre abſence, j'ay aſſez de bon Naturel, pour me rejouir de voſtre Liberte.</p>
               <p>Pour moy; je ſuis, comme j'ay long tems eſte, (en apparence) ſur la veille de ſortir: Cependant, la Porte n'eſt pas en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>core ouverte.</p>
               <p>Le pauvre my Lord a prit les devants; &amp; il eſt preſentement à Boulogne, ou il attend l'arrivee du General Hamilton. Ainſi voila la Baſtille plus triſte que ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mais.
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:175034:77"/>
Le Marquis pourtant continue a nous divertir, &amp; à nous incommoder: Le voicy, Mort Die, qui entre avec toute ſa ſuitte. Que le Diable les emporte tous enſemble. Ils font tant de bruit, qu'il eſt impoſſible d'ecrire davantage. Ainſi A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieu, juſqu'à tantoſt—</p>
               <p>Il y a deux heures que j'ay eſte oblige de quitter ma Lettre, &amp; depuis ce temps la, j'ay eſte entretenu, comme quoy, c'eſt une choſe qui choque l'honneur de la France, qu'un Fils d'un Duc &amp; Pair, de la Noble Race de Cruſole, deſcendu des anciens Comtes de Tholouſe, ſoit detenu Priſonnier à la Baſtille, pendant que la Nation a beſoin de ſes plus grands Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, pour repouſſer une foule d'Enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis qui l'attaquent. Mais, Monſieur, (luy repondi-je) les choſes ne ſont pas encore à l'extremite; la France n'eſt pas encore perdue. Quand le Roy la verra en danger, ce ſera alors qu'il ſe ſervira de ſes dernieres reſources; &amp; ſe ſera alors qu'il vous ſortira glorieuſement de la Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtille, pour vous placer à la teſte de ſes Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mees. Si vous eſtiez deja dehors, il ſcait que vous vous expoſeriez trop, voſtre va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leur luy eſt connue; c'eſt pour l'amour
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:175034:78"/>
de vous, &amp; de luy meſme, qu'il veut vous conſerver; c'eſt pour vous conſerver qu'il vous a donnè en charge à Monſieur de Beſmeaux.</p>
               <p>F—tre de Beſmeaux, (dit-il) F—tre de la Baſtille, F—tre de Sodome, &amp; F—tre de Gommore; je ſuis Fils d'un Duc &amp; Pair, moy.</p>
               <p>Monſieur (luy dis-je) voſtre Illuſtre Naiſſance eſt desja connue à tout le mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de; un peu de Patience feroit auſſi eclat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter voſtre Vertu.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Je me F—de la Vertu—</l>
                  <l>Mais, Monſieur, un peu de Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion—</l>
                  <l>Point: Je veux fortir, moy—Je veux me ſignaler—</l>
                  <l>Mais ecoutez, Marquis. Si vous ſortiez, &amp; que Monſieur de Beſmeaux—</l>
               </lg>
               <p>F—tre de Beſmeaux, je vous dis—Je me mocque de luy, qu'il laiſſe les Gens en repos, s'il le veut; ou je luy. F—tray vingt coups de Pied dans le Ventre, &amp; autant de coups de Poing ſur le Nez; &amp; flinque &amp; flanque, &amp; l'Abere, &amp; Gara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:175034:78"/>
&amp; encore cent milles F—tus Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coignes, Mort Die, je les feray tous trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler.</p>
               <p>Monſieur le Marquis, (luy dis-je) je ſuis voſtre tres humble Serviteur; mais comme je n'ay point de Cuiraſſe, je ne veux plus demeurer ſeul avec vous. O (dit-il) vous ne riſquez rien.</p>
               <p>Pardonnez moy (repartis-je) on riſque beaucoup, quand le Sang des Cruſoles eſt bouillant. Adieu.</p>
               <p>Je deſcendis donc, &amp; il evacua ma Chambre: &amp; à mon Retour, pour ache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ma Lettre, j'ay bien barricade ma Porte.</p>
               <p>Comme tout le monde icy, pretend que vous allez droit en Angleterre, pour Retablir le Roy Jacques, bon gre, mal gre. Et que je conſidere, que dans les Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peditions de Mars, Venus ne manque ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mais de ſe mettre de la Partie: Je vous prie d'avoir ſoin, que ſi mes Soeurs doi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent eſtre baiſees, du moins elles puiſſent avoir la Conſolation d'eſtre bien baiſees Il y en a à choiſir; mais la troiſieme, en
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:175034:79"/>
etant la plus Belle, je vous la recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande pour voſtre propre Bouche. Si vous la trouvez Vierge (car je ne repons de rien) allez doucement, ne faites point trop de fracas; de peur de faire pleurer la pauvre Fille. Mais quand vous aurez pris le Fort, je vous ſupplie de n'y pas laiſſer Garniſon.</p>
               <p>Pour nos Egliſes: Remettez-y tout ce qu'il vous plaira, hors le Pouvoir Deſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique du Preſtre; car je ne deſire pas d'aller au Ciel la Fourche au Cul.</p>
               <p>Dans la Police, faites moy la grace de pendre tous les Procureurs: mais traitez avec becaucoup the Reſpect un certain Avocat, qui s'appelle <hi>Habeas Corpus.</hi> C'eſt un veritable honneſte Homme: mal gre ſa Robe longue, vous pouvez vous ſouve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nir que nous avons quelque fois beu à ſa Sante. En verite il le merite bien: c'eſt un Amy à tout le monde, &amp; qui en meſme temps ne flatte perſonne: il eſt vray qu'il va ſouvent à la Court, mais il n'eſt pas du tout Courtizan. Il faut que vous ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiez qu'il a des manieres qui ne s'ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodent pas tout à fait avec ſes Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieurs la: ils luy donnent de bonnes oa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roles,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:175034:79"/>
mais ils ne l'aiment pas trop. Que cela ne vous empeche pas de luy faire la Reverence: Toſt ou tard, vous en pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez avoir beſoin. Je vous prie de luy faire bien mes Compliments, &amp; de luy aſſeurer que je me ſouviens fort ſouvent de luy.</p>
               <p>Au reſte: Crevez moy toutes les Vieilles, qui refuſent d'eſtre Maquerelles; car il neſt pas pour le bien publicq, que des choſes inutiles, mangeaſſent le Pain de l'Etat.</p>
               <p>Etoufez tous les petits Chiens de Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, &amp; les Enfans qui crient; car tout ce qui fait du bruit me deſole.</p>
               <p>Enfin, ſi vous rencontrez (ce que je no crois pas) un Fils d'un Duc &amp; Pair, pareil au Marquis, envoyez le a la Tour, pour le repos de ſa Famille.</p>
               <p>Et voila, mon cher Compatriot de malheur, toutes les Commiſſions que j'ay a vous donner. Si je vous voy a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, d'icy en ſix Mois, vous me rendre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Compte comment vous les aurez execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tez. Si c'eſt bien, je vous en loueray
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:175034:80"/>
fort: ſi c'eſt mal, je vous pardonneray vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lontiers. Car je ſuis (ſans Compliment) tout a fait de vos Amis, &amp; fort voſtre Serviteur.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:175034:80"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mr.</hi>—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>HARRY,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I'M afraid thou'rt turn'd a meer <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damite,</hi> that is, haſt forfeited thy Health and Happineſs to purchaſe more Knowledge, or elſe thou art plagui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bely'd. Oh! that Pleaſure, <hi>Harry,</hi> is a Helliſh Pleaſure. How ſweet in the Enjoyment, and how ſower in the Event! Well, I ſuppoſe thou'rt throughly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd, there's no ſuch thing as Heaven upon Earth, as a great many vain Fellows imagine; ſince our Pleaſures are not only bounded in one particular thing; but the greateſt Variety of Enjoyments finiſh in the uneaſie Deſire of their Continuance, or the more torturing Experience of its Impoſſibility; or at leaſt, their Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by a prodigious Fluxing. The moſt permanent of all our Habits, is that part of 'em which are vicious; or that which we are taught to believe ſo. A good Thought is as eaſily ſpoil'd in Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as 'tis in Study. The obſceneſt B—
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:175034:81"/>
in one Moment will ruine the ſtrongeſt Efforts of a pious Preparation. Oh! this Nature of ours, tho' it be the moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> is yet a Compound of Extreams: the Minute that gives Birth to the moſt endear'd of our Entertainments, gives ſuch an Aſſurance of their Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that palls them in the poſſeſſion: Our Entertainment is very often uneafie to us, from the Care we take to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular; and we are ſeldom guilty of ſo great <hi>Soleciſm,</hi> as when we endeavour to avoid all for <hi>Silence,</hi> which is a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Remedy againſt 'em, is at the ſame time the greateſt <hi>Soleciſm</hi> in Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Why, this Moment I was thinking to treat you as one of my Familiars; and in my very Deſign of being ſo, my Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency has carried me to a quite oppoſite Matter, and I am unawares an unskilful Moraliſt, or an unbiting <hi>Satyr.</hi> I hope you will pardon my Impertinence, and accept this ſmall Epiſtle from him, who is your affectionate</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Humble Servant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:175034:81"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To Mrs.</hi>—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Cou'd no more hope to ſee you (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the time of your Letter's coming to my Hands) than I could have any Peace without it. Not all the Objects in the World could divert my Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, but your Letter, which had done it effectually, but that it gave me the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Mortification of deſpairing to find you. Lord, Madam, how inſenſible of Paſſion are you, to ſee and reject ſuch Evidence of my Love? I am ſorry you give me ſo great a ſhew of your Levity, and ſo much Apprehenſion of my ill For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. If my Condition be not anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to your Beauty, this I can tell, my Paſſion is the moſt exalted in Nature. I wiſh Nature would afford me ſome ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Method to convince you of it, that I might at leaſt hope a reciprocal one from you. In my own Brain, I feel both all the Pain and Love, which <hi>Poets</hi> feign <hi>Romantick Heroes</hi> to have done;
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:175034:82"/>
and am ſcarce leſs mad to let you know, how much I wou'd be thought to be your Humble Servant.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>DAMON.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:175034:82"/>
               <head>To Sir <hi>John</hi> In Imitation of a Letter in the <hi>Hiſtoires Facetieuſes,</hi> p. 78.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear KNIGHT,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THis comes to inform you, that I am in the Land of the Living; and that's all. But as for the Pleaſures of this Tranſitory World, (which the <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites</hi> that uſe them, and the <hi>Rakehells</hi> that are paſt them, call <hi>Vanities)</hi> I am no more the better for them, than a <hi>Lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lander</hi> is for the Sun of <hi>Italy;</hi> or, to come nearer Home, than <hi>Grocer's-Hall</hi> is for the Wealth of the Bank at <hi>Amſterdam.</hi> A Curſe on that unlucky Night, when you and I got ſo drunk at the <hi>Blue-poſts</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: for do but obſerve what were the Effects on't. Drunkenneſs, Sir <hi>John,</hi> drew Fornication after it; and theſe two Sins in wicked Conjunction begot a moſt undutiful Child, the Lord knows, between 'em, who before he was a Fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night old, depos'd both his Father and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:175034:83"/>
Mother. Thus being diſabled from Whoring, and out of reſpect to my own Carcaſs not daring to drink, I am grown as grave, and as contemplative, and as virtuous a Perſon, as you cou'd deſire to ſtick your Knife in. Like the reſt of the World too, when they turn <hi>Saints,</hi> I find the Devil and all of <hi>Ill Nature</hi> has come upon me with my <hi>Virtue.</hi> I am as <hi>ſplena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> and <hi>peeviſh</hi> as a poor Dog of an <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> that has been bilked in a <hi>Dedication.</hi> Neither Man, Woman, nor Child can eſcape my <hi>Cenſures.</hi> I roar againſt Sin, louder than a Fellow that is paid to do it in <hi>Publick,</hi> tho' at the ſame time wiſhes it no miſchief in his Heart. I rail at Every-body, whether I know them or no; and in ſome of my moody Fits don't care a Farthing if half the Men in the Kingdom were hang'd, and all the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſent pick-a-pack to Old <hi>Cloven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Once more, a Curſe on that unlucky Night, when this Diſaſter befel me. Dear Sir <hi>John,</hi> for Heavens ſake, help me to pelt it with ſome <hi>Vigorous,</hi> ſome <hi>Emphatical,</hi> ſome <hi>Gigantick</hi> Curſes: May it hereafter know no Mirth nor Pleaſure,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:175034:83"/>
not even that of <hi>Lamb-blacking</hi> Signs, and rubbing out of <hi>Milk-ſcores;</hi> no Balls, nor Serenades; no Jollity of Drunkards, nor Enjoyment of Lovers. May it hear of nothing but Execrations of Loſing Gameſters, Fires, Burglaries, and ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered Watchmen. <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> of the Night ſurrendring up their pious Souls in <hi>Kennels,</hi> and the <hi>Withered Bullies</hi> that did it, dying and blaſpheming by their ſide. <hi>Murders</hi> hideous enough to fright an <hi>Italian,</hi> and unnatural <hi>Rapes,</hi> that would make even a <hi>Pamper'd Cardinal</hi> tremble. But a Pox on't, I don't curſe worth a ſtraw. One <hi>Scotch</hi> Pedlar hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly warm'd wou'd out-do half a dozen ſuch puny Fellows as I am. Therefore, dear Sir <hi>John,</hi> come to my Aſſiſtance, and help me out at a Pinch. Curſe that unlucky <hi>Night,</hi> or curſe the <hi>Wine,</hi> or curſe the <hi>Maſter;</hi> 'tis all one in the <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Hebrew,</hi> ſo you do but curſe. But eſpecially pour a double Vial of your wrathful Spirit upon the Diſcourteous Damoſel that brought me to this. May Providence everlaſtingly toſs her from the <hi>Chirurgeon</hi>'s Hands to the <hi>Bayliff's,</hi> and ſo back again <hi>in Soecula Soeculorum:</hi> Or may her Ill Fate force her in her Old
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:175034:84"/>
Age to <hi>Scotland,</hi> where may the <hi>Kirk</hi> condemn her to be roaſted alive for a <hi>Sorcereſs;</hi> and may ſhe be as long a burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as the Univerſe will be at the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flagration.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>T. Brown.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:175034:84"/>
               <head>TO Mrs.—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>NEver any Mortal laboured under ſuch a Perplexity of Fortune, or Variety of Confuſions: I ſhould cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly put a Period to this Being of mine, but that I am ſtill willing to ſubmit to you the Triumph: As you have had it ſo indiſputably over my Heart, even ſo take it over my Life, ſince it offends you, and affords me no Comfort. How can you imagine, that one bereft of his Soul, can ſurvive its Abſence? No more can you the Poſſibility of mine, and at the ſame time be convinc'd of the Reality of my Paſſion. Theſe Twelve Months at leaſt have I been endeavouring to caſt off my Chains, and to quit a Cauſe which I cou'd no more hope to triumph in, than I had to be happy without it: but find as impoſſible as to abandon my Breath, and retain my Vital Motion. I conjure you, <hi>Madam,</hi> by all the Ties of Nature, pity me, and the miſchievous Circumſtances of my ill Fortune, that has plac'd me in a
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:175034:85"/>
Sphere, which can no more entitle me to your eſteem, than encourage my Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption. But pardon me, <hi>Madam,</hi> if I wiſh <hi>Fortune</hi> had been leſs benevolent to you, that I might have given you a more ample Evidence of my Paſſion, and my ſelf a greater Proſpect of Succeſs; and believe aſſuredly, 'twou'd be the greateſt Inhumanity in the World in ceaſing to kill, or ceaſing to make me the happieſt of your Humble Servants.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Adieu.</salute>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:175034:85"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To a Gentleman in</hi> Cambridge.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Honeſt SAM!</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SInce you are ſo ſtout, I'll be ſo too, and pick your Pocket of two Pence; a thing, I hope, excuſable in a Friend. But perhaps you'll ſay, Some People have a plaguy deal of Impudence, to call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo, ſince you give 'em no encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement by your Letters; but, at the ſame time, that does not ſuppreſs this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence: For <hi>what's bred in the Bone, will never out of the Fleſh;</hi> and ſo there's a Proverb for you. Why, I'll promiſe thee, <hi>Sam,</hi> I wiſh thoud'ſt pick my Pocket af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch a friendly manner. But, I ſee, abſent Acquaintance are as little thought of, as paſt Iniquities; and the Devil of Forgetfulneſs reigns as much in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgeſhire,</hi> as that of Poverty does in <hi>London.</hi> However, I heartily wiſh thee void of both; for theſe Devils are bloody things to be diſpoſſeſs'd, when they have once got a footing: As an Inſtance of which, there's a good honeſt Fellow has ſent his Wife to the other World under
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:175034:86"/>
the ſame Predicament. Your Brother and I are conſulting now to make you Pennileſs; for we're plaguily afraid, that you eat ſo much of the <hi>Divine Banquet,</hi> that you can afford none of your abſent Friends ſo much as a Refreſhment: And ſo, Honeſt <hi>Sam,</hi> good Night to thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:175034:86"/>
               <head>To <hi>T—W—,</hi> Eſq.</head>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>May</hi> the 19th, 93.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <lg>
                  <l>TIs ſtrange, that what e're Noddle akes,</l>
                  <l>Some Friend or other ſtill partakes;</l>
                  <l>Whoever wrote, have always ſought</l>
                  <l>Some one for <hi>Goſſip</hi> to their Thought.</l>
                  <l>I, after hunting long in vain,</l>
                  <l>To vent th' Incumbrance of my Brain,</l>
                  <l>(Like ſpurious. Race of humble Whore)</l>
                  <l>Reſolve to lay it at your Dore.</l>
                  <l>And just as other <hi>Writers</hi> uſe,</l>
                  <l>Shall plead <hi>Preſcription</hi> for Excuſe:</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Cuſtom</hi> that does ſtill diſpenſe</l>
                  <l>With Univerſal <hi>Influence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And makes things right or wrong appear,</l>
                  <l>Just as they do her Liv'ry wear;</l>
                  <l>Can juſtifie <hi>Impertinence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſtamp it into <hi>Sterling</hi> Sence.</l>
                  <l>I therefore care not what I write,</l>
                  <l>For tho' I Scribble, You Endite;</l>
                  <l>I treat you at Your own Expence,</l>
                  <l>And furniſh words, but You the Sence.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="158" facs="tcp:175034:87"/>
And therefore fear not to miſcarry,</l>
                  <l>Since I am but Your <hi>Secretary:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For as our Eyes but paſſive are,</l>
                  <l>(As learned <hi>Philoſophers</hi> aver)</l>
                  <l>And only convey to the Mind,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Idea's,</hi> which first there we find;</l>
                  <l>Yet are Themſelves but Helps to ſee,</l>
                  <l>As other <hi>Optick-Glaſſes</hi> be,</l>
                  <l>So in theſe <hi>Lines,</hi> what ever's meant,</l>
                  <l>I only am Your <hi>Inſtrument;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And nothing have at my command,</l>
                  <l>But the meer Motion of my Hand:</l>
                  <l>For all the Sence, You must expect,</l>
                  <l>Springs from Your proper <hi>Intellect.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The learned' st Book that e're was wrot,</l>
                  <l>To him that underſtands it not,</l>
                  <l>No other proſpect e're affords,</l>
                  <l>Then a meer <hi>Anarchy</hi> of Words:</l>
                  <l>For Books (like all things elſe) are good</l>
                  <l>Or bad, but as they're underſtood;</l>
                  <l>And when Men quote 'em, they miſtake,</l>
                  <l>They did not find it ſo, but make:</l>
                  <l>So whatſoe're from them we ſmatter,</l>
                  <l>Is but the Senſe of <hi>Commentator:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For Words indeed, altho' ſown thick,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Cyphers</hi> in <hi>Arithmetick,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When all cast up, to nothing come,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Figure</hi> only make the Sum:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="159" facs="tcp:175034:87"/>
So Readers must to Books ſupply,</l>
                  <l>What feeble Characters deny.</l>
                  <l>And hence it is that all things ſound,</l>
                  <l>Just as their Fancies do expound;</l>
                  <l>And if they take 'em in a wrong ſence,</l>
                  <l>All Authors have been ſerv'd ſo long ſince.</l>
                  <l>Did they not make old <hi>Homer</hi> prate</l>
                  <l>Of Boots and Shooes, and <hi>God</hi> knows what?</l>
                  <l>Made him hold-forth on <hi>Philoſophy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And Vertues of <hi>Sage, Tea</hi> and <hi>Coffee;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And Jeſts too up and down to ſcatter,</l>
                  <l>Where he thought nothing of the matter?</l>
                  <l>Made they not <hi>Virgil</hi> ſtrange things write,</l>
                  <l>And propheſie by After-light;</l>
                  <l>Fore-tell the Means of our Salvation,</l>
                  <l>And all this by their Inſpiration?</l>
                  <l>Make they not him Mens Fortunes tell,</l>
                  <l>Of which he ne're thought Syllable;</l>
                  <l>Pronounce the Fate of Men in Battle,</l>
                  <l>And of Invaders of ſtrange Cattle;</l>
                  <l>Detect by Whole-ſale in his Verſe,</l>
                  <l>Thieves, Pick-pockets and Conjurers;</l>
                  <l>And ſurer tell who drives that Game on,</l>
                  <l>Than <hi>P—dge, G—ry,</hi> or <hi>S—on?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Mean time, perhaps, there's but one Leaf,</l>
                  <l>Betwixt the Juſtice and the Thief:</l>
                  <l>His Worſhip wou'd a little later,</l>
                  <l>Have found it quite another matter,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="160" facs="tcp:175034:88"/>
And had been, to his ſole jeopardy,</l>
                  <l>Suſpended for meer being tardy;</l>
                  <l>Or acted at the Rump of Cart,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Spartan</hi> Patience his part.</l>
                  <l>Make they not <hi>Horace</hi> a ſtark Aſs,</l>
                  <l>Reduc'd to <hi>Du——</hi>Ballad Claſs,</l>
                  <l>Strip him of all that's gay and witty,</l>
                  <l>To fit him up to doleful Ditty?</l>
                  <l>Tagg'd forth with miſerable Rhimes,</l>
                  <l>From Bulks, and in the Streets he chimes.</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Roſamond</hi> now <hi>Lydia</hi> vies,</l>
                  <l>And fills the <hi>Milk-maids</hi> maudlin Eyes;</l>
                  <l>While <hi>Hopkins</hi> is forgot and <hi>Sternhold,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So often chanted forth in Barn old.</l>
                  <l>Was not Sage <hi>Terence</hi> at adventure,</l>
                  <l>By Oily <hi>Shadwell</hi> turn'd to banter?</l>
                  <l>And taught, for duller Sence of's own,</l>
                  <l>The brisk gay Nonſenſe of the Town?</l>
                  <l>And his inſipid Tale improv'd,</l>
                  <l>By what the Town and <hi>Sh—ll</hi> lov'd?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sh—ll,</hi> whoſe whole Stock is, a Bully,</l>
                  <l>A Wench, a Uſurer, a Cully.</l>
                  <l>From whence, with little pains, ſtraightway,</l>
                  <l>Or Wit, he oft does launch a Play:</l>
                  <l>As Cits, with Blue, ſecure from ſtaining,</l>
                  <l>A Heroe fit on Days of Training.</l>
                  <l>I need not tell of late Projectors,</l>
                  <l>That Stories tell of <hi>Witches Spectres;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="161" facs="tcp:175034:88"/>
Hold forth, with learned <hi>Theory,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>On the <hi>Proboſcis</hi> of a <hi>Flea;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Purſue with <hi>Microſcope,</hi> the Tract</l>
                  <l>Of List upon a <hi>Grey-louſe</hi> Back;</l>
                  <l>Philoſophize upon <hi>Salt-waters,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And other much ſurprizing Matters.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Pedlars</hi> in all ſorts of Wares,</l>
                  <l>That Haberdaſh in <hi>Love-Affairs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Mechanicks, Metre, Politicks,</l>
                  <l>And forty other modiſh Tricks,</l>
                  <l>As Tumbling, Jugling, Vaulting, Dancing,</l>
                  <l>Intriguing, Ridling, and Romancing,</l>
                  <l>That do with Pamphlets <hi>Epidemick,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Laden with <hi>Billingſgate Polemicks,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Confound the <hi>Jacobites,</hi> and <hi>Quakers,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With their Adherents, and Partakers,</l>
                  <l>To th' ruine of their Grace, and quite</l>
                  <l>Extinguiſhing their inward <hi>Light;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That fill Men for a Diſh of <hi>Coffee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With <hi>Politicks</hi> and <hi>Philoſophy;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And for a ſingle Penny can</l>
                  <l>Inſtruct at once a whole <hi>Divan</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of Coblers, Chimney-ſweepers, Car-men,</l>
                  <l>And the whole Tribe of Two-legg'd Vermin</l>
                  <l>Nor need I mention Foreign Journal,</l>
                  <l>Tranſlated to Gallants Diurnal,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Verſes</hi> given, and ſtoln <hi>Proſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A motly <hi>Rhapſody</hi> compoſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="162" facs="tcp:175034:89"/>
To teach poor Prentice, ſadly panting,</l>
                  <l>More modern Methods of Gallanting;</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Sempſtreſs,</hi> the most recent Arts,</l>
                  <l>Of captivating ſtragling Hearts,</l>
                  <l>And exerciſe the Wit of Youth,</l>
                  <l>On Snails, Tobacco-pipes and Truth.</l>
                  <l>Nor him that late in ſparkiſh <hi>Proſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Appear'd to edifie the <hi>Beaus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who, with ſoft Lines, and ſofter Looks,</l>
                  <l>Expertly baits his Amorous Hooks,</l>
                  <l>And brings with Elegant <hi>Epiſtle,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Each melting <hi>Damſel</hi> to his <hi>Whiſtle,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And makes her ſtoop to him as ſure</l>
                  <l>As hungry <hi>Hawk</hi> does to his <hi>Lure;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who lately drew, in <hi>Vindication,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of all the <hi>Beauties</hi> in the <hi>Nation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And boldly tilted with his <hi>Pen,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Gainſt all that durſt oppoſe him then;</l>
                  <l>Which ſome <hi>Apology</hi> miſ-call, ſome <hi>Satyr,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Both equidiſtant from the <hi>Matter;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For ſurely no <hi>Deſign</hi> was in't,</l>
                  <l>But barely to appear in <hi>Print.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which he as kindly ſince has done,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gallants,</hi> for your <hi>Inſtruction;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where the <hi>Grand Secrets</hi> he imparts,</l>
                  <l>For battering <hi>Obdurate Hearts;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How you to <hi>Vizard-mask,</hi> or <hi>Coach,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May make a Regular <hi>Approach:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="163" facs="tcp:175034:89"/>
He ſhews you how you ſhall prevail</l>
                  <l>With Lines as fenceleſs as a <hi>Flail;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For <hi>Letters Miſſive, Weapons</hi> are,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Lovers</hi> combat with from far:</l>
                  <l>Shews how to take 'em by <hi>Surprize,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or uſe the <hi>Artillery</hi> of <hi>Eyes:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But if <hi>Neceſſity</hi> oblige</l>
                  <l>To Methods of a cloſer <hi>Siege,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He ſhews ſuch <hi>Means</hi> as might improve</l>
                  <l>The greateſt <hi>Engineer</hi> in <hi>Love;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To bribe the <hi>Sentinel,</hi> her <hi>Maid,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or ſtorm her with a <hi>Serenade:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And if by theſe ſhe be not won,</l>
                  <l>Bombard with <hi>Sonnet,</hi> or <hi>Lampoon;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If theſe <hi>Attempts</hi> ſhe ſtill defies,</l>
                  <l>To blow her up with <hi>Mines</hi> of <hi>Sighs;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For <hi>Sighs</hi> indeed, altho' no lowder,</l>
                  <l>Are the Diſcharge of <hi>Love's White-pow-der;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And therefore 'tis they ſeldom fail,</l>
                  <l>To blow up <hi>Petticoats</hi> full well:</l>
                  <l>But if ſo fortify'd ſhe prove,</l>
                  <l>To baffle all the <hi>Aſſaults</hi> of <hi>Love;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, on ſtrict <hi>Scrutiny,</hi> you are</l>
                  <l>Oblig'd in <hi>Honour</hi> to deſpair;</l>
                  <l>He's deepeſt read in all thoſe <hi>Laws,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That relate neareſt to your <hi>Cauſe;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Can tell you whether, ſoon as known,</l>
                  <l>'Twere properer to Hang or Drown;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="164" facs="tcp:175034:90"/>
Inſtruct you too what Streams or Boughs,</l>
                  <l>It were convenient you ſhou'd chuſe,</l>
                  <l>What Art is requiſite, what Care</l>
                  <l>To plunge, or ſwing with moving Air;</l>
                  <l>What Rules are order'd by Romance,</l>
                  <l>And which are <hi>A la mode de France:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For theſe things must be nicely done,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe the Glory of 'em's gone;</l>
                  <l>By one Miſtake more Honour's lost,</l>
                  <l>Than being beaten from your Post.</l>
                  <l>I paſs by <hi>S—tle, D—rs, A—es,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For Doggrel celebrated Names;</l>
                  <l>With Authors of ſubſtantial <hi>Proſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That dreſs like <hi>Wits,</hi> and write like <hi>Beaux.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, to return to Application,</l>
                  <l>That is, to Self-juſtification;</l>
                  <l>From citing Verſe-wrights of great Name,</l>
                  <l>That oft fill every Mouth of <hi>Fame,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Render'd by her ſo neceſſary,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Grocer, Cook, Apothecary;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In doing which, my ſole Intent</l>
                  <l>Was meerly to ſhew Precedent,</l>
                  <l>And prove, that fine things may be writ,</l>
                  <l>With very little, or no <hi>Wit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For <hi>Wit</hi> (ſome Authors do maintain)</l>
                  <l>Is but a <hi>Fungus</hi> of the <hi>Brain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Off-ſpring of ſuperfluous Thought,</l>
                  <l>By too luxuriant <hi>Fancy</hi> wrought;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="165" facs="tcp:175034:90"/>
A haſty and abortive Birth,</l>
                  <l>Like that of over-teeming Earth,</l>
                  <l>Which doth to thouſand Figures vary,</l>
                  <l>And therefore not held ſalutary;</l>
                  <l>And tho' for wanton Palates drest,</l>
                  <l>Counted uneaſie to digest;</l>
                  <l>And then too, must be taken young,</l>
                  <l>Before its Venom grow too ſtrong:</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Wit</hi>'s anomalous and rude,</l>
                  <l>Of ill digeſtion, and crude,</l>
                  <l>Till after needful Preparation,</l>
                  <l>With wholeſom Picle of Diſcretion;</l>
                  <l>And, where it is of conſtant uſe,</l>
                  <l>Does Surfeits in the Mind produce;</l>
                  <l>Breeds ſtrange Diſeaſes in the Purſe,</l>
                  <l>And is its own Admirer's Curſe:</l>
                  <l>They therefore Pardon ſurely merit,</l>
                  <l>Who in their Writings do forbear it;</l>
                  <l>And rather chuſe to feed in quiet,</l>
                  <l>On homelier, but more whole ſome Diet;</l>
                  <l>From whence, if peccant Vapours breed,</l>
                  <l>Or turgid Flatulence proceed,</l>
                  <l>The only <hi>Symptoms</hi> they produce</l>
                  <l>And Danger's, but a <hi>Crepitus;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which (as we do in Authors read)</l>
                  <l>Springs from the Bowels, not the Head;</l>
                  <l>And, tho' receiv'd with publick ſcorn,</l>
                  <l>Expires as ſoon as it is born:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="166" facs="tcp:175034:91"/>
So Writings, which no Sence affords,</l>
                  <l>Are but a <hi>Crepitus</hi> of Words;</l>
                  <l>And, tho' with windy Lines they ſwell ye,</l>
                  <l>Riſe from a <hi>Vacuum</hi> in the Belly;</l>
                  <l>In which no Meaning's to be found,</l>
                  <l>Or any Scope, beſide the Sound.</l>
                  <l>But, Sir, I have almost forgot,</l>
                  <l>What I intended to have wrote,</l>
                  <l>And my first Subject worſe neglect,</l>
                  <l>Than modern <hi>Pulpiteer</hi> his Text,</l>
                  <l>Who take the freedom to digreſs,</l>
                  <l>And vary Subjects as they pleaſe;</l>
                  <l>While with <hi>Rhetorical Harangue,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And Voice tun'd to Religious Twang,</l>
                  <l>He treats all thoſe that come to hear it,</l>
                  <l>With choicest Gifts of pureſt Spirit:</l>
                  <l>Where Pious Folks convene, drawn thither</l>
                  <l>By th' help of ſtiff erected Leather;</l>
                  <l>With Dreſſes, Faces, Mien, and Air,</l>
                  <l>Screw'd up to Piety and Pray'r;</l>
                  <l>Where Holy Man in all he ſaith,</l>
                  <l>Lays Salt of Grace on Tails of Faith;</l>
                  <l>Where Saints are ſous'd in Goſpel-pickle,</l>
                  <l>By Moderns ſtyl'd, <hi>A Conventicle.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:175034:91"/>
            <head>LETTERS OF LOVE <hi>and</hi> GALLANTRY.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>To</hi> Eugenia.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THO' it be not a full Week ſince I received the Honour of my dear <hi>Eugenia</hi>'s Letter, yet it has been long enough for me to wiſh a thouſand times I were Left-handed; ſince, by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky <hi>Sprain</hi> in my Right-hand, I've been forced to omit the Duty theſe three Poſts. My Building is near finiſh'd; and when it is ſo, I hope my dear <hi>Euge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> will be ſo kind to her conſtant <hi>Slave,</hi> to furniſh my new Houſe with an <hi>Enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging</hi> new Miſtreſs; if not for my ſake, at leaſt for her own; ſince I vow I ſhall
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:175034:92"/>
come into—with a moſt fierce De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign on <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Matrimony:</hi> And <hi>Love,</hi> you know, is a Spirit, that when once a Woman has conjur'd up, ſhe muſt find it ſome Employment, or elſe 'twill tear the Charming Sorcereſs her ſelf to pieces. Therefore, fair Widow, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware!</p>
               <p>If my Hand were not ſtill in great Pain, I'd give you a thouſand Thanks for your dear Letter; and, perhaps, pick as many Quarrels with you about it: But Heaven forgive you your want of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, when you think I could write the ſame things to my Grand-mother, I do to <hi>Eugenia;</hi> when my Conſcience can't reproach me with thinking the youngeſt of your Sex charming enough to extort one of this kind from me, excepting your ſelf. Nor is it, <hi>Madam,</hi> the eaſieſt thing in the World to feign a Paſſion, ſay things of that Force and Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or act an abſent <hi>Lover</hi> for ſo many Years together, as I have been <hi>Eugenia</hi>'s Votary. I'm ſure the whole <hi>Legend</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> can't furniſh you with one Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of ſo conſtant an <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> as I have been, if I muſt needs be ſo. Therefore,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:175034:92"/>
if I can't convince you of my Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and by that plead a Merit to your <hi>Love;</hi> yet let the Novelty of the thing, at leaſt, move your Pity, when you think what Pains I've taken (ſince all that comes not Naturally is ſo) to ſay ſo many kind, tender, and paſſionate things of one I have no concern for. Think whether it be not almoſt equally difficult to write paſſionately to one I am not really in love with, and to paint a Sound. Who can act Hunger without an Appetite? Or long Scene of Fury and Anger, without being pefectly heated.</p>
               <p>But if you are ſo ſevere, to think that my firſt Pretences were all Fiction; yet, <hi>Madam,</hi> pray, conſider that Liars often tell Stories of their own Invention ſo long, till at laſt they themſelves believe 'em true: And, as the <hi>Roman</hi> in <hi>Martial</hi> counterfeited the <hi>Gout,</hi> till he had it in earneſt; ſo, ſuppoſing my Vows at firſt but feign'd, they muſt by this time be ripen'd into <hi>Truth</hi> by your Influence, (like the <hi>Dew drops</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> into <hi>Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Stones</hi> by the heat of the <hi>Eaſtern Sun)</hi> and ſo become Sacred, as all things ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed to you muſt be, <hi>Madam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:175034:93"/>
But if I lov'd not <hi>Eugenia</hi> with the greateſt and moſt ſincere Paſſion that ever Man lov'd a Woman, I know not what Reaſon, what Intereſt, or what Deſign I cou'd have to pretend it, ſince I'm not ſo vain to expect any other Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of it than her Laughter, and in that my Trouble. However, <hi>Madam,</hi> I have this Satisfaction in my own Mind, that I love the beſt and fineſt of her Sex, (tho' a Mother) who, like a Taper, has not ſuffer'd the leaſt Diminution of her own Luſtre, by the lighting others into the World; but ſtill preſerves her Original Light ſo firmly, as to enſlave all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold her, as well as, <hi>Madam,</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Eternal Slave,
Lysander.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:175034:93"/>
               <head>By the Same.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>NO deſperate Wretch, guilty of the moſt execrable Murders, had ever that Trouble, that Agony of Mind, that I have endur'd ſince the Receipt of Your laſt; in which you diſcovered ſo ſevere and cruel a Reſentment of a Crime I was not guilty of. If I have ever offended You, I ask Your Ladiſhip ten thouſand thouſand Pardons. Ah! <hi>Madam,</hi> if my <hi>Love</hi> were not as laſting as my <hi>Life,</hi> and ſo were as inſeparable as <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body:</hi> Nay, were there any Proſpect, any Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of my ever loving You leſs, I ſhou'd not need to be thus troubleſom to Your Ladiſhip, to beg You not to uſe the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of Your Power over me, to puniſh me for a Crime I was never guilty of: Yet, whether I'm guilty or not, ſo much, ſo extravagantly I love You, that if You yet convict me, I ſhall ſtand condemned even in my own Opinion. Nay, if You, <hi>Madam,</hi> will poſitively accuſe me of all the the Ills in the World, I'll own 'em; for it
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:175034:94"/>
ſhall never be ſaid, That for the ſake of my own Happineſs, Intereſt, or Honour, I ever contradicted the Aſſertion of her, I profeſs'd the greateſt and moſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Paſſion for, that ever unhappy Man experienc'd. But, <hi>Madam,</hi> had I been guilty of any little Error, conſider it as coming from a Man almoſt diſtracted:—<hi>Diſtracted, Madam,</hi> for the Love of you; for I'm ſure I appear ſo to all that viſit me; yet, tho' moſt gueſs the Cauſe, the Perſon is only known to the wounded Heart of,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam, </salute> 
                  <signed>Your Conſtant Slave,
Lysander.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>Ah! <hi>Madam,</hi> don't uſe a Paſſion ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as mine with ſo much Tyranny, ſince the Power you have is but what I give; and it is not generous enough for <hi>Eugenia</hi> to turn againſt its Original, tho' he's incapable of with-holding it.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:175034:94"/>
               <head>By the Same.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>HOw can the Unfortunate <hi>Lyſander</hi> ever hope for his Divine <hi>Eugenia</hi>'s Pardon, thus daily to torment her with his Impertinence, if ſhe were not the beſt, and moſt generous Woman living. As for the Character of a <hi>Beau,</hi> which you're pleas'd to honour me with, I pretty well gueſs whence you had it; a very honeſt good-humour'd Lady as lives, I mean M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>. <hi>S</hi>—, who Din'd with me once at my Lodging, where Night nor Day you were not forgot. I need not tell you, that M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>. <hi>S</hi>—is as good a Woman as lives, ſince all that you recommend muſt be ſo. When<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhe's a mind to oblige me moſt, and render her Houſe moſt agreeable, ſhe tells me, many think her like <hi>Eugenia:</hi> But cou'd ſhe make me believe ſo too, ſhe had done her Buſineſs: For (as I told her) that was the way to make her Houſe my Priſon; for had <hi>Eugenia</hi> been Miſtreſs of it, I cou'd with Pleaſure have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd to it for ever. If you would do an Act of <hi>Charity,</hi> (as Widows, you know,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:175034:95"/>
are good for nothing elſe) you would come up to Town, and help marry me to ſome old rich Woman, that would be ſure to die quickly, in order to the marrying a young one; at leaſt, you wou'd ſpeak a good Word for me to my Lady—, whom, if ever I was to marry, my Lord <hi>D</hi>—ſhould give her, as you ſhould me.</p>
               <p>I hope, fair Widow, after this long Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, your Pen will venture on ſome other Subject beſides Buſineſs. If your Letters were ſometimes daſh'd with <hi>Love, &amp;c.</hi> 'twere but a Venial Sin, and what I week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pardon to ſome young Women in the <hi>Mal,</hi> of your Acquaintance; from whom, by my Soul, I've as good Letters, as thoſe celebrated Nuns Letters. My two Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes <hi>Valeria</hi> and <hi>Belinda,</hi> I ſerve under the Name of <hi>Polydorus;</hi> but would be ten times more proud and happy to ſerve your Ladiſhip under any Title or Name, whereby I might merit the Character ſo long ſince engraven in the Heart of,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute> 
                  <signed> Your Humble Slave,
Lysander.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:175034:95"/>
               <head>By the Same.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THis Day's Poſt made me the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieſt Man living, in receiving the Honour of a moſt obliging Letter from my dear <hi>Eugenia,</hi> who can never do any thing that is otherwiſe: However, did I not know your Modeſty was ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream, as to look on the ſmalleſt <hi>Enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miums</hi> as Flatteries, tho' your real Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit keeps the greateſt from being ſo: I confeſs it would be a real Trouble to me, that one, whom I ſo cordially honour, ſhou'd miſ-interpret the unfeign'd Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of my Soul, for Compliments. A Devotion, ſo juſtly grounded on Merit, can never be judg'd counterfeit; for the Glory of the Sun, and the Benefits Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind reap'd from his Beams, were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd as ſufficient Arguments, to juſtifie the <hi>Perſians</hi> Adoration of him. Your generous Invitation of me into—is ſo much to my own Advantage, that a dying Man, when he knows there are but two ways to go, wou'd ſooner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:175034:96"/>
an Invitation to Heaven. I beg you, <hi>Madam,</hi> make an Experiment of your Dominion over me, in impoſing ſome Commands, that you judge the moſt Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous, and that may appear as Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult as this is pleaſing. I wou'd fain ſee how Ill-natur'd you can be, as well as give a Proof of my Pride, in obeying you. As for <hi>London,</hi> every thing that is worth a Viſit there, will be gone the very Minute you leave it: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, till your Return, I declare for an Abdication of it, and will here, like an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <hi>Timon</hi> of <hi>Athens,</hi> live retir'd, and in hatred of all Mankind, for your Sexes ſake.</p>
               <p>But now, Fair Widow, you muſt give me my Revenge, and let me give you Advice, in Return of what I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd from you, tho' mine, I promiſe you, ſhall be more conſcionable than yours was: For you adviſe me to marry an Old Woman (bleſs'd, for ought I know, with a ſtinking Breath, Rheu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiſms, Coughs, Catarrhs, falſe Teeth, and the other damn'd Accompliſhments, which may entitle her to the honourable Appellation of <hi>Venerable:)</hi> But I am,
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:175034:96"/>
                  <hi>Madam,</hi> better natur'd in my choice for your Ladiſhip, and recommend to you a young Man that prefers the Widow to the Jointure, and leaves all but the Treaſure of her Heart to others; one who wou'd be confin'd to a Deſart (if to be in Heaven can be a Confinement) with her, where the perpetual Buſineſs of his Life ſhou'd be Immortal <hi>Love;</hi> and I ſwear, he that would not do all this, and ten thouſand times more, is not worthy of her. Such a one, <hi>Madam,</hi> I chuſe for you, and if that will not pleaſe, forbear Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock for ever, as I will do, rather than take up with that reverend piece of Antiquity you mention. In the mean time, the only Alms I beg, is, your Pity and Pardon for,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute> 
                  <signed>Your most ſincere, oblig'd humble Slave,
Lysander.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="178" facs="tcp:175034:97"/>
               <head>By the Same.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>TO expreſs the real Senſe I have of all the Noble Favours conferr'd on me at your Houſe, during the long Perſecution I gave you there, were as impoſſible as to give your Ladiſhip a full and perfect Character of the Pangs and Tortures of Mind I have been under, ever ſince my Departure from the Divine <hi>Eugenia,</hi> whoſe <hi>Idea</hi> perpetually ſwims before my Sight in all Companies and Places. <hi>Madam,</hi> I'm ſenſible, I have ten thouſand Pardons to ask for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagance of my Paſſion in the Preſence of the Divine <hi>Eugenia:</hi> But I can appeal to Heaven and my own Conſcience, that never any Prophane Thought enter'd my Breaſt, reflecting on the Divinity I with ſo unfeign'd a Zeal adore, ſince no Man living has that Sacred Opinion of the exalted Honour, Vertue, Wit and Beauty of any Woman, that I have of my too Dear and Deſtructive <hi>Eugenia.</hi>
                  <pb n="179" facs="tcp:175034:97"/>
Your Caution, <hi>Madam,</hi> of the <hi>Bath,</hi> might have been neceſſary to one that lov'd leſs than I do; the Variety of Company that Place now affords, with its other divert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Amuſements, might have ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence over an <hi>Amorous Friend,</hi> or <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Lover:</hi> But as my Paſſion is propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable to the Object, ſo nothing on Earth is Diverſion or Pleaſure to me, but the Thoughts of Her I love. I can be alone ev'n in a Crowd, and therefore make it my endeavour <hi>to avoid ſo trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome a ſolitude.</hi> Good <hi>GOD, Madam!</hi> What is there I can do to ſhew how miſerable I am for your ſake? 'Tis true, <hi>Madam,</hi> my Miſery derives it ſelf partly from my Unworthineſs; But ah! more! much more, from your not knowing what it is to love: For who can have a real Senſe of another's Pain, but they who have felt the ſame? How can the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate <hi>Lyſander</hi> ever hope for one kind Thought from his Ador'd <hi>Eugenia,</hi> while her Heart's not touch'd with his Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, nay, fortify'd againſt Compaſſion, by her being ſurrounded by none but his Enemies? Some may think it a <hi>Reflection on their Friends, to be refus'd, if you ſhou'd honour any other with your Favour, but
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:175034:98"/>
them:</hi> And <hi>others think it impoſſible, that a Paſſion for</hi> Eugenia <hi>ſhou'd last an Age, ſince they never had Merit enough to procure an Hour's Love for Themſelves.</hi> Thus, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> between the Vanity of the Old, and the Ignorance, Envy, and impotent Charms of the Young, I may well expect to be ſacrific'd; but, however, I ſhall have the ſatisfaction of being diſtinguiſh'd from the reſt of your Adorers, by being at leaſt your Martyr,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Lysander.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lyſander,</hi> Madam, can never baniſh nor leſſen that Paſſion you mention for <hi>Eugenia,</hi> yet my Eſteem of Friendſhip is ſo great, that if I cou'd preſent you with a Pillow of <hi>Love,</hi> to repoſe your charming Head on, it ſhou'd be ſtuff'd with <hi>Friendſhip;</hi> if with a Landskip of <hi>Love,</hi> the Shadows ſhou'd be <hi>Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;</hi> if with an Embroidery, the Ground ſhou'd be <hi>Friendſhip;</hi> tho' in the Gardens of <hi>Venus</hi> I can never allow Friendſhip to
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:175034:98"/>
be more than a <hi>Winter-fruit,</hi> which, when the Delicacies of the <hi>Summer</hi> is over, may be comfortable enough to the Reverend Old Couple, ſitting by a Fire-ſide, in a long <hi>Winter</hi>'s Night, ev'n as good as roaſted Apples.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:175034:99"/>
               <head>LYSANDER <hi>to</hi> EUGENIA, <hi>whom he had deſir'd to write Letters enough to him to make him a</hi> Shroud.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THis Day was I Bleſt with a Letter from <hi>Eugenia,</hi> which comes far ſhort of finiſhing my Shroud; a Ream, at leaſt, will modeſtly ſuffice to keep even Death from bluſhing at himſelf; and then, for Warmth, another Ream, I'm ſure, you'll not deny, when cold <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſander</hi> begs</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>That Heat and Flame which now your Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty gives,</l>
                  <l>Can then alone be by your Wit ſupply'd.</l>
                  <l>Entomb'd in Amber, Bees may boast their turn;</l>
                  <l>And wrapt in Flames, let pious Martyrs burn.</l>
                  <l>Stretch'd in your Letter, Death will be my Triumph.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="183" facs="tcp:175034:99"/>
Embalm'd in <hi>Senſe,</hi> who would not wiſh to die?</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Senſe</hi> that comes from ſo Divine a Hand?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aegyptian Mummies</hi> periſh and decay;</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Shrouds,</hi> like mine, will <hi>Time</hi> it ſelf out-live,</l>
                  <l>Wear out his Scythe, and every fleeting Sand.</l>
                  <l>One Dram of Body cannot here be lost:</l>
                  <l>But, like a Summer-ſute, laid ſafely by;</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Spring</hi> appears, are fit to wear again.</l>
                  <l>So true a <hi>Reſurrection</hi> will be rare;</l>
                  <l>The ſelf-ſame <hi>Body,</hi> with the ſelf-ſame <hi>Soul.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who then can doubt but the ſame Paſſions too?</l>
                  <l>The ſame my <hi>Love,</hi> the ſame my <hi>Miſtreſs YOU.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Madam,</hi> tho' I deſign'd theſe Thoughts in down-right Proſe, yet in the Ardor of writing they run into Blank Verſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I would or no. I hope your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip receiv'd my laſt Godly Letter, by which, you may perceive, I can be Deviliſhly Devout upon Occaſion. The Truth on't is, I have often wondred, <hi>Why all the Young Fellows of the Town ſet up for</hi> Atheiſm, <hi>ſince they can be ſo much more conveniently lewd under the Maſque
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:175034:100"/>
of</hi> Religion. If <hi>Belinda,</hi> in the Letters I've communicated to your Ladiſhip, has behav'd her ſelf in any kind diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to her Sex, let me know it, and I'll engage ſhe ſhall mend her Manners for the future. If you don't think ſhe loves enough, ſhe ſhall grow jealous, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpeak well of him her ſelf, nor ſuffer Any-body elſe to ſpeak ill of him, (the ſureſt ſign of Love in the World) Or if you think her too kind to her Lover, ſhe ſhall ſet up for <hi>Religion,</hi> be very Godly, and very Ill-natur'd, rail at <hi>Profaneneſs,</hi> and in a Pious <hi>Chriſtian</hi> way enjoy Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body ſhe likes better.</p>
               <p>Your Ladiſhip is pleaſed to cenſure my <hi>Jealouſie</hi> as incurable: But pray, <hi>Madam,</hi> be pleas'd to conſider, where Men are apt to be jealous out of Fondneſs, as they are often jealous without a Cauſe; ſo they're as often ſatisfy'd without Reaſon. I'm ſurpriz'd at <hi>Eugenia's Apology</hi> for her writing Non-ſenſe, when there's no Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man living, but what might be proud to copy after her: ſo Free, ſo Eaſie, ſo Witty are her Letters: Beſides were it not ſo, as Mr. <hi>Congreve</hi> has it, there would be more Eloquence in your falſe-ſpelt Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſcription,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:175034:100"/>
than in all <hi>Tully</hi>'s and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes</hi> his Orations, to me, <hi>Madam,</hi> who am</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your most conſtant and faithful Humble Servant.
LYSANDER.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="186" facs="tcp:175034:101"/>
               <head>By the Same.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>TEN Thouſand Thanks to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Eugenia</hi> for this Morning's Bleſſing of a Letter, full of the Charms of her that ſent 'em; full of Honour, Wit, and Good-humour: nay, more than <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> cou'd ſpare to you, without form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Maſs of Fools at the ſame time to retrieve the Expence.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>On You the Image of Himſelf he ſtamp'd,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And every part He most Divinely hit;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Your Eyes His Glory, and his Power Your Wit.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Pardon me, <hi>Madam,</hi> for this Start of <hi>Poetry;</hi> for tho' I have no Skill in it, I have yet a double Pretence to the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, both as <hi>Lover</hi> and <hi>Fidler.</hi> Beſides, your Ladiſhip's <hi>Poetry</hi> (the fineſt, as well as the eaſieſt in the World) provoked me to return the Debt; not that I preſum'd, <hi>Madam,</hi> that I could pay you in the ſame <hi>Sterling,</hi> but in ſuch <hi>Birmigham</hi> Coin as I can compaſs. Tho'I'm perſwaded there's
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:175034:101"/>
ſo much of the <hi>Poetick</hi> Fire in yours, that more of them would do with me, what the <hi>Hermetick</hi> Fire does with Metals, tranſmute me into true Standard Gold, and make my <hi>Poetry</hi> as engaging as your Charms, that inſpire me with a Love as laſting as your Slave.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>LYSANDER.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="188" facs="tcp:175034:102"/>
               <head>By the Same.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>HOw long muſt I Write and Sigh in vain? Not one line, not one word, to the Man that loves and adores you next Heaven? Why ſhou'd I grieve for her, that hates me? Or write to her, that ſcorns to anſwer me? That, after all her Profeſſions of Friendſhip to her <hi>Lyſander,</hi> forgets him, now <hi>Alphonſo</hi>'s in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try? As if ſhe meaſur'd <hi>Love</hi> by the proud weight of the Perſon, and not of the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; that, after ſo many Years of ſincere Love, after the faithful Service of the old Patriarch's waiting, turns him off, for a New-comer; as if you did it to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil what is written, in giving the Laborer that came the laſt Hour, the ſame wages with him that came the firſt. For my part, <hi>Madam,</hi> I never knew what it was to compound a Debt with a Miſtreſs; and for Love to dwindle into Friendſhip, is not ſo much as to pay Twelve-pence in the Pound: No, <hi>Madam,</hi> Time has not made me ſuch a Bankrupt, and I've an
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:175034:102"/>
honeſter Principle, than to break, when I'm ſo well ſtock'd with Love.</p>
               <p>This is the third Letter, <hi>Madam,</hi> I've ſent you, ſince I've heard from you: Town and Country are equally uneaſie to me, when I hear not from <hi>Eugenia,</hi> when I'm depriv'd from the fight of her: But I ſhall find more frequent Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of ſeeing you, deſigning, <hi>Don Quixot</hi> like, with my <hi>Sanca Panca,</hi> to travel about in purſuit of Adventures, that may bring me to <hi>Eugenia,</hi> or Death.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>LYSANDER.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="190" facs="tcp:175034:103"/>
               <head>By the Same.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THe Letter this Day's Poſt brought me, wou'd have ſurpriz'd any one but me, whom you have ſo inur'd to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, that I look on my ordinary Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice as an Obligation, having had the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to have receiv'd an hundred times more than this from your Ladiſhip. I was telling my Friend, laſt Night, That I had read ſeveral <hi>Encomiums</hi> on the <hi>Gout, Feaver, Plague, &amp;c.</hi> written by witty Men; to which I thought the Praiſe of Women might be annex'd; but little expected ſo home and ſerious a Proof of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs of my Jeſt. Faith, <hi>Madam,</hi> you have ſuch ill ſucceſs in the Counſels of your <hi>Allies,</hi> that I wou'd, were I you, for once, try my own. You ſeldom find Confederates ſucceſsful againſt a ſingle Foe, who has No-body to conſult but his own Will and Pleaſure. We take the Field when we will; march when we will, and do what we will, while the
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:175034:103"/>
different Powers, that make up a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy, draw each a ſeveral way, and by the ſlowneſs of their Reſolutions, loſe the Opportunity of their Fortune. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, <hi>Madam,</hi> 'tis not your Severity can deſtroy my Paſſion, I muſt and will be yours one way or other; no Reſolutions, no Unkindneſs can ever alter me. My Love, <hi>Eugenia,</hi> is like the Appearance of a <hi>Phoenix,</hi> not to be ſeen, but once in a thouſand Years: My Tongue never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes what my Heart is not poſſeſs'd with. No, no, <hi>Madam, Love</hi> is too noble a Paſſion to be fool'd with. Your laying Addreſſes elſewhere to my Charge, is Obliging; for nothing cou'd pleaſe me more than your Jealouſie; yet, let me aſſure the Divine <hi>Eugenia,</hi> that 'tis no eaſie matter for a Man bred up in an Adoration, for twice ſeven Years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to change his Devotion; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever little Excurſions I might make, all this time, 'twas but to pray to others for your ſake. And thus you ſee, <hi>Madam,</hi> how little Pains I ſpare to win the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of the World, <hi>Your Love.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="192" facs="tcp:175034:104"/>
                  <l>If only to be happy, be to live,</l>
                  <l>As all the Brave and Generous believe;</l>
                  <l>You'll in one Year within my Arms live more,</l>
                  <l>Than all the taſtleſs Years you liv'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore;</l>
                  <l>One blaſt of Breath will never then be loſt,</l>
                  <l>But Lip from Lip, each others Soul be toſt:</l>
                  <l>Thus by a new <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> we'll prove,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Perpetual Motion,</hi> and <hi>Eternal Love.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Deareſt <hi>Eugenia,</hi> Adieu; never again be ſo cruel to throw away any more fruitleſs Advice, about changing my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs; for 'tis impoſſible I ſhou'd ever be other than</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Conſtant Slave,
LYSANDER.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="193" facs="tcp:175034:104"/>
               <head>To my Lady—</head>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Richmond, <date>March 4.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>HEre I am at laſt, <hi>Madam,</hi> to ſhew you the force of my Reſolution; and here I poſitively ſtay till <hi>Saturday:</hi> Nay, I don't know but I may ſtretch it to <hi>Monday:</hi> For if once I get into Town again, the <hi>Lord</hi> knows when I get out on't; and, I'm afraid, I ſhan't ſuck ſo much of this Heavenly Air in two Days, as I may poſſibly ſtand in need of: For I don't find my Legs of half that Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to me they us'd to be. Half a Mile up Hill makes 'em grumble curſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. I have a ſcoundrel pair of Bellows too, that puff and blow, and make a dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Splutter. In ſhort, the preſent Scituation of my Affairs are ſuch, I can give but a very ſcurvy Account of the perteſt part about me.</p>
               <p>That things may mend, is my Hope and my Comfort, <hi>Madam;</hi> for were they to hang long thus, 'twere no great Loſs, either to my ſelf, or other Folks, if I were hang'd too. Poſſibly your Ladiſhip may
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:175034:105"/>
be of my Opinion; if you are, pray, toſs me a ſhort Prayer into your <hi>Lent-devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> for my Re-eſtabliſhment. I would have begg'd one from a <hi>Catholick</hi> Lady in the next Room, who is puzzling over a long lewd Account ſhe's to make up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Eaſter;</hi> but ſhe's ſo taken up with her Sins and her <hi>Crucifix,</hi> ſhe cares not if I were damn'd. If I am not, I hope ſhe will; for ſhe's ſo ugly, I deſire I may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be in the ſame place with her again.</p>
               <closer/>
               <postscript>
                  <p>The Penny-poſt, <hi>Madam,</hi> is to hand this to the Town's-end, and he's juſt ſtarting: So, if my Letter's too ſhort, 'tis he's the Puppy-dog this time, not I.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="195" facs="tcp:175034:105"/>
               <head>To Mr.—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Honeſt DICK,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have not only heard of, but born a part in ſome of your Frolicks; yet never obſerved any ſo extravagant, as gave me reaſon to apprehend you wou'd ever be ſo mad as to marry. Sure the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is in thee, or her; for without <hi>Faſcina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> this Miracle could never be wrought? To be very ſick of <hi>Love</hi> is no wonder, but that can't laſt long; the raging <hi>Feaver</hi> muſt paſs, or kill. Your <hi>Fate</hi> is ſoon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd; a few Days bring it to its <hi>Criſis:</hi> And is it not better dying quietly in your own Sheets, than in a whining Wife's Arms? You can never live in Charity with her ten Days together, unleſs you are a ſtricter <hi>Chriſtian</hi> than I take you, or think it poſſible for one of Nineteen to be. Experience, dear-bought Experience has convinc'd me, that the Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Women conſiſts more in our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricious Humours, and the Senſe of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety, than any intrinſick Goodneſs, not very common to their Sex. The Novelty may pleaſe, 'tis true; but after the firſt
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:175034:106"/>
Week's Enjoyment, a Wife is eternally the ſame: the Ruine of your Eſtate, and the Diſquiet of your Bed. If ſhe live three Years, ſhe'll ſpend more than her Fortune in Cloaths. If ſhe bring you any Children, theſe are ſo many freſh Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions to your Misfortunes, creating Torments if they live, and Grief if they die. Which of thy Sins, <hi>Dick,</hi> has been ſo black in it ſelf, or ſo heinous in its cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; ſo frequently repeated, or ſo long unrepented of, as to deſerve ſo heavy, ſo laſting a Damnation? You that cou'd never like a Woman above a Week, and chang'd your Miſtreſſes faſter than they did their Lodgings: How, alas! do you think it poſſible not to be miſerable under this Pagan Yoak? Tho' I don't pretend to the Spirit of Prophecy, yet I dare engage you'd give five times her E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, within the Year, to be at Liberty again. Alas! <hi>Dick,</hi> this is not a Confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that ten <hi>Guinea's</hi> will bear you out of; but, what is the greateſt Miſchief, 'twill laſt all your Life. The knowing that we can't alter our Condition, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, is the moſt ſenſible Affliction that can befal us. You know the Story of the Man that broke his Heart with the
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:175034:106"/>
Thoughts of being forbidden to walk without the Walls of a great City, tho' he had never ſtirr'd a Foot out of it before. Beſides, a Husband is the moſt inſipid Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of all Mankind, never pleaſing, and ſeldom pleaſed; tormented in his own Perſon, and more feelingly in that of his Children, who are continually whipp'd and beaten, to be reveng'd of his Unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or to provoke his Anger. Be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber once in thy Life, and renounce the Thoughts of ſo fatal a Conſequence. Why will you affect drinking out of <hi>Horn,</hi> when you have ſo much <hi>Plate?</hi> You had beſt ſhew this to you Fair <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> and demonſtrate the Powers of her Eyes, by reſiſting ſo wholſom and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Advice. If you think fit, do ſo; I had rather loſe her Good-will, than not ſhew my own <hi>Integrity;</hi> and wou'd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe your <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> if I might not ſhew my own.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="198" facs="tcp:175034:107"/>
               <head>To Mrs.—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Lovely Object of my ſolicitous Deſires!</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>TIs impoſſible for me to reſiſt the Charms of your bewitching Face; and if you are not leſs cruel than you're fair, I ſhall be eternally miſerable. Heaven knows with what an unuſual throbbing my Heart was ſeiz'd, when firſt I ſaw you. And who, indeed, could behold, without a tender Concern, the Beautifulleſt Creature, that Nature ever made, or our Eyes at leaſt beheld? And from whence cou'd proceed ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable a Diſorder, unleſs from <hi>Love?</hi> It is not ſuperfluous to confeſs a Flame, I cou'd not poſſibly avoid. And what needs there more to convince the World of my Paſſion, than the Aſſurance I had ſeen you? <hi>Love</hi> is ſo Charming in its Birth, that we readily yield to his ſofter Impulſes; but ſo powerful withal, that we as vainly oppoſe them. In your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany conſiſts my Happineſs; and I am wretched, when I am forc'd from your Feet. Could my Dear <hi>Dorinda</hi> know, with what Anguiſh and Horror I paſs
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:175034:107"/>
every tedious Hour away, while at this diſtance from her, ſhe wou'd doubtleſs wiſh my Condition leſs wretched. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Gratitude obliges us to Pity, if we can't redreſs the Miſeries we cauſe. Since this is the only Happineſs I can at preſent enjoy, be ſo indulgent as to permit it: For why ſhou'd you refuſe me a Felicity, that can ſtand you but in Two Pence? If the declaring my Paſſion you imputed to me as a Crime, the Torments it creates me, are a ſufficient Puniſhment, and you are reveng'd of all my Faults in my own Deſpair.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="200" facs="tcp:175034:108"/>
            <head>A <hi>LETTER</hi> of <hi>AENEAS SYLVIUS,</hi> who was afterwards Pope <hi>PIUS</hi> the Second, to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, about a Baſtard-Son, whom he ſent to him.</head>
            <head type="sub">Tranſlated from the <hi>Latin,</hi> by Mr. <hi>T. Brown.</hi>
            </head>
            <bibl>
               <hi>Aeu. Sylv. Oper. p. 510. Edit. Baſil.</hi>
            </bibl>
            <p>YOu ſent me word in your laſt, That you could not tell whether you were to rejoyce, or grieve at the late <hi>Preſent</hi> that <hi>Providence</hi> made me of a Son. For my part, I ſee reaſon enough for the former, but not the leaſt pretence for the latter: For tell me, what prettier Sport is there, than for a Man to beget his own Likeneſs? Or what more refreſhing ſight can there be, on this ſide. Heaven, than to ſee one's Table well ſtock'd with Olive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branches? As for my ſelf, without bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I own to you, That 'tis an unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Pleaſure to me, to find, that I have not beſtow'd my Pains in a barren Soil; and I daily return my Thanks to Heaven, for
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:175034:108"/>
ſending me no <hi>Cloven Preſent,</hi> no whim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering, ſilly Girl; but a fine chopping, luſty Boy, who will help to divert you and ray Mother, with his innocent Prat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Now, Sir, if you took any Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction at my Birth, why ſhou'd not the Cockies or your old Heart dance upon this occaſion; or why ſhou'd you not be as well pleas'd to behold my Picture in a Grand-ſon? But, perhaps, you'll tell me, That your Conſcience is ſome what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie, becauſe the poor Child was begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Sin, and out of the Pale of <hi>Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</hi> If the Shooe pinches you there, I muſt ask you a few Civil Queſtions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we part. Pray, Sir, what Materials was I compos'd of? As I take it, I am not made of Stone, or Iron, or any ſuch unrelenting Ingredients. You begot me true Fleſh and Blood, and, if I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any Crime, in making uſe of my Parts, I'll e'en place it to your Score; for I'll ſwear I had all the peccant Utenſils from you. In the next place, Do but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how it was with your ſelf at my Years: You know well enough, without my refreſhing your Memory for you, that you never lay under the ſcandal of a Fum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler. I am your own lawful Son; no blot
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:175034:109"/>
to your Family, I hope; no <hi>Eunuch,</hi> or any thing like it. Neither am I <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite</hi> enough, to pretend to more Sanctity than the reſt of my Neighbours. I frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly own, I have been a treſpaſſer, a vile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable treſpaſſer in my time; but, to my great Comfort, <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> went the ſame road before me: and, as I am modeſt in my own Nature, a Curſe light on me, if ever I deſire to be thought holier than King <hi>David,</hi> or wiſer than his Son. If 'tis a Sin, it can ſay abundance of ſhrewd things for it ſelf; it can plead An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity and Univerſality, and quotes the <hi>Lord</hi> knows how many Texts out of the New and old Teſtament; and, to deal plainly with you, I don't believe there's one Man between the two Poles, unleſs he has a very ſcurvy confounded Body in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that has not at one time or another been guilty of it in Thought or Deed. This Corruption (if it may be call'd a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption for a Man to imploy his Natural Talent) is of all Countries and Regions: But, under the Roſe, Sir, why ſhou'd <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation</hi> be treated with ſuch ill Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, as generally 'tis; or why ſhou'd our <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> ſo furiouſly condemn it, ſince Nature, that never does any thing in vain,
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:175034:109"/>
has interwoven this Appetite with our very Conſtitutions, and inſpired the whole Creation with an eternal deſire to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue their own Species? But, I ſuppoſe you'll reply, That there are certain limits within which 'tis lawful, and that this Action ought never to be done without the Church's Conſent. Well, for once, let us take it for granted, That as Man ought never to get up and ride, without the Prieſts Benediction: But how does this mend the Matter? Was there never any Sin, do you think, committed within the Matrimonial Sheets? I hope, Old Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, you'll not advance ſuch falſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine as that is. There are fix'd Rules too for our Eating and Drinking; but what Man, in a thouſand, is ſuch a ſlaviſh Coxcomb, as to be confin'd to them? Some Whining-grave Raſcals may tell you, They were never guilty of Sin, and demurely wipe their Mouths after they have ſaid it; but I hate all Lyars, and, ſince I carry Human Infirmities about me, ſcorn to conceal or deny them: So much for this Point. But becauſe you ſeem to diſtruſt, that other People have had a Finger in the Pye, and wou'd fain be ſatisfied whether the Child really be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:175034:110"/>
to me or no: Pray, Sir, be pleas'd to take this ſhort Hiſtory of the whole Affair. I had been <hi>Envoy</hi> at <hi>Strasburg</hi> ſome two Years, and, as it happen'd, had no great Buſineſs upon my Hands, when a Woman, newly arrived from <hi>England,</hi> who had Youth and Beauty enough to pleaſe a nicer Palate than mine, chanced to come to the ſame Inn where I lodged: She ſpoke the <hi>Italian</hi> Tongue perfectly well, and I had a long Converſation with her in that Language, which was ſo much the more entertaining to me, becauſe I ſo little expected to meet one that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>Italian</hi> in thoſe parts of the World. In ſhort, what with her <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Beauty,</hi> ſhe gain'd an abſolute Aſcendant over my Heart; ſo that, as often as I beheld her, I cou'd not help thinking on the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> who, chiefly with the Gaiety and Charms of her Diſcourſe, made ſuch a pair of Aſſes of <hi>Julius Coeſar</hi> and <hi>Mark Antony.</hi> Thought I, to my ſelf, who can blame ſuch an inconſiderable diminutive Fellow as I am, for doing what the moſt Illuſtrious <hi>Heroes</hi> of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity have juſtified by their own Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples? Sometimes I ſupported my ſelf by the Precedent of <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſometimes of
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:175034:110"/>
               <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and ſometimes by famous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church. To make ſhort of my Story, I was paſſionately in love with this <hi>Belle Tramontane,</hi> and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted her with all the <hi>Rhetorick</hi> I was Maſter of. But ſhe, deaf to my Vows and Paſſion, ſlighted all my Proteſtations; ſo that, for three long-liv'd Days, (an Age in the Chronicles of <hi>Love)</hi> I found I had made little or no progreſs in her Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Whether this was the Effect of her <hi>Vertue,</hi> her <hi>Fear,</hi> or <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> I won't be poſitive, but am inclin'd to the latter. For, as it appear'd, ſhe ſtood in ſome awe of the Houſe, from whom ſhe expected cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Kindneſſes.</p>
            <p>The fatal Night now approach'd, and next Morning early ſhe was to purſue her Journey. What <hi>Fears,</hi> what <hi>Apprehenſions</hi> reached my Soul, leaſt the <hi>Quarry</hi> ſhould eſcape me? I threw my ſelf down at her Feet, embraced her Knees, and conjur'd her not to bolt her Door; adding, that in the Silence of the Night I wou'd ſteal to her Chamber, and give her the laſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions, that I was her moſt devoted Vaſſal. She refus'd to comply with my Deſires, ſtood much upon her <hi>Virtue,</hi> and gave me not the leaſt Hopes of ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:175034:111"/>
I ſtill importun'd her upon the ſame Chapter, but ſhe ſtill made me the ſame Anſwer, and inſiſted upon her <hi>Vertue.</hi> Well, when all the Family was gone to Bed, ſaid I to my ſelf, Shall I ſee whether the Lady has done as I deſir'd her, or no? All Women are Riddles; perhaps ſhe has ſince thought better of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and, after all, 'tis no great trouble to try the Experiment. Finding all was huſhed, I groped my way to her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in the dark: The Door was ſhut, but not bolted; ſo in I came, ruſh'd into Bed, and after a little fooliſh ſtruggling, got Poſſeſſion of her Body, the Fruit of which Night's Work was this hopeful Boy. This merry Scene befel me about the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of <hi>February,</hi> and nine Months after, my dear lovely Bedfellow, whoſe Name was <hi>Betty,</hi> dropt in two, and was deliver'd of the above-mention'd Babe. This Account I had from her own Mouth at <hi>Baſil,</hi> where it was my good Fortune to meet with her again. At firſt I thought ſhe had invented this Story, on purpoſe to wheedle a Sum of Money out of me, and gave no great heed to it: But then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, that the Enjoyment of her at <hi>Strasburg</hi> had not coſt me a Farthing,
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:175034:111"/>
but only put me to the Expence of a few fooliſh Oaths, and ſo forth, which are ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily coined in a Lover's Mint, I began to alter my Opinion. She acted before upon a generous Principle of Love, and no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct mercenary Ends; therefore, why ſhould I now ſuſpect her Integrity? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the Time, and all other Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances agreed ſo well, that I could no longer doubt of what ſhe told me, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially it being at a Juncture, when ſhe cou'd expect no great matters from me. Theſe Reaſons induced me to believe, that the Child was begot with the Sweat of my Brows: Therefore, pray Sir, take him into your Family; beſtow ſome little <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> upon the young Rogue, breed him up in the Fear of his Maker, and afford him Shelter in a Garret, till he's big enough to find the way to his Daddy.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
